<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.1">
<book code="1CH" style="id">- unfoldingWord Literal -</book>
<para style="h">First Chronicles</para>
<para style="toc1">First Chronicles</para>
<para style="toc2">First Chronicles</para>
<para style="mt1">First Chronicles</para>
<chapter number="1" style="c" sid="1CH 1"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 1:1"/>Adam, Seth, Enosh,<verse eid="1CH 1:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 1:2"/>Kenan, Mahalalel, Jared,<verse eid="1CH 1:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 1:3"/>Enoch, Methuselah, Lamech,<verse eid="1CH 1:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 1:4"/>Noah, Shem, Ham, and Japheth.<verse eid="1CH 1:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 1:5"/>The sons of Japheth: Gomer, and Magog, and Madai, and Javan, and Tubal, and Meshek, and Tiras.<verse eid="1CH 1:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 1:6"/>And the sons of Gomer: Ashkenaz, and Diphath, and Togarmah.<verse eid="1CH 1:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 1:7"/>And the sons of Javan: Elishah, and Tarshish, the Kittites, and the Rodanites.<verse eid="1CH 1:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 1:8"/>The sons of Ham: Cush and Egypt, Put and Canaan.<verse eid="1CH 1:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 1:9"/>And the sons of Cush: Seba, and Havilah, and Sabta, and Raamah, and Sabteka. And the sons of Raamah: Sheba and Dedan.<verse eid="1CH 1:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 1:10"/>And Cush fathered Nimrod; he began to be a mighty one on the earth.<verse eid="1CH 1:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 1:11"/>And Egypt fathered the Ludites, and the Anamites, and the Lehabites, and the Naphtuhites,<verse eid="1CH 1:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 1:12"/>and the Pathrusites, and the Kasluhites (from whom the Philistines came), and the Caphtorites.<verse eid="1CH 1:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 1:13"/>And Canaan fathered Sidon, his firstborn, and Heth,<verse eid="1CH 1:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 1:14"/>and the Jebusites, and the Amorites, and the Girgashites,<verse eid="1CH 1:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CH 1:15"/>and the Hivites, and the Arkites, and the Sinites,<verse eid="1CH 1:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CH 1:16"/>and the Arvadites, and the Zemarites, and the Hamathites.<verse eid="1CH 1:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CH 1:17"/>The sons of Shem: Elam, and Ashur, and Arpachshad, and Lud, and Aram, and Uz, and Hul, and Gether, and Meshek.<verse eid="1CH 1:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CH 1:18"/>And Arpachshad fathered Shelah, and Shelah fathered Eber.<verse eid="1CH 1:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CH 1:19"/>And to Eber were born two sons. The name of the one, Peleg, for in his days the earth was divided. And the name of his brother, Joktan.<verse eid="1CH 1:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CH 1:20"/>And Joktan fathered Almodad, and Sheleph, and Hazarmaveth, and Jerah,<verse eid="1CH 1:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CH 1:21"/>and Hadoram, and Uzal, and Diklah,<verse eid="1CH 1:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CH 1:22"/>and Obal, and Abimael, and Sheba,<verse eid="1CH 1:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CH 1:23"/>and Ophir, and Havilah, and Jobab; all these, the sons of Joktan.<verse eid="1CH 1:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CH 1:24"/>Shem, Arpachshad, Shelah,<verse eid="1CH 1:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CH 1:25"/>Eber, Peleg, Reu,<verse eid="1CH 1:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CH 1:26"/>Serug, Nahor, Terah,<verse eid="1CH 1:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CH 1:27"/>Abram, that is, Abraham.<verse eid="1CH 1:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CH 1:28"/>The sons of Abraham: Isaac and Ishmael.<verse eid="1CH 1:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CH 1:29"/>These, their generations: the firstborn of Ishmael, Nebaioth; then Kedar, and Adbeel, and Mibsam,<verse eid="1CH 1:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CH 1:30"/>Mishma, and Dumah, Massa, Hadad, and Tema,<verse eid="1CH 1:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CH 1:31"/>Jetur, Naphish, and Kedemah. These were the sons of Ishmael.<verse eid="1CH 1:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CH 1:32"/>And the sons of Keturah, the concubine of Abraham: she bore Zimran, and Jokshan, and Medan, and Midian, and Ishbak, and Shuah. And the sons of Jokshan: Sheba and Dedan.<verse eid="1CH 1:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1CH 1:33"/>And the sons of Midian: Ephah, and Epher, and Hanok, and Abida, and Eldaah; all these, the sons of Keturah.<verse eid="1CH 1:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="1CH 1:34"/>And Abraham fathered Isaac. The sons of Isaac: Esau and Israel.<verse eid="1CH 1:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="1CH 1:35"/>The sons of Esau: Eliphaz, Reuel, and Jeush, and Jalam, and Korah.<verse eid="1CH 1:35"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" sid="1CH 1:36"/>The sons of Eliphaz: Teman, and Omar, Zepho, and Gatam, Kenaz, and Timna, and Amalek.<verse eid="1CH 1:36"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" sid="1CH 1:37"/>The sons of Reuel: Nahath, Zerah, Shammah, and Mizzah.<verse eid="1CH 1:37"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" sid="1CH 1:38"/>And the sons of Seir: Lotan, and Shobal, and Zibeon, and Anah, and Dishon, and Ezer, and Dishan.<verse eid="1CH 1:38"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" sid="1CH 1:39"/>And the sons of Lotan: Hori and Homam. And the sister of Lotan: Timna.<verse eid="1CH 1:39"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" sid="1CH 1:40"/>The sons of Shobal: Alian, and Manahath, and Ebal, Shephi, and Onam. And the sons of Zibeon: Aiah and Anah.<verse eid="1CH 1:40"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v" sid="1CH 1:41"/>The sons of Anah: Dishon. And the sons of Dishon: Hemdan, and Eshban, and Ithran, and Keran.<verse eid="1CH 1:41"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="42" style="v" sid="1CH 1:42"/>The sons of Ezer: Bilhan, and Zaavan, and Akan. The sons of Dishan: Uz and Aran.<verse eid="1CH 1:42"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="43" style="v" sid="1CH 1:43"/>And these, the kings who reigned in the land of Edom before the face of a king reigned over the sons of Israel: Bela, son of Beor. And the name of his city: Dinhabah.<verse eid="1CH 1:43"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="44" style="v" sid="1CH 1:44"/>And Bela died, and Jobab son of Zerah from Bozrah reigned in his place.<verse eid="1CH 1:44"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="45" style="v" sid="1CH 1:45"/>And Jobab died, and Husham from the land of the Temanites reigned in his place.<verse eid="1CH 1:45"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="46" style="v" sid="1CH 1:46"/>And Husham died, and Hadad son of Bedad, who struck down Midian in the field of Moab, reigned in his place. And the name of his city: Avith.<verse eid="1CH 1:46"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="47" style="v" sid="1CH 1:47"/>And Hadad died, and Samlah from Masrekah reigned in his place.<verse eid="1CH 1:47"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="48" style="v" sid="1CH 1:48"/>And Samlah died, and Shaul from Rehoboth of the river reigned in his place.<verse eid="1CH 1:48"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="49" style="v" sid="1CH 1:49"/>And Shaul died, and Baal-Hanan son of Akbor reigned in his place.<verse eid="1CH 1:49"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="50" style="v" sid="1CH 1:50"/>And Baal-Hanan died, and Hadad reigned in his place. And the name of his city: Pai. And the name of his wife: Mehetabel, the daughter of Matred, the daughter of Me-Zahab.<verse eid="1CH 1:50"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="51" style="v" sid="1CH 1:51"/>And Hadad died. And the chiefs of Edom were Chief Timna, Chief Alvah, Chief Jetheth,<verse eid="1CH 1:51"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="52" style="v" sid="1CH 1:52"/>Chief Oholibamah, Chief Elah, Chief Pinon,<verse eid="1CH 1:52"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="53" style="v" sid="1CH 1:53"/>Chief Kenaz, Chief Teman, Chief Mibzar,<verse eid="1CH 1:53"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="54" style="v" sid="1CH 1:54"/>Chief Magdiel, Chief Iram. These, the chiefs of Edom.<verse eid="1CH 1:54"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 1"/>
<chapter number="2" style="c" sid="1CH 2"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 2:1"/>These were the sons of Israel: Reuben, Simeon, Levi, and Judah, Issachar, and Zebulun,<verse eid="1CH 2:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 2:2"/>Dan, Joseph, and Benjamin, Naphtali, Gad, and Asher.<verse eid="1CH 2:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 2:3"/>The sons of Judah: Er, and Onan, and Shelah; three were born to him by Bath-shua the Canaanite. And Er, the firstborn of Judah, was wicked in the eyes of Yahweh, and he killed him.<verse eid="1CH 2:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 2:4"/>And Tamar, his daughter-in-law, bore to him Perez and Zerah. All the sons of Judah, five.<verse eid="1CH 2:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 2:5"/>The sons of Perez: Hezron and Hamul.<verse eid="1CH 2:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 2:6"/>And the sons of Zerah: Zimri, and Ethan, and Heman, and Kalkol, and Dara. All of them, five.<verse eid="1CH 2:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 2:7"/>And the sons of Karmi: Achar, the troubler of Israel who violated the ban.<verse eid="1CH 2:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 2:8"/>And the sons of Ethan: Azariah.<verse eid="1CH 2:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 2:9"/>And the sons of Hezron who were born to him: Jerahmeel, and Ram, and Caleb.<verse eid="1CH 2:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 2:10"/>And Ram fathered Amminadab, and Amminadab fathered Nahshon, leader of the sons of Judah.<verse eid="1CH 2:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 2:11"/>And Nahshon fathered Salmon, and Salmon fathered Boaz.<verse eid="1CH 2:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 2:12"/>And Boaz fathered Obed, and Obed fathered Jesse.<verse eid="1CH 2:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 2:13"/>And Jesse fathered his firstborn, Eliab, and Abinadab the second, and Shimea the third,<verse eid="1CH 2:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 2:14"/>Nethanel the fourth, Raddai the fifth,<verse eid="1CH 2:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CH 2:15"/>Ozem the sixth, David the seventh,<verse eid="1CH 2:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CH 2:16"/>and their sisters: Zeruiah and Abigail. And the sons of Zeruiah: Abishai, and Joab, and Asahel, three.<verse eid="1CH 2:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CH 2:17"/>And Abigail bore Amasa, and the father of Amasa: Jether the Ishmaelite.<verse eid="1CH 2:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CH 2:18"/>And Caleb son of Hezron had children with Azubah, a wife, and with Jerioth. And these, her sons: Jesher, and Shobab, and Ardon.<verse eid="1CH 2:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CH 2:19"/>And Azubah died, and Caleb took for himself Ephrath. And she bore to him Hur.<verse eid="1CH 2:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CH 2:20"/>And Hur fathered Uri, and Uri fathered Bezalel.<verse eid="1CH 2:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CH 2:21"/>And afterward Hezron went into the daughter of Makir the father of Gilead, and he took her. And he was a son of 60 years. And she bore to him Segub.<verse eid="1CH 2:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CH 2:22"/>And Segub fathered Jair. And there were to him 23 cities in the land of Gilead.<verse eid="1CH 2:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CH 2:23"/>And Geshur and Aram took from them Havvoth-Jair, Kenath, and its daughters, 60 towns. All these, the sons of Makir, the father of Gilead.<verse eid="1CH 2:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CH 2:24"/>And after the death of Hezron in Caleb Ephrathah, then the wife of Hezron, Abijah, then she bore to him Ashhur, the father of Tekoa.<verse eid="1CH 2:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CH 2:25"/>And the sons of Jerahmeel, the firstborn of Hezron, were the firstborn Ram, and Bunah, and Oren, and Ozem, Ahijah.<verse eid="1CH 2:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CH 2:26"/>And there was another wife of Jerahmeel, and her name, Atarah. She, the mother of Onam.<verse eid="1CH 2:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CH 2:27"/>And the sons of Ram, the firstborn of Jerahmeel, were Maaz, and Jamin, and Eker.<verse eid="1CH 2:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CH 2:28"/>And the sons of Onam were Shammai and Jada. And the sons of Shammai: Nadab and Abishur.<verse eid="1CH 2:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CH 2:29"/>And the name of the wife of Abishur: Abihail. And she bore to him Ahban and Molid.<verse eid="1CH 2:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CH 2:30"/>And the sons of Nadab: Seled and Appaim. And Seled died without sons.<verse eid="1CH 2:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CH 2:31"/>And the sons of Appaim: Ishi. And the sons of Ishi: Sheshan. And the sons of Sheshan: Ahlai.<verse eid="1CH 2:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CH 2:32"/>And the sons of Jada, the brother of Shammai: Jether and Jonathan. And Jether died without sons.<verse eid="1CH 2:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1CH 2:33"/>And the sons of Jonathan: Peleth and Zaza. These were the sons of Jerahmeel.<verse eid="1CH 2:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="1CH 2:34"/>And there were not to Sheshan sons, but only daughters. And to Sheshan a servant, an Egyptian, and his name, Jarha.<verse eid="1CH 2:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="1CH 2:35"/>And Sheshan gave his daughter to Jarha his servant for a wife. And she bore to him Attai.<verse eid="1CH 2:35"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" sid="1CH 2:36"/>And Attai fathered Nathan, and Nathan fathered Zabad.<verse eid="1CH 2:36"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" sid="1CH 2:37"/>And Zabad fathered Ephlal, and Ephlal fathered Obed.<verse eid="1CH 2:37"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" sid="1CH 2:38"/>And Obed fathered Jehu, and Jehu fathered Azariah.<verse eid="1CH 2:38"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" sid="1CH 2:39"/>And Azariah fathered Helez, and Helez fathered Eleasah.<verse eid="1CH 2:39"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" sid="1CH 2:40"/>And Eleasah fathered Sismai, and Sismai fathered Shallum.<verse eid="1CH 2:40"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v" sid="1CH 2:41"/>And Shallum fathered Jekamiah, and Jekamiah fathered Elishama.<verse eid="1CH 2:41"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="42" style="v" sid="1CH 2:42"/>And the sons of Caleb, the brother of Jerahmeel: Mesha his firstborn; he, the father of Ziph. And the sons of Mareshah, the father of Hebron.<verse eid="1CH 2:42"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="43" style="v" sid="1CH 2:43"/>And the sons of Hebron: Korah, and Tappuah, and Rekem, and Shema.<verse eid="1CH 2:43"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="44" style="v" sid="1CH 2:44"/>And Shema fathered Raham, the father of Jorkeam. And Rekem fathered Shammai.<verse eid="1CH 2:44"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="45" style="v" sid="1CH 2:45"/>And the son of Shammai: Maon, and Maon the father of Beth Zur.<verse eid="1CH 2:45"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="46" style="v" sid="1CH 2:46"/>And Ephah, the concubine of Caleb, bore Haran, and Moza, and Gazez. And Haran fathered Gazez.<verse eid="1CH 2:46"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="47" style="v" sid="1CH 2:47"/>And the sons of Jahdai: Regem, and Jotham, and Geshan, and Pelet, and Ephah, and Shaaph.<verse eid="1CH 2:47"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="48" style="v" sid="1CH 2:48"/>The concubine of Caleb, Maakah, bore Sheber and Tirhanah.<verse eid="1CH 2:48"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="49" style="v" sid="1CH 2:49"/>And she bore Shaaph the father of Madmannah, Sheva the father of Makbenah and the father of Gibea. And the daughter of Caleb, Aksah.<verse eid="1CH 2:49"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="50" style="v" sid="1CH 2:50"/>These were the sons of Caleb. The son of Hur, the firstborn of Ephrathah: Shobal the father of Kiriath Jearim,<verse eid="1CH 2:50"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="51" style="v" sid="1CH 2:51"/>Salma the father of Bethlehem, Hareph the father of Beth Gader.<verse eid="1CH 2:51"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="52" style="v" sid="1CH 2:52"/>And the sons of Shobal, the father of Kiriath Jearim, were Haroeh, half of the Menuhoth,<verse eid="1CH 2:52"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="53" style="v" sid="1CH 2:53"/>and the clans of Kiriath Jearim: the Ithrites, and the Puthites, and the Shumathites, and the Mishraites. From these came the Zorathites and Eshtaolites.<verse eid="1CH 2:53"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="54" style="v" sid="1CH 2:54"/>The sons of Salma: Bethlehem, and the Netophathites, Atroth Beth Joab, and half of the Manahathites, the Zorites.<verse eid="1CH 2:54"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="55" style="v" sid="1CH 2:55"/>And the clans of the scribes lived at Jabez: the Tirathites, the Shimeathites, and the Sucathites. These, the Kenites who came from Hammath, the father of the house of Rekab.<verse eid="1CH 2:55"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 2"/>
<chapter number="3" style="c" sid="1CH 3"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 3:1"/>And these were the sons of David who were born to him in Hebron: the firstborn Amnon by Ahinoam the Jezreelite; the second Daniel by Abigail the Carmelite;<verse eid="1CH 3:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 3:2"/>the third Absalom, the son of Maakah, the daughter of Talmai the king of Geshur; the fourth Adonijah, the son of Haggith;<verse eid="1CH 3:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 3:3"/>the fifth Shephatiah by Abital; the sixth Ithream by Eglah, his wife.<verse eid="1CH 3:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 3:4"/>Six were born to him in Hebron, and he reigned there seven years and six months. Then 33 years he reigned in Jerusalem.<verse eid="1CH 3:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 3:5"/>And these were born to him in Jerusalem: Shimea, and Shobab, and Nathan, and Solomon, four by Bathshua, the daughter of Ammiel;<verse eid="1CH 3:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 3:6"/>and Ibhar, and Elishua, and Eliphelet,<verse eid="1CH 3:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 3:7"/>and Nogah, and Nepheg, and Japhia,<verse eid="1CH 3:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 3:8"/>and Elishama, and Eliada, and Eliphelet; nine.<verse eid="1CH 3:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 3:9"/>All the sons of David, besides sons of concubines, and Tamar their sister.<verse eid="1CH 3:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 3:10"/>And the son of Solomon, Rehoboam; Abijah his son; Asa his son; Jehoshaphat his son;<verse eid="1CH 3:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 3:11"/>Joram his son; Ahaziah his son; Joash his son;<verse eid="1CH 3:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 3:12"/>Amaziah his son; Azariah his son; Jotham his son;<verse eid="1CH 3:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 3:13"/>Ahaz his son; Hezekiah his son; Manasseh his son;<verse eid="1CH 3:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 3:14"/>Amon his son; Josiah his son.<verse eid="1CH 3:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CH 3:15"/>And the sons of Josiah: the firstborn Johanan, the second Jehoiakim, the third Zedekiah, the fourth Shallum.<verse eid="1CH 3:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CH 3:16"/>And the sons of Jehoiakim: Jeconiah his son, Zedekiah his son.<verse eid="1CH 3:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CH 3:17"/>And the sons of Jeconiah, a prisoner: Shealtiel his son,<verse eid="1CH 3:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CH 3:18"/>and Malkiram, and Pedaiah, and Shenazzar, Jekamiah, Hoshama, and Nedabiah.<verse eid="1CH 3:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CH 3:19"/>And the sons of Pedaiah: Zerubbabel and Shimei. And the son of Zerubbabel: Meshullam, and Hananiah, and Shelomith their sister;<verse eid="1CH 3:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CH 3:20"/>and Hashubah, and Ohel, and Berekiah, and Hasadiah, Jushab-Hesed, five.<verse eid="1CH 3:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CH 3:21"/>And the son of Hananiah: Pelatiah and Jeshaiah. The sons of Rephaiah, the sons of Arnan, the sons of Obadiah, the sons of Shekaniah.<verse eid="1CH 3:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CH 3:22"/>And the sons of Shekaniah: Shemaiah. And the sons of Shemaiah: Hattush, and Igal, and Bariah, and Neariah, and Shaphat, six.<verse eid="1CH 3:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CH 3:23"/>And the son of Neariah: Elioenai, and Hizkiah, and Azrikam, three.<verse eid="1CH 3:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CH 3:24"/>And the sons of Elioenai: Hodaviah, and Eliashib, and Pelaiah, and Akkub, and Johanan, and Delaiah, and Anani, seven.<verse eid="1CH 3:24"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 3"/>
<chapter number="4" style="c" sid="1CH 4"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 4:1"/>The sons of Judah: Perez, Hezron, and Karmi, and Hur, and Shobal.<verse eid="1CH 4:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 4:2"/>And Reaiah the son of Shobal fathered Jahath. And Jahath fathered Ahumai and Lahad. These, the clans of the Zorathites.<verse eid="1CH 4:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 4:3"/>And these of the father Etam: Jezreel, and Ishma, and Idbash. And the name of their sister, Hazzelelponi.<verse eid="1CH 4:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 4:4"/>And Penuel, the father of Gedor, and Ezer the father of Hushah; these, the sons of Hur, the firstborn of Ephrathah, the father of Bethlehem.<verse eid="1CH 4:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 4:5"/>And to Ashhur the father of Tekoa were two wives, Helah and Naarah.<verse eid="1CH 4:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 4:6"/>And Naarah bore to him Ahuzzam, and Hepher, and Temeni, and Haahashtari. These, the sons of Naarah.<verse eid="1CH 4:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 4:7"/>And the sons of Helah: Zereth, and Zohar, and Ethnan.<verse eid="1CH 4:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 4:8"/>And Koz fatherered Anub and Hazzobebah. And the clans of Aharhel, the son of Harum.<verse eid="1CH 4:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 4:9"/>And Jabez was respected more than his brothers. And his mother called his name Jabez, saying, “Because I bore in pain.”<verse eid="1CH 4:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 4:10"/>And Jabez called to the God of Israel, saying, “Oh that you would surely bless me, and would enlarge my territory, and your hand would be with me, and you would act not in accordance with harm, so that I might not be in pain!” And God brought about what he asked.<verse eid="1CH 4:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 4:11"/>And Kelub, the brother of Shuhah, fathered Mehir; he, the father of Eshton.<verse eid="1CH 4:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 4:12"/>And Eshton fathered Beth Rapha, and Paseah, and Tehinnah, the father of Ir Nahash. These, the men of Rekah.<verse eid="1CH 4:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 4:13"/>And the sons of Kenaz: Othniel and Seraiah. And the sons of Othniel: Hathath.<verse eid="1CH 4:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 4:14"/>And Meonothai fathered Ophrah, and Seraiah fathered Joab, the father of Ge-Harashim, for craftsmen they were.<verse eid="1CH 4:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CH 4:15"/>And the sons of Caleb, the son of Jephunneh: Iru, Elah, and Naam. And the sons of Elah: Kenaz.<verse eid="1CH 4:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CH 4:16"/>And the sons of Jehallelel: Ziph, and Ziphah, Tiria, and Asarel.<verse eid="1CH 4:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CH 4:17"/>And the sons of Ezrah: Jether, and Mered, and Epher, and Jalon. And she conceived Miriam, and Shammai, and Ishbah, the father of Eshtemoa.<verse eid="1CH 4:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CH 4:18"/>And his Judahite wife bore Jered the father of Gedor, and Heber the father of Soco, and Jekuthiel the father of Zanoah. And these, the sons of Bithiah the daughter of Pharaoh, whom Mered took.<verse eid="1CH 4:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CH 4:19"/>And the sons of the wife of Hodiah, the sister of Naham, the father of Keilah the Garmite, and Eshtemoa the Maakathite.<verse eid="1CH 4:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CH 4:20"/>And the sons of Shimon: Amnon, and Rinnah, Ben-Hanan, and Tilon. And the sons of Ishi: Zoheth and Ben-Zoheth.<verse eid="1CH 4:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CH 4:21"/>The sons of Shelah the son of Judah: Er the father of Lekah, and Laadah the father of Mareshah, and the clans of the house of the service of linen at Beth Ashbea,<verse eid="1CH 4:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CH 4:22"/>and Jokim, and the men of Kozeba, and Joash and Saraph, who ruled in Moab and Jashubi Lehem. And the words are ancient.<verse eid="1CH 4:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CH 4:23"/>These, the potters and inhabitants in Netaim and Gederah. With the king in his work, they lived there.<verse eid="1CH 4:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CH 4:24"/>The sons of Simeon: Nemuel, and Jamin, Jarib, Zerah, Shaul;<verse eid="1CH 4:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CH 4:25"/>Shallum his son, Mibsam his son, Mishma his son.<verse eid="1CH 4:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CH 4:26"/>And the sons of Mishma: Hammuel his son; Zakkur his son; Shimei his son.<verse eid="1CH 4:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CH 4:27"/>And to Shimei, 16 sons and six daughters; but to his brothers, not many sons, and all their clan did not multiply like the sons of Judah.<verse eid="1CH 4:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CH 4:28"/>And they lived in Beersheba, and Moladah, and Hazar Shual,<verse eid="1CH 4:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CH 4:29"/>and in Bilhah, and in Ezem, and in Tolad,<verse eid="1CH 4:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CH 4:30"/>and in Bethuel, and in Hormah, and in Ziklag,<verse eid="1CH 4:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CH 4:31"/>and in Beth Markaboth, and in Hazar Susim, and in Beth Biri, and in Shaaraim. These, their cities until the reign of David.<verse eid="1CH 4:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CH 4:32"/>And their villages: Etam, and Ain, and Rimmon, and Token, and Ashan, five towns,<verse eid="1CH 4:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1CH 4:33"/>and all their villages which are around these towns as far as Baal. These, their settlements, and their genealogy was to them.<verse eid="1CH 4:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="1CH 4:34"/>And Meshobab, and Jamlech, and Joshah the son of Amaziah,<verse eid="1CH 4:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="1CH 4:35"/>and Joel, and Jehu the son of Joshibiah, the son of Seraiah, the son of Asiel,<verse eid="1CH 4:35"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" sid="1CH 4:36"/>and Elioenai, and Jaakobah, and Jeshohaiah, and Asaiah, and Adiel, and Jesimiel, and Benaiah,<verse eid="1CH 4:36"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" sid="1CH 4:37"/>and Ziza the son of Shiphi, the son of Allon, the son of Jedaiah, the son of Shimri, the son of Shemaiah.<verse eid="1CH 4:37"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" sid="1CH 4:38"/>These mentioned by name, leaders in their clans and the house of their fathers broke through into a multitude.<verse eid="1CH 4:38"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" sid="1CH 4:39"/>And they went to the entrance of Gedor, as far as to the east of the valley, to seek pasture for their flock.<verse eid="1CH 4:39"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" sid="1CH 4:40"/>And they found rich and good pasture, and the land was broad of hands, and quiet, and peaceful; for those from Ham had lived there before faces.<verse eid="1CH 4:40"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v" sid="1CH 4:41"/>And these, written by names, came in the days of Hezekiah, the king of Judah, and struck down their tents and the Meunites, who were found there. And they destroyed them completely to this day, and they lived in their place because pasture for their flock was there.<verse eid="1CH 4:41"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="42" style="v" sid="1CH 4:42"/>And from them, from the sons of Simeon, they went to Mount Seir, 500 men, and Pelatiah, and Neariah, and Rephaiah, and Uzziel, the sons of Ishi, their heads.<verse eid="1CH 4:42"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="43" style="v" sid="1CH 4:43"/>And they struck down the rest of the Amalekites who escaped, and they have lived there to this day.<verse eid="1CH 4:43"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 4"/>
<chapter number="5" style="c" sid="1CH 5"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 5:1"/>And the sons of Reuben, the firstborn of Israel; for he was the firstborn, but when he defiled the bed of his father, his birthright was given to the sons of Joseph, the son of Israel, and not recorded according to the birthright,<verse eid="1CH 5:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 5:2"/>though Judah was superior among his brothers, and a leader was from him, but the birthright was to Joseph—<verse eid="1CH 5:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 5:3"/>the sons of Reuben, the firstborn of Israel: Hanok, and Pallu, Hezron, and Karmi.<verse eid="1CH 5:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 5:4"/>The sons of Joel: Shemaiah his son, Gog his son, Shimei his son,<verse eid="1CH 5:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 5:5"/>Micah his son, Reaiah his son, Baal his son,<verse eid="1CH 5:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 5:6"/>Beerah his son, whom Tilgath-Pileser, the king of Assyria, took into exile. He was a leader of the Reubenites.<verse eid="1CH 5:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 5:7"/>And his brothers by his clans in the genealogy of their generations: the head Jeiel, and Zechariah,<verse eid="1CH 5:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 5:8"/>and Bela the son of Azaz, the son of Shema, the son of Joel; he lived in Aroer, and as far as Nebo and Baal Meon,<verse eid="1CH 5:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 5:9"/>and to the east he lived as far as the entrance of the wilderness extending to the Euphrates River; for their livestock multiplied in the land of Gilead.<verse eid="1CH 5:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 5:10"/>And in the days of Saul, they made war with the Hagrites and they fell into their hand. And they lived in their tents over all the face of the east of Gilead.<verse eid="1CH 5:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 5:11"/>And the sons of Gad lived opposite them in the land of Bashan as far as Salekah:<verse eid="1CH 5:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 5:12"/>Joel the head, and Shapham the second, and Janai, and Shaphat in Bashan.<verse eid="1CH 5:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 5:13"/>And their brothers, according to the house of their fathers: Michael, and Meshullam, and Sheba, and Jorai, and Jakan, and Zia, and Eber, seven.<verse eid="1CH 5:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 5:14"/>These, the sons of Abihail, the son of Huri, the son of Jaroah, the son of Gilead, the son of Michael, the son of Jeshisha, the son of Jahdo, the son of Buz.<verse eid="1CH 5:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CH 5:15"/>Ahi, the son of Abdiel, the son of Guni, head of the house of their fathers.<verse eid="1CH 5:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CH 5:16"/>And they lived in Gilead, in Bashan, and in its daughters, and in all the pasturelands of Sharon as far as their borders.<verse eid="1CH 5:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CH 5:17"/>All of them were listed in the genealogies in the days of Jotham, the king of Judah, and in the days of Jeroboam, the king of Israel.<verse eid="1CH 5:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CH 5:18"/>The sons of Reuben, and the Gadites, and the half tribe of Manasseh from sons of strength, men who carried shield and sword, and who bent the bow, and who were trained in battle, 44,760 who went out to war.<verse eid="1CH 5:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CH 5:19"/>And they made war with the Hagrites, and Jetur, and Naphish, and Nodab.<verse eid="1CH 5:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CH 5:20"/>And they were helped against them, and the Hagrites were given into their hand and all who were with them. For they cried out to God in the battle, and he granted their entreaty because they trusted in him.<verse eid="1CH 5:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CH 5:21"/>And they took captive their livestock: their camels 50,000, and sheep 250,000, and donkeys 2,000, and living people 100,000.<verse eid="1CH 5:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CH 5:22"/>For many fell slain because the battle was from God. And they lived in their place until the exile.<verse eid="1CH 5:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CH 5:23"/>And the sons of the half tribe of Manasseh lived in the land from Bashan as far as Baal Hermon and Senir, and Mount Hermon. They multiplied.<verse eid="1CH 5:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CH 5:24"/>And these, the heads of the house of their fathers: even Epher, and Ishi, and Eliel, and Azriel, and Jeremiah, and Hodaviah, and Jahdiel, men mighty of strength, men of names, heads of the house of their fathers.<verse eid="1CH 5:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CH 5:25"/>And they acted faithlessly against the God of their fathers, and they acted like a harlot after the gods of the peoples of the land whom God had destroyed before their faces.<verse eid="1CH 5:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CH 5:26"/>And the God of Israel stirred up the spirit of Pul, the king of Assyria, and the spirit of Tilgath-Pileser, the king of Assyria. And he took them into exile, namely the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and the half tribe of Manasseh. And he brought them to Halah, and Habor, and Hara, and the river of Gozan until this day.<verse eid="1CH 5:26"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 5"/>
<chapter number="6" style="c" sid="1CH 6"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 6:1"/>The sons of Levi: Gershon, Kohath, and Merari.<verse eid="1CH 6:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 6:2"/>And the sons of Kohath: Amram, Izhar, and Hebron, and Uzziel.<verse eid="1CH 6:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 6:3"/>And the sons of Amram: Aaron, and Moses, and Miriam. And the sons of Aaron: Nadab, and Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar.<verse eid="1CH 6:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 6:4"/>Eleazar fathered Phinehas. Phinehas fathered Abishua.<verse eid="1CH 6:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 6:5"/>And Abishua fathered Bukki, and Bukki fathered Uzzi.<verse eid="1CH 6:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 6:6"/>And Uzzi fathered Zerahiah, and Zerahiah fathered Meraioth.<verse eid="1CH 6:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 6:7"/>Meraioth fathered Amariah, and Amariah fathered Ahitub.<verse eid="1CH 6:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 6:8"/>And Ahitub fathered Zadok, and Zadok fathered Ahimaaz.<verse eid="1CH 6:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 6:9"/>And Ahimaaz fathered Azariah, and Azariah fathered Johanan.<verse eid="1CH 6:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 6:10"/>And Johanan fathered Azariah, he who served as priest in the house that Solomon built in Jerusalem.<verse eid="1CH 6:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 6:11"/>And Azariah fathered Amariah, and Amariah fathered Ahitub.<verse eid="1CH 6:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 6:12"/>And Ahitub fathered Zadok, and Zadok fathered Shallum.<verse eid="1CH 6:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 6:13"/>And Shallum fathered Hilkiah, and Hilkiah fathered Azariah.<verse eid="1CH 6:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 6:14"/>And Azariah fathered Seraiah, and Seraiah fathered Jozadak.<verse eid="1CH 6:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CH 6:15"/>And Jozadak went when Yahweh took into exile Judah and Jerusalem in the hand of Nebuchadnezzar.<verse eid="1CH 6:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CH 6:16"/>The sons of Levi: Gershon, Kohath, and Merari.<verse eid="1CH 6:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CH 6:17"/>And these, the names of the sons of Gershon: Libni and Shimei.<verse eid="1CH 6:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CH 6:18"/>And the sons of Kohath: Amram, and Izhar, and Hebron, and Uzziel.<verse eid="1CH 6:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CH 6:19"/>The sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi. And these, the clans of the Levites according to their fathers.<verse eid="1CH 6:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CH 6:20"/>Of Gershom: Libni his son, Jahath his son, Zimmah his son,<verse eid="1CH 6:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CH 6:21"/>Joah his son, Iddo his son, Zerah his son, Jeatherai his son.<verse eid="1CH 6:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CH 6:22"/>The sons of Kohath: Amminadab his son, Korah his son, Assir his son,<verse eid="1CH 6:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CH 6:23"/>Elkanah his son, and Ebiasaph his son, and Assir his son,<verse eid="1CH 6:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CH 6:24"/>Tahath his son, Uriel his son, Uzziah his son, and Shaul his son.<verse eid="1CH 6:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CH 6:25"/>And the sons of Elkanah: Amasai, and Ahimoth,<verse eid="1CH 6:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CH 6:26"/>Elkanah, his son Elkanah, Zophai his son, and Nahath his son,<verse eid="1CH 6:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CH 6:27"/>Eliab his son, Jeroham his son, Elkanah his son.<verse eid="1CH 6:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CH 6:28"/>And the sons of Samuel: the firstborn and the second, Abijah.<verse eid="1CH 6:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CH 6:29"/>The sons of Merari: Mahli, Libni his son, Shimei his son, Uzzah his son,<verse eid="1CH 6:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CH 6:30"/>Shimea his son, Haggiah his son, Asaiah his son,<verse eid="1CH 6:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CH 6:31"/>And these whom David set up over hands of song in the house of Yahweh, after the Box came to rest.<verse eid="1CH 6:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CH 6:32"/>And they were the ones ministering to the face of the tabernacle, the tent of meeting, with song until Solomon built the house of Yahweh in Jerusalem. And they stood according to their judgments over their service.<verse eid="1CH 6:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1CH 6:33"/>And these, the ones standing and their sons. From the sons of the Kohathites: Heman the singer, the son of Joel, the son of Samuel,<verse eid="1CH 6:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="1CH 6:34"/>the son of Elkanah, the son of Jeroham, the son of Eliel, the son of Toah,<verse eid="1CH 6:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="1CH 6:35"/>the son of Zuph, the son of Elkanah, the son of Mahath, the son of Amasai,<verse eid="1CH 6:35"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" sid="1CH 6:36"/>the son of Elkanah, the son of Joel, the son of Azariah, the son of Zephaniah,<verse eid="1CH 6:36"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" sid="1CH 6:37"/>the son of Tahath, the son of Assir, the son of Ebiasaph, the son of Korah,<verse eid="1CH 6:37"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" sid="1CH 6:38"/>the son of Izhar, the son of Kohath, the son of Levi, the son of Israel.<verse eid="1CH 6:38"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" sid="1CH 6:39"/>And his brother Asaph who stood at his right hand, Asaph, the son of Berekiah, the son of Shimea,<verse eid="1CH 6:39"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" sid="1CH 6:40"/>the son of Michael, the son of Baaseiah, the son of Malkijah,<verse eid="1CH 6:40"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v" sid="1CH 6:41"/>the son of Ethni, the son of Zerah, the son of Adaiah,<verse eid="1CH 6:41"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="42" style="v" sid="1CH 6:42"/>the son of Ethan, the son of Zimmah, the son of Shimei,<verse eid="1CH 6:42"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="43" style="v" sid="1CH 6:43"/>the son of Jahath, the son of Gershon, the son of Levi.<verse eid="1CH 6:43"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="44" style="v" sid="1CH 6:44"/>And the sons of Merari, their brothers, on the left: Ethan, the son of Kishi, the son of Abdi, the son of Malluk,<verse eid="1CH 6:44"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="45" style="v" sid="1CH 6:45"/>the son of Hashabiah, the son of Amaziah, the son of Hilkiah,<verse eid="1CH 6:45"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="46" style="v" sid="1CH 6:46"/>the son of Amzi, the son of Bani, the son of Shemer,<verse eid="1CH 6:46"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="47" style="v" sid="1CH 6:47"/>the son of Mahli, the son of Mushi, the son of Merari, the son of Levi.<verse eid="1CH 6:47"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="48" style="v" sid="1CH 6:48"/>And their brothers, the Levites, were set to all the service of the tabernacle of the house of God.<verse eid="1CH 6:48"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="49" style="v" sid="1CH 6:49"/>And Aaron and his sons made sacrifices on the altar of burnt offering and on the altar of incense for all the work of the Holy of Holies and to make atonement for Israel, according to all that Moses the servant of God had commanded.<verse eid="1CH 6:49"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="50" style="v" sid="1CH 6:50"/>And these, the sons of Aaron: Eleazar his son, Phinehas his son, Abishua his son,<verse eid="1CH 6:50"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="51" style="v" sid="1CH 6:51"/>Bukki his son, Uzzi his son, Zerahiah his son,<verse eid="1CH 6:51"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="52" style="v" sid="1CH 6:52"/>Meraioth his son, Amariah his son, Ahitub his son,<verse eid="1CH 6:52"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="53" style="v" sid="1CH 6:53"/>Zadok his son, Ahimaaz his son.<verse eid="1CH 6:53"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="54" style="v" sid="1CH 6:54"/>And these, their dwellings according to their encampments in their borders. To the sons of Aaron, to the clans of the Kohathites, for to them was the lot.<verse eid="1CH 6:54"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="55" style="v" sid="1CH 6:55"/>And they gave to them Hebron in the land of Judah and its surrounding pasturelands,<verse eid="1CH 6:55"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="56" style="v" sid="1CH 6:56"/>but the field of the city and its villages, they gave to Caleb, the son of Jephunneh.<verse eid="1CH 6:56"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="57" style="v" sid="1CH 6:57"/>And to the sons of Aaron they gave the cities of refuge: Hebron, and Libnah and its pasturelands, and Jattir, and Eshtemoa and its pasturelands,<verse eid="1CH 6:57"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="58" style="v" sid="1CH 6:58"/>and Hilez and its pasturelands, Debir and its pasturelands,<verse eid="1CH 6:58"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="59" style="v" sid="1CH 6:59"/>and Ashan and its pasturelands, and Beth Shemesh and its pasturelands.<verse eid="1CH 6:59"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="60" style="v" sid="1CH 6:60"/>And from the tribe of Benjamin: Geba and its pasturelands, and Alemeth and its pasturelands, and Anathoth and its pasturelands. All their cities, 13 cities, among their clans.<verse eid="1CH 6:60"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="61" style="v" sid="1CH 6:61"/>And to the sons of Kohath remaining from the clan of the tribe, from the half tribe, the half of Manasseh, by lot, ten cities.<verse eid="1CH 6:61"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="62" style="v" sid="1CH 6:62"/>And to the sons of Gershom, for their clans, from the tribe of Issachar and from the tribe of Asher and from the tribe of Naphtali and from the tribe of Manasseh in Bashan, 13 cities.<verse eid="1CH 6:62"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="63" style="v" sid="1CH 6:63"/>To the sons of Merari, for their clans, from the tribe of Reuben and from the tribe of Gad and from the tribe of Zebulun, by lot, 12 cities.<verse eid="1CH 6:63"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="64" style="v" sid="1CH 6:64"/>And the sons of Israel gave to the Levites the cities and their pasturelands.<verse eid="1CH 6:64"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="65" style="v" sid="1CH 6:65"/>And they gave by lot from the tribe of the sons of Judah and from the tribe of the sons of Simeon and from the tribe of the sons of Benjamin these cities which they called them by names.<verse eid="1CH 6:65"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="66" style="v" sid="1CH 6:66"/>And from the clans of the sons of Kohath; and there were cities of their territory from the tribe of Ephraim.<verse eid="1CH 6:66"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="67" style="v" sid="1CH 6:67"/>And they gave to them the cities of refuge: Shechem and its pasturelands in the hill country of Ephraim, and Gezer and its pasturelands,<verse eid="1CH 6:67"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="68" style="v" sid="1CH 6:68"/>and Jokmeam and its pasturelands, and Beth Horon and its pasturelands,<verse eid="1CH 6:68"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="69" style="v" sid="1CH 6:69"/>and Aijalon and its pasturelands, and Gath Rimmon and its pasturelands.<verse eid="1CH 6:69"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="70" style="v" sid="1CH 6:70"/>And from the half tribe of Manasseh, Aner and its pasturelands, and Bileam and its pasturelands, for the clans of the sons of Kohath remaining.<verse eid="1CH 6:70"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="71" style="v" sid="1CH 6:71"/>To the sons of Gershon from the clans of the half tribe of Manasseh: Golan in Bashan and its pasturelands, and Ashtaroth and its pasturelands.<verse eid="1CH 6:71"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="72" style="v" sid="1CH 6:72"/>And from the tribe of Issachar: Kedesh and its pasturelands, Daberath and its pasturelands,<verse eid="1CH 6:72"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="73" style="v" sid="1CH 6:73"/>and Ramoth and its pasturelands, and Anem and its pasturelands.<verse eid="1CH 6:73"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="74" style="v" sid="1CH 6:74"/>And from the tribe of Asher: Mashal and its pasturelands, and Abdon and its pasturelands,<verse eid="1CH 6:74"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="75" style="v" sid="1CH 6:75"/>and Hukok and its pasturelands, and Rehob and its pasturelands.<verse eid="1CH 6:75"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="76" style="v" sid="1CH 6:76"/>And from the tribe of Naphtali: Kedesh in Galilee and its pasturelands, and Hammon and its pasturelands, and Kiriathaim and its pasturelands.<verse eid="1CH 6:76"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="77" style="v" sid="1CH 6:77"/>To the sons of Merari remaining: from the tribe of Zebulun, Rimmono and its pasturelands, Tabor and its pasturelands;<verse eid="1CH 6:77"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="78" style="v" sid="1CH 6:78"/>and from beyond the Jordan at Jericho, to the east of the Jordan from the tribe of Reuben, Bezer in the wilderness and its pasturelands, and Jahzah and its pasturelands,<verse eid="1CH 6:78"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="79" style="v" sid="1CH 6:79"/>and Kedemoth and its pasturelands, and Mephaath and its pasturelands.<verse eid="1CH 6:79"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="80" style="v" sid="1CH 6:80"/>And from the tribe of Gad: Ramoth in Gilead and its pasturelands, and Mahanaim and its pasturelands,<verse eid="1CH 6:80"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="81" style="v" sid="1CH 6:81"/>and Heshbon and its pasturelands, and Jazer and its pasturelands.<verse eid="1CH 6:81"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 6"/>
<chapter number="7" style="c" sid="1CH 7"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 7:1"/>And to the sons of Issachar: Tola, and Puah, Jashub, and Shimron, four.<verse eid="1CH 7:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 7:2"/>And the sons of Tola: Uzzi, and Rephaiah, and Jeriel, and Jahmai, and Ibsam, and Samuel, the heads of the house of their fathers, from of Tola, mighty of strength in their generations. Their number in the days of David, 22, 600.<verse eid="1CH 7:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 7:3"/>And the sons of Uzzi: Izrahiah. And the sons of Izrahiah: Michael, and Obadiah, and Joel, and Ishijah, five heads all of them.<verse eid="1CH 7:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 7:4"/>And along with them, by their generations according to the house of their fathers, troops of the army of war, 36,000; for they multiplied wives and sons.<verse eid="1CH 7:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 7:5"/>And their brothers of all the clans of Issachar, mighty of strength, 87,000 listed in their genealogy in all.<verse eid="1CH 7:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 7:6"/>Of Benjamin: Bela, and Beker, and Jediael, three.<verse eid="1CH 7:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 7:7"/>And the sons of Bela: Ezbon, and Uzzi, and Uzziel, and Jerimoth, and Iri, five heads of the house of their fathers, mighty of strength, and listed in their genealogy, 22,034.<verse eid="1CH 7:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 7:8"/>And the sons of Beker: Zemirah, and Joash, and Eliezer, and Elioenai, and Omri, and Jeremoth, and Abijah, and Anathoth, and Alemeth. All these, the sons of Beker,<verse eid="1CH 7:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 7:9"/>and listed in their genealogy, according to their generations, heads of the house of their fathers, mighty of strength, 20,200.<verse eid="1CH 7:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 7:10"/>And the sons of Jediael: Bilhan. And the sons of Bilhan: Jeush, and Benjamin, and Ehud, and Kenaanah, and Zethan, and Tarshish, and Ahishahar.<verse eid="1CH 7:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 7:11"/>All these, the sons of Jediael, according to the heads of their fathers, mighty of strength, 17,200, going out as an army to battle.<verse eid="1CH 7:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 7:12"/>And Shuppim and Huppim, the sons of Ir. Hushim, the sons of Aher.<verse eid="1CH 7:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 7:13"/>The sons of Naphtali: Jahziel, and Guni, and Jezer, and Shillem, the sons of Bilhah.<verse eid="1CH 7:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 7:14"/>The sons of Manasseh: Asriel, whom his Aramean concubine bore. She bore Makir, the father of Gilead.<verse eid="1CH 7:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CH 7:15"/>And Makir took a wife of Huppim and of Shuppim. And the name of his sister, Maakah. And the name of the second, Zelophehad. And to Zelophehad there were daughters.<verse eid="1CH 7:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CH 7:16"/>And Maakah, the wife of Makir, bore a son and she called his name Peresh. And the name of his brother, Sheresh; and his sons, Ulam and Rakem.<verse eid="1CH 7:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CH 7:17"/>And the sons of Ulam: Bedan. These, the sons of Gilead, the son of Makir, the son of Manasseh.<verse eid="1CH 7:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CH 7:18"/>And his sister Hammoleketh bore Ishhod, and Abiezer, and Mahlah.<verse eid="1CH 7:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CH 7:19"/>And the sons of Shemida were Ahian, and Shechem, and Likhi, and Aniam.<verse eid="1CH 7:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CH 7:20"/>And the sons of Ephraim: Shuthelah, and Bered his son, and Tahath his son, and Eleadah his son, and Tahath his son,<verse eid="1CH 7:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CH 7:21"/>and Zabad his son, and Shuthelah his son, and Ezer and Elead. And the men of Gath who were born in the land killed them because they came down to take their livestock.<verse eid="1CH 7:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CH 7:22"/>And Ephraim their father mourned many days, and his brothers came to comfort him.<verse eid="1CH 7:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CH 7:23"/>And he went into his wife. And she conceived. And she bore a son. And he called his name Beriah, because disaster was in his house.<verse eid="1CH 7:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CH 7:24"/>And his daughter, Sheerah, and she built Lower Beth Horon, and the Upper, and Uzzen Sheerah.<verse eid="1CH 7:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CH 7:25"/>And Rephah, his son, and Resheph, and Telah, his son, and Tahan, his son,<verse eid="1CH 7:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CH 7:26"/>Ladan, his son, Ammihud, his son, Elishama, his son,<verse eid="1CH 7:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CH 7:27"/>Non, his son, Joshua, his son.<verse eid="1CH 7:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CH 7:28"/>And their possessions and their dwellings: Bethel and its daughters. And to the east, Naaran. And to the west, Gezer and its daughters, and Shechem and its daughters as far as Ayyah and its daughters.<verse eid="1CH 7:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CH 7:29"/>And on the hands of the sons of Manasseh, Beth Shan and its daughters, Taanach and its daughters, Megiddo and its daughters, Dor and its daughters. In these lived the sons of Joseph, the son of Israel.<verse eid="1CH 7:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CH 7:30"/>The sons of Asher: Imnah, and Ishvah, and Ishvi, and Beriah, and Serah their sister.<verse eid="1CH 7:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CH 7:31"/>And the sons of Beriah: Heber and Malkiel; he, the father of Birzaith.<verse eid="1CH 7:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CH 7:32"/>And Heber fathered Japhlet, and Shomer, and Hotham, and Shua their sister.<verse eid="1CH 7:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1CH 7:33"/>And the sons of Japhlet: Pasak, and Bimhal, and Ashvath. These, the sons of Japhlet.<verse eid="1CH 7:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="1CH 7:34"/>And the sons of Shamer: Ahi, and Rohgah, and Hubbah, and Aram.<verse eid="1CH 7:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="1CH 7:35"/>And the sons of Helem his brother: Zophah, and Imna, and Shelesh, and Amal.<verse eid="1CH 7:35"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" sid="1CH 7:36"/>And the sons of Zophah: Suah, and Harnepher, and Shual, and Beri, and Imrah,<verse eid="1CH 7:36"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" sid="1CH 7:37"/>Bezer, and Hod, and Shamma, and Shilshah, and Ithran, and Beera.<verse eid="1CH 7:37"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" sid="1CH 7:38"/>And the sons of Jether: Jephunneh, and Pispah, and Ara.<verse eid="1CH 7:38"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" sid="1CH 7:39"/>And the sons of Ulla: Arah, and Hanniel, and Rizia.<verse eid="1CH 7:39"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" sid="1CH 7:40"/>All these, the sons of Asher, heads of the house of their fathers, chosen, mighty of strength, heads of the chiefs. And listed in their genealogy in the army for war, their number, 26,000 men.<verse eid="1CH 7:40"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 7"/>
<chapter number="8" style="c" sid="1CH 8"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 8:1"/>And Benjamin fathered Bela his firstborn, Ashbel the second, and Aharah the third,<verse eid="1CH 8:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 8:2"/>Nohah the fourth, and Rapha the fifth.<verse eid="1CH 8:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 8:3"/>And there were sons to Bela: Addar, and Gera, and Abihud,<verse eid="1CH 8:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 8:4"/>and Abishua, and Naaman, and Ahoah,<verse eid="1CH 8:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 8:5"/>and Gera, and Shephuphan, and Huram.<verse eid="1CH 8:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 8:6"/>And these, the sons of Ehud: these, they, heads of fathers, belonging to those dwelling in Geba. And they took them into exile to Manahath:<verse eid="1CH 8:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 8:7"/>and Naaman, and Ahijah, and Gera. He took them into exile, and he fathered Uzzah and Ahihud.<verse eid="1CH 8:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 8:8"/>And Shaharaim fathered in the field of Moab, after he sent them away, Hushim and Baara, his wives.<verse eid="1CH 8:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 8:9"/>And he fathered from Hodesh his wife: Jobab, and Zibia, and Mesha, and Malkam,<verse eid="1CH 8:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 8:10"/>and Jeuz, and Sakia, and Mirmah. These, his sons, heads of fathers.<verse eid="1CH 8:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 8:11"/>And from Hushim he fathered Abitub and Elpaal.<verse eid="1CH 8:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 8:12"/>And the sons of Elpaal: Eber, and Misham, and Shemed, he built Ono and Lod and its daughters;<verse eid="1CH 8:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 8:13"/>and Beriah and Shema. They, heads of the fathers to those living in Aijalon; they caused those living in Gath to flee.<verse eid="1CH 8:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 8:14"/>and Ahio, Shashak, and Jeremoth,<verse eid="1CH 8:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CH 8:15"/>and Zebadiah, and Arad, and Eder,<verse eid="1CH 8:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CH 8:16"/>and Michael, and Ishpah, and Joha, the sons of Beriah.<verse eid="1CH 8:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CH 8:17"/>And Zebadiah, and Meshullam, and Hizki, and Heber,<verse eid="1CH 8:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CH 8:18"/>and Ishmerai, and Izliah, and Jobab, the sons of Elpaal.<verse eid="1CH 8:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CH 8:19"/>And Jakim, and Zikri, and Zabdi,<verse eid="1CH 8:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CH 8:20"/>and Elienai, and Zillethai, and Eliel,<verse eid="1CH 8:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CH 8:21"/>and Adaiah, and Beraiah, and Shimrath, the sons of Shimei.<verse eid="1CH 8:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CH 8:22"/>And Ishpan, and Eber, and Eliel,<verse eid="1CH 8:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CH 8:23"/>and Abdon, and Zikri, and Hanan,<verse eid="1CH 8:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CH 8:24"/>and Hananiah, and Elam, and Anthothijah,<verse eid="1CH 8:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CH 8:25"/>and Iphdeiah, and Penuel, the sons of Shashak.<verse eid="1CH 8:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CH 8:26"/>And Shamsherai, and Shehariah, and Athaliah,<verse eid="1CH 8:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CH 8:27"/>and Jaareshiah, and Elijah, and Zikri, the sons of Jeroham.<verse eid="1CH 8:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CH 8:28"/>These, heads of fathers by their generations, heads. They lived in Jerusalem.<verse eid="1CH 8:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CH 8:29"/>And in Gibeon, they lived: the father of Gibeon, and the name of his wife, Maakah,<verse eid="1CH 8:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CH 8:30"/>and his son, the firstborn, Abdon, and Zur, and Kish, and Baal, and Nadab,<verse eid="1CH 8:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CH 8:31"/>and Gedor, and Ahio, and Zeker.<verse eid="1CH 8:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CH 8:32"/>And Mikloth fathered Shimeah. And also they, opposite their brothers, lived in Jerusalem with their brothers.<verse eid="1CH 8:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1CH 8:33"/>And Ner fathered Kish. And Kish fathered Saul. And Saul fathered Jonathan, and Malki-Shua, and Abinadab, and Esh-Baal.<verse eid="1CH 8:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="1CH 8:34"/>And the son of Jonathan, Merib-Baal. And Merib-Baal fathered Micah.<verse eid="1CH 8:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="1CH 8:35"/>And the sons of Micah: Pithon, and Melek, and Tarea, and Ahaz.<verse eid="1CH 8:35"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" sid="1CH 8:36"/>And Ahaz fathered Jehoaddah. And Jehoaddah fathered Alemeth, and Azmaveth, and Zimri. And Zimri fathered Moza.<verse eid="1CH 8:36"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" sid="1CH 8:37"/>And Moza fathered Binea. Raphah his son, Eleasah his son, Azel his son.<verse eid="1CH 8:37"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" sid="1CH 8:38"/>And to Azel six sons. And these, their names: Azrikam, Bokeru, and Ishmael, and Sheariah, and Obadiah, and Hanan. All these, the sons of Azel.<verse eid="1CH 8:38"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" sid="1CH 8:39"/>And the sons of Eshek, his brother: Ulam his firstborn, Jeush the second, and Eliphelet the third.<verse eid="1CH 8:39"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" sid="1CH 8:40"/>And the sons of Ulam were men mighty in strength, who bent the bow, and multipliers of sons and sons of sons, 150. All these from the sons of Benjamin.<verse eid="1CH 8:40"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 8"/>
<chapter number="9" style="c" sid="1CH 9"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 9:1"/>And all Israel were listed in genealogy, and behold, they are written on the scroll of the kings of Israel. And Judah was taken into exile to Babylon because of their unfaithfulness.<verse eid="1CH 9:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 9:2"/>And the first inhabitants who were in their possession, in their cities: Israel, the priests, the Levites, and the temple servants.<verse eid="1CH 9:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 9:3"/>And in Jerusalem they lived, from the sons of Judah, and from the sons of Benjamin, and from the sons of Ephraim and Manasseh.<verse eid="1CH 9:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 9:4"/>Uthai the son of Ammihud, the son of Omri, the son of Imri, the son of Bani, from the sons of Perez, the son of Judah.<verse eid="1CH 9:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 9:5"/>And from the Shilonites: Asaiah the firstborn and his sons.<verse eid="1CH 9:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 9:6"/>And from the sons of Zerah: Jeuel and their brothers, 690.<verse eid="1CH 9:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 9:7"/>And from the sons of Benjamin: Sallu, the son of Meshullam, the son of Hodaviah, the son of Hassenuah,<verse eid="1CH 9:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 9:8"/>and Ibneiah the son of Jeroham, and Elah the son of Uzzi, the son of Mikri, and Meshullam the son of Shephatiah, the son of Reuel, the son of Ibnijah,<verse eid="1CH 9:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 9:9"/>and their brothers according to their generations, 956. All these men, heads of fathers, according to the house of their fathers.<verse eid="1CH 9:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 9:10"/>And from the priests: Jedaiah, and Jehoiarib, and Jakin,<verse eid="1CH 9:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 9:11"/>and Azariah, the son of Hilkiah, the son of Meshullam, the son of Zadok, the son of Meraioth, the son of Ahitub, the leader of the house of God,<verse eid="1CH 9:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 9:12"/>and Adaiah, the son of Jeroham, the son of Pashhur, the son of Malkijah, and Maasai, the son of Adiel, the son of Jahzerah, the son of Meshullam, the son of Meshillemith, the son of Immer,<verse eid="1CH 9:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 9:13"/>and their brothers, heads of the house of their fathers, 1,760, mighty of strength for the work of the service of the house of God.<verse eid="1CH 9:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 9:14"/>And from the Levites: Shemaiah, the son of Hasshub, the son of Azrikam, the son of Hashabiah, from the sons of Merari,<verse eid="1CH 9:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CH 9:15"/>and Bakbakkar, Heresh, and Galal, and Mattaniah, the son of Mika, the son of Zikri, the son of Asaph,<verse eid="1CH 9:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CH 9:16"/>and Obadiah, the son of Shemaiah, the son of Galal, the son of Jeduthun, and Berekiah, the son of Asa, the son of Elkanah, who lived in the villages of the Netophathites.<verse eid="1CH 9:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CH 9:17"/>And the gatekeepers: Shallum, and Akkub, and Talmon, and Ahiman, and their brothers; Shallum, the head.<verse eid="1CH 9:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CH 9:18"/>And until now in the gate of the king to the east, they were the gatekeepers for the camps of the sons of Levi.<verse eid="1CH 9:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CH 9:19"/>And Shallum, the son of Kore, the son of Ebiasaph, the son of Korah, and his brothers of the house of his father, the Korahites, were over the work of the service, the keepers of the thresholds of the tent, and their fathers over the camp of Yahweh, the keepers of the entrance.<verse eid="1CH 9:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CH 9:20"/>And Phinehas the son of Eleazar was leader over them before faces; Yahweh was with him.<verse eid="1CH 9:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CH 9:21"/>Zechariah the son of Meshelemiah, gatekeeper of the entrance to the tent of meeting.<verse eid="1CH 9:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CH 9:22"/>All those chosen as gatekeepers at the thresholds, 212. They in their villages listed in their genealogy, they, David and Samuel the seer, established in their official duty.<verse eid="1CH 9:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CH 9:23"/>And they and their sons over the gates of the house of Yahweh, of the house of the tent as guards.<verse eid="1CH 9:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CH 9:24"/>To the four winds were the gatekeepers, east, west, north, and south.<verse eid="1CH 9:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CH 9:25"/>And their brothers in their villages were to come for seven days from time to time with these.<verse eid="1CH 9:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CH 9:26"/>For in official duty, they, the four leaders of the gatekeepers, they were Levites, and they were over the chambers and over the treasuries of the house of God.<verse eid="1CH 9:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CH 9:27"/>And around the house of God they would lodge, for on them was the watch. And they were over the key and morning by morning.<verse eid="1CH 9:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CH 9:28"/>And from them over the utensils of the service, for by number they would bring them in and by number they would bring them out.<verse eid="1CH 9:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CH 9:29"/>And from them ones who were appointed over the vessels and over all the utensils of the Holy Place, and over the fine flour, and the wine, and the oil, and the frankincense, and the spices.<verse eid="1CH 9:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CH 9:30"/>And from the sons of the priests, mixers of the ointment for the spices.<verse eid="1CH 9:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CH 9:31"/>And Mattithiah, from the Levites, he the firstborn of Shallum the Korahite, in official duty over the work of the flat cakes.<verse eid="1CH 9:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CH 9:32"/>And from the sons of the Kohathites, from their brothers, over the bread of the rows, to prepare Sabbath by Sabbath.<verse eid="1CH 9:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1CH 9:33"/>And these, the singers, the heads of the fathers of the Levites in the chambers were free, for by day and by night they were over them in the work.<verse eid="1CH 9:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="1CH 9:34"/>These, the heads of the fathers of the Levites, according to their generations, heads. These lived in Jerusalem.<verse eid="1CH 9:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="1CH 9:35"/>And in Gibeon, they lived, the father of Gibeon, Jeiel, and the name of his wife, Maakah,<verse eid="1CH 9:35"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" sid="1CH 9:36"/>and his son, the firstborn, Abdon, and Zur, and Kish, and Baal, and Ner, and Nadab,<verse eid="1CH 9:36"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" sid="1CH 9:37"/>and Gedor, and Ahio, and Zechariah, and Mikloth.<verse eid="1CH 9:37"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" sid="1CH 9:38"/>And Mikloth fathered Shimeam. And also they, opposite their brothers, lived in Jerusalem with their brothers.<verse eid="1CH 9:38"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" sid="1CH 9:39"/>And Ner fathered Kish. And Kish fathered Saul. And Saul fathered Jonathan, and Malki-Shua, and Abinadab, and Esh-Baal.<verse eid="1CH 9:39"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" sid="1CH 9:40"/>And the son of Jonathan, Merib-Baal. And Merib-Baal fathered Micah.<verse eid="1CH 9:40"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v" sid="1CH 9:41"/>And the sons of Micah: Pithon, and Melek, and Tahrea.<verse eid="1CH 9:41"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="42" style="v" sid="1CH 9:42"/>And Ahaz fathered Jarah. And Jarah fathered Alemeth, and Azmaveth, and Zimri. And Zimri fathered Moza.<verse eid="1CH 9:42"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="43" style="v" sid="1CH 9:43"/>And Moza fathered Binea. And Rephaiah his son, Eleasah his son, Azel his son.<verse eid="1CH 9:43"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="44" style="v" sid="1CH 9:44"/>And to Azel six sons, and these, their names: Azrikam, Bokeru, and Ishmael, and Sheariah, and Obadiah, and Hanan. These, the sons of Azel.<verse eid="1CH 9:44"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 9"/>
<chapter number="10" style="c" sid="1CH 10"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 10:1"/>And the Philistines fought with Israel. And the men of Israel fled from the faces of the Philistines, and they fell slain on Mount Gilboa.<verse eid="1CH 10:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 10:2"/>And the Philistines pursued after Saul and after his sons. And the Philistines struck down Jonathan, and Abinadab, and Malki-Shua, the sons of Saul.<verse eid="1CH 10:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 10:3"/>And the battle was heavy against Saul, and those who shoot with the bow found him, and he writhed in pain from the ones shooting.<verse eid="1CH 10:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 10:4"/>Then Saul said to the lifter of his equipment, “Draw your sword and pierce me with it, lest these uncircumcised will come and mistreat me.” But the lifter of his equipment was not willing, for he feared greatly. And Saul took the sword, and he fell on it.<verse eid="1CH 10:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 10:5"/>And the lifter of his equipment saw that Saul had died, and he himself likewise fell on the sword, and he died.<verse eid="1CH 10:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 10:6"/>And Saul died, and his three sons. And all his house died together.<verse eid="1CH 10:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 10:7"/>And every man of Israel who was in the valley saw that they had fled, and that Saul and his sons had died. And they abandoned their cities, and they fled. And the Philistines came, and they lived in them.<verse eid="1CH 10:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 10:8"/>And it happened on the next day, and the Philistines came to strip the slain, and they found Saul and his sons fallen on Mount Gilboa.<verse eid="1CH 10:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 10:9"/>And they stripped him, and they carried away his head and his armor. And they sent among the land of the Philistines all around to bring news to their idols and the people.<verse eid="1CH 10:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 10:10"/>And they put his armor in the house of their gods, and his head they fastened in the house of Dagon.<verse eid="1CH 10:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 10:11"/>And all Jabesh Gilead heard all that the Philistines did to Saul,<verse eid="1CH 10:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 10:12"/>and all the men of strength rose, and they carried the corpse of Saul and the corpses of his sons. And they brought them to Jabesh. And they buried their bones under the large tree in Jabesh, and they fasted seven days.<verse eid="1CH 10:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 10:13"/>And Saul died because of his infidelity which he was unfaithful to Yahweh on account of the word of Yahweh which he did not keep, and also to ask a medium to seek,<verse eid="1CH 10:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 10:14"/>and he did not seek Yahweh, and he killed him. And he turned the kingdom to David, the son of Jesse.<verse eid="1CH 10:14"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 10"/>
<chapter number="11" style="c" sid="1CH 11"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 11:1"/>And all Israel gathered to David at Hebron, saying, “Look, your bones and your flesh are we.<verse eid="1CH 11:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 11:2"/>Even yesterday also the day before that, even when Saul was king, you were the one who brought out and the one who brought in Israel. And Yahweh your God said to you, ‘You yourself will shepherd my people, Israel, and you yourself will be leader over my people Israel.’”<verse eid="1CH 11:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 11:3"/>And all the elders of Israel came to the king at Hebron, and David cut with them a covenant at Hebron before the face of Yahweh. And they anointed David king over Israel according to the word of Yahweh by the hand of Samuel.<verse eid="1CH 11:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 11:4"/>And David went and all Israel to Jerusalem; that is, Jebus. And there were the Jebusites, the inhabitants of the land.<verse eid="1CH 11:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 11:5"/>And the inhabitants of Jebus said to David, “You will not come in here.” But David captured the stronghold of Zion, that is, the city of David.<verse eid="1CH 11:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 11:6"/>And David said, “Whoever strikes down the Jebusites first will become head and chief.” And Joab the son of Zeruiah went up first, and he became head.<verse eid="1CH 11:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 11:7"/>And David lived in the stronghold; therefore they called it the city of David.<verse eid="1CH 11:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 11:8"/>And he built the city all around, from the Millo and as far as that which surrounds. And Joab restored the rest of the city.<verse eid="1CH 11:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 11:9"/>And David went, going and becoming great, and Yahweh of Hosts was with him.<verse eid="1CH 11:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 11:10"/>And these, the heads of the mighty ones who belonged to David strengthened themselves with him in his kingdom, with all Israel, to make him king, according to the word of Yahweh concerning Israel.<verse eid="1CH 11:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 11:11"/>And these, the number of the mighty ones who belonged to David: Jashobeam, a son of a Hachmonite, the head of the officers. He swung his spear against 300, slain at one time.<verse eid="1CH 11:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 11:12"/>And after him, Eleazar the son of Dodo, the Ahohite, he among the three mighty ones.<verse eid="1CH 11:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 11:13"/>He was with David at Pas Dammim, and the Philistines had assembled there for battle. And there was a portion of the field full of barley. And the peope fled from the faces of the Philistines.<verse eid="1CH 11:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 11:14"/>And they took their stand in the midst of the portion. And they delivered it, and they struck down the Philistines. And Yahweh saved a great salvation.<verse eid="1CH 11:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CH 11:15"/>And three from the 30 heads went down to the rock to David, to the cave of Adullam. And the camp of the Philistines encamped in the Valley of Rephaim.<verse eid="1CH 11:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CH 11:16"/>And David then was in the stronghold, and the garrison of the Philistines then was in Bethlehem.<verse eid="1CH 11:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CH 11:17"/>And David desired, and he said, “Who will give me water to drink from the well of Bethlehem which is by the gate?”<verse eid="1CH 11:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CH 11:18"/>And the three broke through the camp of the Philistines, and they drew water from the well of Bethlehem which was by the gate. And they carried, and they brought to David. But David was not willing to drink it, and he poured it out to Yahweh.<verse eid="1CH 11:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CH 11:19"/>And he said, “Far be it from me before my God from doing this! Do I drink the blood of these men with their lives? For with their lives they brought it.” And he was not willing to drink it. These, the three mighty ones did.<verse eid="1CH 11:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CH 11:20"/>And Abshai, the brother of Joab, he was the head of the Three. And he swung his spear against 300, slain. And to him a name among the Three.<verse eid="1CH 11:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CH 11:21"/>From the Three, in the second he was honored and he became to them a chief, but up to the Three he did not enter.<verse eid="1CH 11:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CH 11:22"/>Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, the son of a man of strength, great deeds, from Kabzeel. He himself struck down the two of Ariel of Moab. And he himself went down, and he struck down the lion in the midst of the pit on the day of the snow.<verse eid="1CH 11:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CH 11:23"/>And he himself struck down the man of Egypt, a man of stature, five cubits. And in the hand of the Egyptian, a spear like the beam of weavers, but he went down to him with a staff. And he seized the spear from the hand of the Egyptian, and he killed him with his spear.<verse eid="1CH 11:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CH 11:24"/>These, Benaiah the son of Jehoiada did, and to him a name among the three mighty ones.<verse eid="1CH 11:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CH 11:25"/>From the 30, behold, he himself was honored, but to the three, he did not enter. And David set him over his bodyguard.<verse eid="1CH 11:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CH 11:26"/>And the mighty ones of strength: Asahel the brother of Joab, Elhanan the son of Dodo from Bethlehem,<verse eid="1CH 11:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CH 11:27"/>Shammoth the Harorite, Helez the Pelonite,<verse eid="1CH 11:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CH 11:28"/>Ira the son of Ikkesh the Tekoite, Abiezer the Anathothite,<verse eid="1CH 11:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CH 11:29"/>Sibbekai the Hushathite, Ilai the Ahohite,<verse eid="1CH 11:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CH 11:30"/>Maharai the Netophathite, Heled the son of Baanah the Netophathite,<verse eid="1CH 11:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CH 11:31"/>Ithai the son of Ribai from Gibeah of the sons of Benjamin, Benaiah the Pirathonite,<verse eid="1CH 11:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CH 11:32"/>Hurai from the valleys of Gaash, Abiel the Arbathite,<verse eid="1CH 11:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1CH 11:33"/>Azmaveth the Baharumite, Eliahba the Shaalbonite,<verse eid="1CH 11:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="1CH 11:34"/>the sons of Hashem the Gizonite, Jonathan the son of Shagee the Hararite,<verse eid="1CH 11:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="1CH 11:35"/>Ahiam the son of Sakar the Hararite, Eliphal the son of Ur,<verse eid="1CH 11:35"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" sid="1CH 11:36"/>Hepher the Mekerathite, Ahijah the Pelonite,<verse eid="1CH 11:36"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" sid="1CH 11:37"/>Hezro the Carmelite, Naarai the son of Ezbai,<verse eid="1CH 11:37"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" sid="1CH 11:38"/>Joel the brother of Nathan, Mibhar the son of Hagri,<verse eid="1CH 11:38"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" sid="1CH 11:39"/>Zelek the Ammonite, Naharai the Berothite, the lifter of the equipment of Joab the son of Zeruiah,<verse eid="1CH 11:39"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" sid="1CH 11:40"/>Ira the Ithrite, Gareb the Ithrite,<verse eid="1CH 11:40"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v" sid="1CH 11:41"/>Uriah the Hittite, Zabad the son of Ahlai,<verse eid="1CH 11:41"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="42" style="v" sid="1CH 11:42"/>Adina the son of Shiza the Reubenite, a head of the Reubenites, and with him 30,<verse eid="1CH 11:42"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="43" style="v" sid="1CH 11:43"/>Hanan the son of Maacah, and Joshaphat the Mithnite,<verse eid="1CH 11:43"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="44" style="v" sid="1CH 11:44"/>Uzzia the Ashterathite, Shama and Jeiel the sons of Hotham the Aroerite,<verse eid="1CH 11:44"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="45" style="v" sid="1CH 11:45"/>Jediael the son of Shimri, and Joha his brother, the Tizite,<verse eid="1CH 11:45"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="46" style="v" sid="1CH 11:46"/>Eliel the Mahavite, and Jeribai and Joshaviah, the sons of Elnaam, and Ithmah the Moabite,<verse eid="1CH 11:46"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="47" style="v" sid="1CH 11:47"/>Eliel, and Obed, and Jaasiel the Mezobaite.<verse eid="1CH 11:47"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 11"/>
<chapter number="12" style="c" sid="1CH 12"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 12:1"/>And these, the ones who came to David at Ziklag, while he was one restrained from the face of Saul the son of Kish. And they were among the mighty ones, helping the battle.<verse eid="1CH 12:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 12:2"/>They were armed with a bow, right-handed and left-handed with stones and with arrows with the bow, from the brothers of Saul, from Benjamin.<verse eid="1CH 12:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 12:3"/>The head, Ahiezer, and Joash, the sons of Shemaah the Gibeathite, and Jeziel and Pelet, the sons of Azmaveth, and Berakah, and Jehu the Anathothite,<verse eid="1CH 12:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 12:4"/>and Ishmaiah the Gibeonite, a mighty one among the 30 and over the 30, and Jeremiah, and Jahaziel, and Johanan, and Jozabad the Gederathite,<verse eid="1CH 12:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 12:5"/>Eluzai, and Jerimoth, and Bealiah, and Shemariah, Shephatiah the Haruphite,<verse eid="1CH 12:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 12:6"/>Elkanah, and Isshiah, and Azarel, and Joezer, and Jashobeam, the Korahites,<verse eid="1CH 12:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 12:7"/>and Joelah and Zebadiah, the sons of Jeroham from Gedor.<verse eid="1CH 12:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 12:8"/>And from the Gadites they separated themselves to David at the stronghold in the wilderness, mighty in strength, men of the army for battle, ready with shield and spear, and faces of lions were their faces, and like gazelles on the hills to hasten.<verse eid="1CH 12:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 12:9"/>Ezer the head, Obadiah the second, Eliab the third,<verse eid="1CH 12:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 12:10"/>Mishmannah the fourth, Jeremiah the fifth,<verse eid="1CH 12:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 12:11"/>Attai the sixth, Eliel the seventh,<verse eid="1CH 12:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 12:12"/>Johanan the eighth, Elzabad the ninth,<verse eid="1CH 12:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 12:13"/>Jeremiah the tenth, Makbannai the 11th.<verse eid="1CH 12:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 12:14"/>These from the sons of Gad, the heads of the army. One for 100, the least; and the greatest for 1,000.<verse eid="1CH 12:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CH 12:15"/>These, they who passed over the Jordan in the first month, and it was filling over all its banks, and caused to flee all the valleys, to the east and to the west.<verse eid="1CH 12:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CH 12:16"/>And from the sons of Benjamin and Judah came to the stronghold to David.<verse eid="1CH 12:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CH 12:17"/>And David went out before their faces, and he answered, and he said to them: “If for peace you have come to me, to help me, my heart will be to you all for unity. But if to betray me to my adversaries, with no violence in my palms, may the God of our fathers see and rebuke.”<verse eid="1CH 12:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CH 12:18"/>And the Spirit clothed Amasai, the head of the 30: “To you, O David, and with you, O Son of Jesse. Peace, peace to you and peace to the one who helps you, for your God has helped you.” And David received them and placed them as the heads of the troop.<verse eid="1CH 12:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CH 12:19"/>And from Manasseh fell upon David when he went with the Philistines against Saul to battle. And they did not help them because by counsel the governors of the Philistines sent them away, saying, “By our heads he will fall to his lord, Saul.”<verse eid="1CH 12:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CH 12:20"/>In his going to Ziklag, they fell upon him from Manasseh: Adnah, and Jozabad, and Jediael, and Michael, and Jozabad, and Elihu, and Zillethai, the heads of the thousands who were of Manasseh.<verse eid="1CH 12:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CH 12:21"/>And they helped with David against the troop, for mighty ones of strength, all of them, and they were chiefs in the army.<verse eid="1CH 12:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CH 12:22"/>For at the time of day by day, they were coming to David to help him, until there was a great camp, like the camp of God.<verse eid="1CH 12:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CH 12:23"/>And these, the numbers of the heads of those equipped for war. They came to David at Hebron to turn the kingdom of Saul to him according to the mouth of Yahweh.<verse eid="1CH 12:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CH 12:24"/>The sons of Judah, those carrying shield and spear, 6,800, equipped for war.<verse eid="1CH 12:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CH 12:25"/>From the sons of Simeon, mighty ones of strength for war, 7,100.<verse eid="1CH 12:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CH 12:26"/>From the sons of Levi, 4,600.<verse eid="1CH 12:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CH 12:27"/>And Jehoiada, the leader from Aaron, and with him, 3,700.<verse eid="1CH 12:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CH 12:28"/>And Zadok, a young, mighty one of strength, and the house of his father, 22 chiefs.<verse eid="1CH 12:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CH 12:29"/>And from the sons of Benjamin, the brothers of Saul, 3,000. And until then the majority of them were keeping the charge of the house of Saul.<verse eid="1CH 12:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CH 12:30"/>And from the sons of Ephraim, 20,800 mighty ones of strength, men of names, according to the house of their fathers.<verse eid="1CH 12:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CH 12:31"/>And from the half tribe of Manasseh, 18,000 who were marked by names to come to make David king.<verse eid="1CH 12:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CH 12:32"/>And from the sons of Issachar, those who knew understanding of the times to know what Israel should do, their heads, 200, and all their brothers according to their mouth.<verse eid="1CH 12:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1CH 12:33"/>From Zebulun, those going out for war, prepared for battle with all the weapons of battle, 50,000, and to help with no heart and a heart.<verse eid="1CH 12:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="1CH 12:34"/>And from Naphtali, 1,000 chiefs, and with them with shield and spear, 37,000.<verse eid="1CH 12:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="1CH 12:35"/>And from the Danites, prepared for battle, 28,600.<verse eid="1CH 12:35"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" sid="1CH 12:36"/>And from Asher those going out for war to prepare for battle, 40,000.<verse eid="1CH 12:36"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" sid="1CH 12:37"/>And from beyond the Jordan, from the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and the half tribe of Manasseh, with all the weapons of war for battle, 120,000.<verse eid="1CH 12:37"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" sid="1CH 12:38"/>All these men of battle, helpers of the battle line; with a whole heart, they came to Hebron to make David king over all Israel. And also all the rest of Israel was of one heart to make David king.<verse eid="1CH 12:38"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" sid="1CH 12:39"/>And they were there with David three days, eating and drinking, for their brothers had prepared for them.<verse eid="1CH 12:39"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" sid="1CH 12:40"/>And also, those near to them, as far as Issachar and Zebulun and Naphtali, were bringing bread on donkeys, and on camels, and on mules, and on oxen; food of flour, fig cakes, and raisins cakes, and wine, and oil, and oxen, and sheep, in abundance, for joy was in Israel.<verse eid="1CH 12:40"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 12"/>
<chapter number="13" style="c" sid="1CH 13"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 13:1"/>And David consulted with the chiefs of thousands and of hundreds, to every leader.<verse eid="1CH 13:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 13:2"/>And David said to all the assembly of Israel, “If to you all it is good, and from Yahweh our God, let us break out, let us send to our brothers who remain in all the regions of Israel, and with them the priests and the Levites in the cities of their pasturelands. And let them gather to us.<verse eid="1CH 13:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 13:3"/>And let us return the Box of our God to us, for we did not seek it in the days of Saul.”<verse eid="1CH 13:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 13:4"/>And all the assembly said to do thus, for the thing was right in the eyes of all the people.<verse eid="1CH 13:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 13:5"/>And David assembled all Israel from Shihor of Egypt and as far as Lebo Hamath, to bring in the Box of God from Kiriath Jearim.<verse eid="1CH 13:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 13:6"/>And David went up and all Israel to Baalah, to Kiriath Jearim, which belongs to Judah, to bring up from there the Box of God Yahweh who sits over the cherubim which is called by name.<verse eid="1CH 13:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 13:7"/>And they transported the Box of God on a new cart from the house of Abinadab; and Uzzah and Ahio were driving the cart.<verse eid="1CH 13:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 13:8"/>And David and all Israel were celebrating before the face of God with all might, and with songs, and lyres, and harps, and tambourines, and cymbals, and trumpets.<verse eid="1CH 13:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 13:9"/>And they came to the threshing floor of Kidon, and Uzzah sent out his hand to grasp the Box for the oxen stumbled.<verse eid="1CH 13:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 13:10"/>And the anger of Yahweh burned against Uzzah, and He struck him down because he sent out his hand on the Box. And he died there before the face of God.<verse eid="1CH 13:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 13:11"/>And David became angry because Yahweh broke out a breaking out against Uzzah. And he called that place Perez Uzzah until this day.<verse eid="1CH 13:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 13:12"/>And David feared God in that day, saying, “How will I bring to myself the Box of God?”<verse eid="1CH 13:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 13:13"/>And David did not remove the Box to himself, to the city of David, but he turned it to the house of Obed Edom the Gittite.<verse eid="1CH 13:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 13:14"/>And the Box of God dwelt with the house of Obed Edom in his house three months. And Yahweh blessed the house of Obed Edom and all that belonged to him.<verse eid="1CH 13:14"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 13"/>
<chapter number="14" style="c" sid="1CH 14"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 14:1"/>And Hiram the king of Tyre sent messengers to David, and wood of cedar, and craftsmen of a wall, and craftsmen of wood to build for him a house.<verse eid="1CH 14:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 14:2"/>And David knew that Yahweh had established him as king over Israel, that his kingdom was lifted upwards for the sake of his people Israel.<verse eid="1CH 14:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 14:3"/>And David took more wives in Jerusalem, and David fathered more sons and daughters.<verse eid="1CH 14:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 14:4"/>And these, the names of those born who were to him in Jerusalem: Shammua, and Shobab, Nathan, and Solomon,<verse eid="1CH 14:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 14:5"/>and Ibhar, and Elishua, and Elpelet,<verse eid="1CH 14:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 14:6"/>and Nogah, and Nepheg, and Japhia,<verse eid="1CH 14:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 14:7"/>and Elishama, and Beeliada, and Eliphelet.<verse eid="1CH 14:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 14:8"/>Now the Philistines heard that David was anointed as king over all Israel, and all the Philistines went up to seek David. And David heard and went out before their faces.<verse eid="1CH 14:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 14:9"/>And the Philistines went, and they raided in the Valley of Rephaim.<verse eid="1CH 14:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 14:10"/>Then David asked God, saying, “Should I go up against the Philistines? And will you give them into my hand?” And Yahweh said to him, “Go up and I will give them into your hand.”<verse eid="1CH 14:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 14:11"/>And they went up to Baal Perazim, and David struck them down there. And David said, “God has broken through my enemies by my hand like a breaking through of waters.” Therefore they called the name of that place Baal Perazim.<verse eid="1CH 14:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 14:12"/>And they abandoned their gods there, and David ordered, and they were burned with fire.<verse eid="1CH 14:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 14:13"/>And the Philistines acted yet again, and they raided in the valley.<verse eid="1CH 14:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 14:14"/>And David asked God again. And God said to him, “Do not go up after them; circle around from upon them and come at them in front of the balsam trees.<verse eid="1CH 14:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CH 14:15"/>And it shall be when you hear the sound of the marching in the heads of the balsam trees, at that time you shall go out in battle. For God has gone out before your face to strike down the camp of the Philistines.”<verse eid="1CH 14:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CH 14:16"/>And David did just as God commanded him. And he struck down the camp of the Philistines, from Gibeon and as far as Gezer.<verse eid="1CH 14:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CH 14:17"/>And the name of David went out into all the lands, and Yahweh placed the fear of him on all the nations.<verse eid="1CH 14:17"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 14"/>
<chapter number="15" style="c" sid="1CH 15"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 15:1"/>And he made for himself houses in the city of David. And he prepared a place for the Box of God, and he stretched out a tent for it.<verse eid="1CH 15:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 15:2"/>Then David said, “No one shall carry the Box of God, but only the Levites. For them Yahweh chose to carry the Box of Yahweh and to minister for him forever.”<verse eid="1CH 15:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 15:3"/>And David assembled all Israel to Jerusalem to bring up the Box of Yahweh to its place which he had prepared for it.<verse eid="1CH 15:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 15:4"/>And David gathered the sons of Aaron and the Levites.<verse eid="1CH 15:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 15:5"/>Of the sons of Kohath, Uriel the chief and his brothers, 120.<verse eid="1CH 15:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 15:6"/>Of the sons of Merari, Asaiah the chief and his brothers, 220.<verse eid="1CH 15:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 15:7"/>Of the sons of Gershom, Joel the chief and his brothers, 130.<verse eid="1CH 15:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 15:8"/>Of the sons of Elizaphan, Shemaiah the chief and his brothers, 200.<verse eid="1CH 15:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 15:9"/>Of the sons of Hebron, Eliel the chief and his brothers, 80.<verse eid="1CH 15:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 15:10"/>Of the sons of Uzziel, Amminadab the chief and his brothers, 112.<verse eid="1CH 15:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 15:11"/>And David called for Zadok and for Abiathar the priests, and for the Levites, for Uriel, Asaiah, and Joel, Shemaiah, and Eliel, and Amminadab.<verse eid="1CH 15:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 15:12"/>And he said to them, “You are the heads of the fathers of the Levites. Consecrate yourselves, you and your brothers, and bring up the Box of Yahweh, the God of Israel, to where I prepared for it.<verse eid="1CH 15:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 15:13"/>Because at the first it was not you, Yahweh our God broke out against us, for we did not seek him according to the judgment.”<verse eid="1CH 15:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 15:14"/>And the priests and the Levites consecrated themselves to bring up the Box of Yahweh, the God of Israel.<verse eid="1CH 15:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CH 15:15"/>And the sons of Levi carried the Box of God just as Moses commanded, according to the word of Yahweh, on their shoulders with poles on them.<verse eid="1CH 15:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CH 15:16"/>And David said to the chiefs of the Levites to assign their brothers as the singers with instruments of song, harps, and lyres, and cymbals, playing to raise a sound of joy.<verse eid="1CH 15:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CH 15:17"/>And the Levites assigned Heman the son of Joel and from his brothers, Asaph the son of Berechiah, and from the sons of Merari their brothers, Ethan the son of Kushaiah,<verse eid="1CH 15:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CH 15:18"/>and with them, their brothers of the second rank: Zechariah, Ben, and Jaaziel, and Shemiramoth, and Jehiel, and Unni, Eliab, and Benaiah, and Maaseiah, and Mattithiah, and Eliphelehu, and Mikneiah, and Obed Edom, and Jeiel, the gatekeepers.<verse eid="1CH 15:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CH 15:19"/>And the singers, Heman, Asaph, and Ethan, with bronze cymbals to play.<verse eid="1CH 15:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CH 15:20"/>And Zechariah, and Aziel, and Shemiramoth, and Jehiel, and Unni, and Eliab, and Maaseiah, and Benaiah with harps, according to Alamoth.<verse eid="1CH 15:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CH 15:21"/>And Mattithiah, and Eliphelehu, and Mikneiah, and Obed Edom, and Jeiel, and Azaziah with lyres, according to the Sheminith to lead.<verse eid="1CH 15:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CH 15:22"/>And Kenaniah, the chief of the Levites in lifting up, an instructor in lifting up, for he was one who understood.<verse eid="1CH 15:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CH 15:23"/>And Berechiah and Elkanah, gatekeepers for the Box.<verse eid="1CH 15:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CH 15:24"/>And Shebaniah, and Joshaphat, and Nethanel, and Amasai, and Zechariah, and Benaiah, and Eliezer, the priests, the ones to blow the trumpets before the face of the Box of God. And Obed Edom and Jehiah, gatekeepers for the Box.<verse eid="1CH 15:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CH 15:25"/>And it happened David, and the elders of Israel, and the chiefs of thousands were going to bring up the Box of the covenant of Yahweh from the house of Obed Edom with joy.<verse eid="1CH 15:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CH 15:26"/>And it happened when God helped the Levites carrying the Box of the covenant of Yahweh, and they slaughtered seven bulls and seven rams.<verse eid="1CH 15:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CH 15:27"/>And David was clothed in a robe of fine linen, and all the Levites carrying the Box, and the singers, and Kenaniah, the chief of the lifting up of the singers. And on David, an ephod of linen.<verse eid="1CH 15:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CH 15:28"/>And all Israel was bringing up the Box of the covenant of Yahweh with shouting of joy, and with a sound of a horn and with trumpets, and with cymbals, playing with harps and lyres.<verse eid="1CH 15:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CH 15:29"/>And it happened the Box of the covenant of Yahweh was coming to the city of David, and Michal the daughter of Saul, looked down out of the window. And she saw the king, David, dancing and celebrating. And she despised him in her heart.<verse eid="1CH 15:29"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 15"/>
<chapter number="16" style="c" sid="1CH 16"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 16:1"/>And they brought in the Box of God and put it in the midst of the tent that David streched out for it. And they offered burnt offerings and peace offerings before the face of God.<verse eid="1CH 16:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 16:2"/>And David finished bringing up the burnt offering and the peace offerings, and he blessed the people in the name of Yahweh.<verse eid="1CH 16:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 16:3"/>And he distributed to each person of Israel, from man and as far as woman, to each a loaf of bread, and a date cake, and a raisin cake.<verse eid="1CH 16:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 16:4"/>And he appointed before the face of the Box of Yahweh from the Levites as ones who minister, and to commemorate and to thank and to praise Yahweh, the God of Israel.<verse eid="1CH 16:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 16:5"/>Asaph the head, and second to him Zechariah, Jeiel, and Shemiramoth, and Jehiel, and Mattithiah, and Eliab, and Benaiah, and Obed Edom, and Jeiel, with instruments of harps and lyres, and Asaph with cymbals was playing,<verse eid="1CH 16:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 16:6"/>and Benaiah and Jahaziel the priests with trumpets regularly, before the face of the Box of the covenant of God.<verse eid="1CH 16:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 16:7"/>On that day then David first appointed to thank Yahweh by the hand of Asaph and his brothers.<verse eid="1CH 16:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 16:8"/>Give thanks to Yahweh, call on his name; make known among the peoples his deeds.<verse eid="1CH 16:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 16:9"/>Sing to him, make music to him; tell of all his wonderful acts.<verse eid="1CH 16:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 16:10"/>Glory in his holy name; let the heart of those who seek Yahweh rejoice.<verse eid="1CH 16:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 16:11"/>Seek Yahweh and his strength; seek his face continually.<verse eid="1CH 16:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 16:12"/>Remember his wonderful acts which he has done, his miracles and the judgments of his mouth,<verse eid="1CH 16:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 16:13"/>O seed of Israel his servant, O sons of Jacob, his chosen ones.<verse eid="1CH 16:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 16:14"/>He is Yahweh, our God; in all the earth are his judgments.<verse eid="1CH 16:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CH 16:15"/>Remember forever his covenant, the word he commanded for 1,000 generations,<verse eid="1CH 16:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CH 16:16"/>which he cut with Abraham, and his oath to Isaac.<verse eid="1CH 16:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CH 16:17"/>And he established it for Jacob as a statute, for Israel a covenant forever,<verse eid="1CH 16:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CH 16:18"/>saying, “To you I will give the land of Canaan the allotment of your inheritance.”<verse eid="1CH 16:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CH 16:19"/>When you all were few in number, insignificant, and sojourners in it,<verse eid="1CH 16:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CH 16:20"/>and they walked back and forth from nation to nation, and from a kingdom to another people,<verse eid="1CH 16:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CH 16:21"/>he did not permit a person to oppress them; and he rebuked kings on account of them.<verse eid="1CH 16:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CH 16:22"/>“Do not strike my anointed ones, and against my prophets do not do evil.”<verse eid="1CH 16:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CH 16:23"/>Sing to Yahweh, all the earth; announce from day to day his salvation.<verse eid="1CH 16:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CH 16:24"/>Recount among the nations his glory, among all the peoples his wonderful acts.<verse eid="1CH 16:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CH 16:25"/>For great is Yahweh and to be praised much, and to be feared is he above all gods.<verse eid="1CH 16:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CH 16:26"/>For all the gods of the peoples are worthless, but Yahweh, the heavens he made.<verse eid="1CH 16:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CH 16:27"/>Splendor and majesty are before his face; strength and joy in his place.<verse eid="1CH 16:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CH 16:28"/>Ascribe to Yahweh, O clans of peoples, ascribe to Yahweh glory and strength!<verse eid="1CH 16:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CH 16:29"/>Ascribe to Yahweh the glory of his name; bring an offering and come before his face; worship Yahweh in holy splendor.<verse eid="1CH 16:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CH 16:30"/>Tremble from before his face, all the earth. Indeed, the world is established; it cannot be shaken.<verse eid="1CH 16:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CH 16:31"/>Let the heavens rejoice, and let the earth shout in exultation; and let them say among the nations, “Yahweh reigns.”<verse eid="1CH 16:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CH 16:32"/>Let the sea roar and that which fills it. Let the field exult, and all that is in it.<verse eid="1CH 16:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1CH 16:33"/>Then the trees of the forest will shout for joy from before the face of Yahweh, for he is coming to judge the earth.<verse eid="1CH 16:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="1CH 16:34"/>Give thanks to Yahweh, for he is good, for forever is his loyal love.<verse eid="1CH 16:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="1CH 16:35"/>And say, “Save us, God of our salvation, and gather us and deliver us from the nations, to give thanks to your holy name, to boast in your praise.”<verse eid="1CH 16:35"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" sid="1CH 16:36"/>Blessed be Yahweh, the God of Israel, from everlasting and as far as everlasting. And all the people said, “Amen” and praised Yahweh.<verse eid="1CH 16:36"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" sid="1CH 16:37"/>And he left there before the face of the Box of the covenant of Yahweh Asaph and his brothers to minister before the face of the Box continually, according to the matter of the day in its day,<verse eid="1CH 16:37"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" sid="1CH 16:38"/>and Obed Edom and their brothers, 68, and Obed Edom the son of Jeduthun, and Hosah, were gatekeepers,<verse eid="1CH 16:38"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" sid="1CH 16:39"/>and Zadok the priest and his brothers the priests before the face of the tabernacle of Yahweh at the high place which was in Gibeon<verse eid="1CH 16:39"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" sid="1CH 16:40"/>to bring up burnt offerings to Yahweh on the altar of burnt offering continually morning and evening, even according to all that is written in the law of Yahweh, which he commanded to Israel.<verse eid="1CH 16:40"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v" sid="1CH 16:41"/>And with them, Heman and Jeduthun and the rest of those chosen who were marked by names to give thanks to Yahweh, for forever is his loyal love.<verse eid="1CH 16:41"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="42" style="v" sid="1CH 16:42"/>And with them, Heman and Jeduthun for those playing trumpets and cymbals and the instruments of song of God; and the sons of Jeduthun for the gate.<verse eid="1CH 16:42"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="43" style="v" sid="1CH 16:43"/>And all the people went, each to his house, and David turned around to bless his house.<verse eid="1CH 16:43"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 16"/>
<chapter number="17" style="c" sid="1CH 17"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 17:1"/>And it happened when David was living in his house, and David said to Nathan the prophet, “Behold, I am living in a house of cedars, but the Box of the covenant of Yahweh is under curtains.”<verse eid="1CH 17:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 17:2"/>And Nathan said to David, “All which is in your heart, do, for God is with you.”<verse eid="1CH 17:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 17:3"/>And it happened in that night, and the word of God came to Nathan, saying,<verse eid="1CH 17:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 17:4"/>“Go and say to David my servant, ‘Thus says Yahweh: You yourself shall not build for me a house in which to live,<verse eid="1CH 17:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 17:5"/>for I have not lived in a house from the day that I brought up Israel until this day, but I have been from tent to tent, and from a tabernacle.<verse eid="1CH 17:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 17:6"/>In all where I have walked back and forth among all Israel, what word did I speak to one of the judges of Israel whom I commanded to shepherd my people, saying, “Why have you all not built for me a house of cedars?”’<verse eid="1CH 17:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 17:7"/>And now, thus you shall say to my servant, to David, ‘Thus says Yahweh of Hosts: I myself took you from the pasture, from behind sheep, to be a leader over my people Israel.<verse eid="1CH 17:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 17:8"/>And I have been with you in all where you have gone, and I have cut off all your enemies from before your face, and I will make for you a name, like a name of the great ones who are on the earth.<verse eid="1CH 17:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 17:9"/>And I will set a place for my people Israel, and I will plant them, and they will settle on it, and they will not tremble again. And the sons of injustice will not continue to trouble them, just as at the first,<verse eid="1CH 17:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 17:10"/>and from the days that I commanded judges over my people Israel. And I will humble all your enemies. And I declare to you that a house Yahweh will build for you.<verse eid="1CH 17:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 17:11"/>And it will be when your days are fulfilled, to walk with your fathers, then I will raise up your seed after you who will be from your sons, and I will establish his kingdom.<verse eid="1CH 17:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 17:12"/>He himself will build for me a house, and I will establish his throne as far as forever.<verse eid="1CH 17:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 17:13"/>I myself will be to him a father, and he himself will be to me a son. And my covenant faithfulness I will not take away from with him, as I took away from who was before your face.<verse eid="1CH 17:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 17:14"/>And I will set him up in my house and in my kingdom as far as forever, and his throne will be established as far as forever.’”<verse eid="1CH 17:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CH 17:15"/>According to all these words and according to all this vision, thus Nathan spoke to David.<verse eid="1CH 17:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CH 17:16"/>Then the king David went in and sat before the face of Yahweh; and he said, “Who am I, Yahweh God, and what is my house, that you have brought me as far as here?<verse eid="1CH 17:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CH 17:17"/>And a small thing was this in your eyes, God, and you have spoken regarding the house of your servant from a distance; and you have seen me as an appearance of the man moving upwards, Yahweh God.<verse eid="1CH 17:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CH 17:18"/>What more can David still say to you about honoring your servant. And you, your servant you know.<verse eid="1CH 17:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CH 17:19"/>Yahweh, for the sake of your servant and according to your heart, you have done all this greatness to make known all the greatnesses.<verse eid="1CH 17:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CH 17:20"/>Yahweh, there is none like you, and no God except you, in all which we have heard with our ears.<verse eid="1CH 17:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CH 17:21"/>And who is like your people Israel, one nation on the earth whom God went to ransom for himself a people, to set for you a name great and to be feared, to drive out nations from the faces of your people whom you ransomed from Egypt?<verse eid="1CH 17:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CH 17:22"/>And you made your people Israel for yourself a people as far as forever, and you, Yahweh, became to them God.<verse eid="1CH 17:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CH 17:23"/>And now, Yahweh, the word which you spoke concerning your servant and concerning his house, may it be confirmed as far as forever, and do just as you have spoken.<verse eid="1CH 17:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CH 17:24"/>And may it be confirmed and may your name be great as far as forever, saying, ‘Yahweh of Hosts, the God of Israel, is God to Israel,’ and the house of David your servant established before your face.<verse eid="1CH 17:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CH 17:25"/>For you, my God, have uncovered the ear of your servant to build for him a house; therefore your servant has found to pray before your face.<verse eid="1CH 17:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CH 17:26"/>And now, Yahweh, you are God, and you have spoken concerning your servant this good.<verse eid="1CH 17:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CH 17:27"/>And now, you have decided to bless the house of your servant, to be forever before your face. For you, Yahweh, have blessed, and it is blessed forever.”<verse eid="1CH 17:27"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 17"/>
<chapter number="18" style="c" sid="1CH 18"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 18:1"/>And it happened after this that David struck down the Philistines, and he humbled them. And he took Gath and its daughters from the hand of the Philistines.<verse eid="1CH 18:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 18:2"/>And he struck down Moab, and the Moabites became servants to David, carriers of tribute.<verse eid="1CH 18:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 18:3"/>And David struck down Hadadezer, the king of Zobah Hamath, when he went to set up his hand at the Euphrates River.<verse eid="1CH 18:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 18:4"/>And David captured from him 1,000 chariots, and 7,000 horsemen, and 20,000 men on foot. And David hamstrung all the chariots, but spared from him 100 chariots.<verse eid="1CH 18:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 18:5"/>And Aram of Damascus came to help Hadadezer the king of Zobah, and David struck down of the Arameans 22,000 men.<verse eid="1CH 18:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 18:6"/>And David set up in Aram of Damascus, and Aram became servants to David, carriers of tribute. And Yahweh saved David in all where he went.<verse eid="1CH 18:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 18:7"/>And David took the shields of gold that were on the servants of Hadadezer, and he brought them to Jerusalem.<verse eid="1CH 18:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 18:8"/>And from Tibhath and from Kun, cities of Hadadezer, David took very much bronze. With it, Solomon made the sea of bronze and the pillars and bronze items.<verse eid="1CH 18:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 18:9"/>And Tou, the king of Hamath, heard that David struck down all the army of Hadadezer, the king of Zobah.<verse eid="1CH 18:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 18:10"/>And he sent Hadoram his son to King David to ask him for peace and to bless him because he had fought against Hadadezer and struck him down, for a man of war Tou was with Hadadezer, and all the items of gold and silver and bronze.<verse eid="1CH 18:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 18:11"/>Also these King David consecrated to Yahweh with the silver and the gold that he carried away from all the nations: from Edom, and from Moab, and from the sons of Ammon, and from the Philistines, and from Amalek.<verse eid="1CH 18:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 18:12"/>And Abishai the son of Zeruiah struck down Edom in the Valley of Salt, 18,000.<verse eid="1CH 18:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 18:13"/>And he set in Edom garrisons, and all Edom became servants to David. And Yahweh saved David in all where he went.<verse eid="1CH 18:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 18:14"/>And David reigned over all Israel. And it happened he was doing judgment and righteousness for all his people.<verse eid="1CH 18:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CH 18:15"/>And Joab the son of Zeruiah was over the army, and Jehoshaphat the son of Ahilud, secretary.<verse eid="1CH 18:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CH 18:16"/>And Zadok the son of Ahitub and Ahimelech the son of Abiathar, priests, and Shavsha, scribe.<verse eid="1CH 18:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CH 18:17"/>And Benaiah the son of Jehoiada was over the Kerethites and the Pelethites, and the sons of David, the heads at the hand of the king.<verse eid="1CH 18:17"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 18"/>
<chapter number="19" style="c" sid="1CH 19"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 19:1"/>And it happened after this, and Nahash, the king of the sons of Ammon, died, and his son reigned in his place.<verse eid="1CH 19:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 19:2"/>And David said, “I will do loyal kindness to Hanun the son of Nahash, because his father did to me loyal kindness.” And David sent messengers to comfort him concerning his father. And the servants of David came to the land of the sons of Ammon, to Hanun, to comfort him.<verse eid="1CH 19:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 19:3"/>And the chiefs of the sons of Ammon said to Hanun, “Is David honoring your father in your eyes because he sent to you comforters? Is it not for the sake of to explore and to overthrow and to spy the land his servants came to you?”<verse eid="1CH 19:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 19:4"/>And Hanun took the servants of David, and he shaved them, and he cut their garments in half, until the buttocks, and he sent them away.<verse eid="1CH 19:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 19:5"/>And they went, and they declared to David concerning the men. And he sent to meet them for the men were greatly humiliated. And the king said, “Stay in Jericho until when your beards grow, then return.”<verse eid="1CH 19:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 19:6"/>And the sons of Ammon saw that they were a stench to David, and Hanun sent, and the sons of Ammon, 1,000 talents of silver to hire for themselves from Aram Naharaim, and from Aram Maacah, and from Zobah, chariots and horsemen.<verse eid="1CH 19:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 19:7"/>And they hired for themselves 32,000 chariots and the king of Maacah and his people. And they came, and they encamped before the face of Medeba. And the sons of Ammon assembled from their cities, and came to battle.<verse eid="1CH 19:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 19:8"/>And David heard, and he sent Joab and all the army of mighty ones.<verse eid="1CH 19:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 19:9"/>And the sons of Ammon came out, and they arrayed for battle at the entrance of the city. And the kings who came were by themselves in the field.<verse eid="1CH 19:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 19:10"/>And Joab saw that the face of the battle was to him faces and hindquarter, and he chose from all the choice ones among Israel, and he arrayed to meet Aram.<verse eid="1CH 19:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 19:11"/>And the remainder of the people he placed in the hand of Abishai his brother, and they arrayed to meet the sons of Ammon.<verse eid="1CH 19:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 19:12"/>And he said, “If Aram is too strong for me, then you shall be to me for salvation. And if the sons of Ammon are too strong for you, then I will save you.<verse eid="1CH 19:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 19:13"/>Be strong, and let us strengthen ourselves on behalf of our people and on behalf of the cities of our God, and Yahweh, the good in his eyes, he will do.”<verse eid="1CH 19:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 19:14"/>And Joab drew near, and the people who were with him, before the faces of Aram for battle. And they fled from his face.<verse eid="1CH 19:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CH 19:15"/>And the sons of Ammon saw that Aram fled, and these also fled from the face of Abishai his brother. And they came to the city and Joab came to Jerusalem.<verse eid="1CH 19:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CH 19:16"/>And Aram saw that they were defeated before the face of Israel. And they sent messengers, and they brought out Aram, who was beyond the river, and Shophak the chief of the army of Hadadezer before their faces.<verse eid="1CH 19:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CH 19:17"/>And it was told to David, and he gathered all Israel. And he passed over the Jordan, and he came to them. And he arrayed against them. And David arrayed to meet Aram for battle, and they fought with him.<verse eid="1CH 19:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CH 19:18"/>And Aram fled from before the face of Israel, and David killed from Aram 7,000 chariots and 40,000 men on foot. And Shophak the chief of the army, he killed.<verse eid="1CH 19:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CH 19:19"/>And the servants of Hadadezer saw that they were defeated before the face of Israel, and they made peace with David, and they served him. And Aram was not willing to save the sons of Ammon again.<verse eid="1CH 19:19"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 19"/>
<chapter number="20" style="c" sid="1CH 20"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 20:1"/>And it happened at the time of the turning of the year, at the time of the going out of kings, that Joab led out the army for war and he devastated the land of the sons of Ammon. And he came, and he besieged Rabbah. And David stayed in Jerusalem. And Joab struck down Rabbah, and he tore it down.<verse eid="1CH 20:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 20:2"/>And David took the crown of their king from on his head, and he found the weight was a talent of gold, and in it was a precious stone. And it was on the head of David, and the plunder of the city he brought out, a very great amount.<verse eid="1CH 20:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 20:3"/>And the people who were in it, he brought out, and they sawed with saws and with sharp instruments of iron and with saws. And thus David did to all the cities of the sons of Ammon. Then David and all the people returned to Jerusalem.<verse eid="1CH 20:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 20:4"/>And it happened after this that war arose at Gezer with the Philistines. Then Sibbekai the Hushathite struck down Sippai, from the descendants of the Rephaim, and they were humbled.<verse eid="1CH 20:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 20:5"/>And there was again war with the Philistines, and Elhanan the son of Jair struck down Lahmi the brother of Goliath the Gittite; and the wood of his spear was like a beam of a weaver.<verse eid="1CH 20:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 20:6"/>And there was again war in Gath. And there was a man of stature. And his digits were six and six, 24, and he also was born of Rapha.<verse eid="1CH 20:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 20:7"/>And he taunted Israel. And Jonathan the son of Shimea, the brother of David, struck him down.<verse eid="1CH 20:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 20:8"/>These were born to Rapha in Gath, and they fell by the hand of David and by the hand of his servants.<verse eid="1CH 20:8"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 20"/>
<chapter number="21" style="c" sid="1CH 21"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 21:1"/>And an adversary stood against Israel, and he incited David to count Israel.<verse eid="1CH 21:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 21:2"/>And David said to Joab and to the chiefs of the people, “Go, count Israel from Beersheba and as far as Dan, and bring to me, that I may know their number.”<verse eid="1CH 21:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 21:3"/>And Joab said, “May Yahweh add to his people like them 100 times. Are not, my lord the king, all of them servants to my lord? Why does my lord seek this? Why should it be guilt for Israel?”<verse eid="1CH 21:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 21:4"/>But the word of the king was strong against Joab. So Joab went out and walked back and forth in all Israel. Then he came to Jerusalem.<verse eid="1CH 21:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 21:5"/>And Joab gave the number of the numbering of the people to David. And all Israel was 1,100,000 men who drew the sword, and Judah, 470,000 men who drew the sword.<verse eid="1CH 21:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 21:6"/>But Levi and Benjamin he did not number in their midst, for the word of the king was abhorrent to Joab.<verse eid="1CH 21:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 21:7"/>And it was evil in the eyes of God concerning this word, and he struck Israel.<verse eid="1CH 21:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 21:8"/>And David said to God, “I have sinned greatly in that I have done this thing. And now please cause to pass the iniquity of your servant, for I have acted very foolishly.”<verse eid="1CH 21:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 21:9"/>And Yahweh spoke to Gad, the seer of David, saying,<verse eid="1CH 21:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 21:10"/>“Go and speak to David, saying, ‘Thus says Yahweh, three I am stretching over you; choose for yourself one from them, and I will act towards you.’”<verse eid="1CH 21:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 21:11"/>And Gad came to David, and he said to him, “Thus says Yahweh, ‘Take for yourself:<verse eid="1CH 21:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 21:12"/>either three years famine, or three months being swept away from the faces of your foes and overtaken by the sword of your enemies, or three days of the sword of Yahweh, even pestilence in the land and the angel of Yahweh destroying in all the territory of Israel.’ And now, see; what word shall I bring back to the one who sent me?”<verse eid="1CH 21:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 21:13"/>And David said to Gad, “There is great distress to me! Please let me fall into the hand of Yahweh, for many are his great mercies, but into the hand of man, do not let me fall.”<verse eid="1CH 21:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 21:14"/>And Yahweh gave a pestilence on Israel, and from Israel fell 70,000 men.<verse eid="1CH 21:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CH 21:15"/>And God sent an angel to Jerusalem to destroy her. And when destroying, Yahweh saw, and he relented concerning the disaster. And he said to the angel who was destroying, “Enough! Now release your hand.” And the angel of Yahweh was standing at the threshing floor of Ornan the Jebusite.<verse eid="1CH 21:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CH 21:16"/>And David lifted his eyes and saw the angel of Yahweh standing between the earth and between the heavens and his sword drawn in his hand stretched out over Jerusalem. And David fell, and the elders, covered in sackcloth, on their faces.<verse eid="1CH 21:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CH 21:17"/>And David said to God, “Was it not I myself who said to count the people? And it is I who sinned, and I have surely done evil, but these sheep, what have they done? Yahweh my God, please let your hand be against me and against the house of my father, but not on your people a plague.”<verse eid="1CH 21:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CH 21:18"/>And the angel of Yahweh said to Gad to say to David that David should go up to raise an altar to Yahweh at the threshing floor of Ornan the Jebusite.<verse eid="1CH 21:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CH 21:19"/>So David went up at the word of Gad who spoke in the name of Yahweh.<verse eid="1CH 21:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CH 21:20"/>And Ornan turned, and he saw the angel. And four of his sons with him were hiding themselves. And Ornan was threshing wheat.<verse eid="1CH 21:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CH 21:21"/>And David came to Ornan. And Ornan looked, and he saw David. And he went out from the threshing floor, and he bowed down to David, face to the ground.<verse eid="1CH 21:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CH 21:22"/>And David said to Ornan, “Give to me the place of the threshing floor, and I will build on it an altar to Yahweh. At the full price give it to me, so the plague may be restrained from against the people.”<verse eid="1CH 21:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CH 21:23"/>And Ornan said to David, “Take for yourself that my lord the king may do good in his eyes. See, I give the cattle for the burnt offerings and the threshing sledges for wood, and the wheat for the offering; all I give.”<verse eid="1CH 21:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CH 21:24"/>And King David said to Ornan, “No, for I will surely buy at the full price, for I will not lift up what is yours to Yahweh and offer a burnt offering without paying compensation.”<verse eid="1CH 21:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CH 21:25"/>And David gave to Ornan for the place 600 shekels of gold by weight.<verse eid="1CH 21:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CH 21:26"/>And David built there an altar to Yahweh and he offered burnt offerings and peace offerings. And he called to Yahweh, and he answered him with fire from the heavens on the altar of the burnt offering.<verse eid="1CH 21:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CH 21:27"/>And Yahweh spoke to the angel, and he returned his sword to its sheath.<verse eid="1CH 21:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CH 21:28"/>At that time, when David saw that Yahweh had answered him at the threshing floor of Ornan the Jebusite, then he sacrificed there.<verse eid="1CH 21:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CH 21:29"/>And the tabernacle of Yahweh which Moses made in the wilderness and the altar of the burnt offering at that time were at the high place at Gibeon.<verse eid="1CH 21:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CH 21:30"/>And David was not able to go to its face to seek God, for he was terrified from the faces of the sword of the angel of Yahweh.<verse eid="1CH 21:30"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 21"/>
<chapter number="22" style="c" sid="1CH 22"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 22:1"/>And David said, “This is the house of Yahweh God, and this is the altar for the burnt offering of Israel.”<verse eid="1CH 22:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 22:2"/>And David said to gather the foreigners who were in the land of Israel. And he assigned stonemasons to hew out cut stones to build the house of God.<verse eid="1CH 22:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 22:3"/>And a large amount of iron for the nails for the doors of the gates and for braces, David prepared; and a large amount of bronze, there is no weighing.<verse eid="1CH 22:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 22:4"/>And trees of cedar without number, for the Sidonians and the Tyrians brought a large amount of cedar trees to David.<verse eid="1CH 22:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 22:5"/>And David said, “Solomon my son is young and tender, and the house to be built for Yahweh must be great for the sake of a name and for beauty in all the lands. I will now prepare for it.” And David prepared a large amount before the face of his death.<verse eid="1CH 22:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 22:6"/>And he called for Solomon his son, and he commanded him to build a house for Yahweh, the God of Israel.<verse eid="1CH 22:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 22:7"/>And David said to Solomon, “My son, it was with my heart to build a house myself for the name of Yahweh my God.<verse eid="1CH 22:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 22:8"/>But the word of Yahweh was to me, saying, ‘A large amount of blood you have shed and great wars you have made; you shall not build a house for my name because a large amount of blood you have shed on the ground before my face.<verse eid="1CH 22:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 22:9"/>Behold, a son is being born to you; he himself will be a man of rest. And I will give rest to him from all his enemies from all around. For Solomon will be his name, and peace and quietness I will give to Israel in his days.<verse eid="1CH 22:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 22:10"/>He himself will build a house for my name. And he himself will be to me a son, and I to him a father. And I will establish the throne of his kingdom over Israel as far as forever.’<verse eid="1CH 22:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 22:11"/>Now, my son, may Yahweh be with you, and may you be successful and build a house of Yahweh your God, just as he spoke concerning you.<verse eid="1CH 22:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 22:12"/>Only may Yahweh give to you insight and understanding, and give you charge over Israel so that you may keep the law of Yahweh your God.<verse eid="1CH 22:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 22:13"/>Then you will succeed, if you are careful to do the statutes and the judgments which Yahweh commanded Moses concerning Israel. Be strong and courageous. Do not fear and do not be dismayed.<verse eid="1CH 22:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 22:14"/>Now, see, in my affliction, I have prepared for the house of Yahweh gold talents, 100,000, and silver, 1,000,000 talents, and for bronze and for iron, there is no weighing, for there is a large amount. And trees and stones I have prepared. And to them you will add.<verse eid="1CH 22:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CH 22:15"/>And with you is a large amount of doers of work: stonemasons, and craftsmen of stone and wood, and all wise in all work,<verse eid="1CH 22:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CH 22:16"/>for gold, for silver, and for bronze, and for iron; there is no numbering. Arise and work. And may Yahweh be with you.”<verse eid="1CH 22:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CH 22:17"/>And David commanded all the chiefs of Israel to help Solomon his son,<verse eid="1CH 22:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CH 22:18"/>“Is not Yahweh your God with you all and given rest to you all from all around? For he has given into my hand the inhabitants of the land, and the land is subdued before the face of Yahweh and before the faces of his people.<verse eid="1CH 22:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CH 22:19"/>Now, give your heart and your life to seek Yahweh your God, and arise and build the sanctuary of Yahweh God to bring the Box of the covenant of Yahweh and the sacred items of God to the house to be built for the name of Yahweh.”<verse eid="1CH 22:19"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 22"/>
<chapter number="23" style="c" sid="1CH 23"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 23:1"/>And David was old and was full of days, and he made Solomon his son king over Israel.<verse eid="1CH 23:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 23:2"/>And he gathered all the chiefs of Israel and the priests and the Levites.<verse eid="1CH 23:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 23:3"/>And the Levites were counted from sons of 30 years and upward and the numbering was by their heads, by males, 38, 000.<verse eid="1CH 23:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 23:4"/>“From these, to lead the work of the house of Yahweh, 24,000, and officers and judges, 6,000,<verse eid="1CH 23:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 23:5"/>and 4,000 gatekeepers and 4,000 praisers to Yahweh with the instruments which I made to praise.”<verse eid="1CH 23:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 23:6"/>And David divided them into divisions according to the sons of Levi: of Gershon, Kohath, and Merari.<verse eid="1CH 23:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 23:7"/>Of the Gershonites: Ladan and Shimei.<verse eid="1CH 23:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 23:8"/>The sons of Ladan: the head Jehiel, and Zetham, and Joel, three.<verse eid="1CH 23:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 23:9"/>The sons of Shimei: Shelomoth, and Haziel, and Haran, three. These, the heads of the fathers of Ladan.<verse eid="1CH 23:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 23:10"/>And the sons of Shimei: Jahath, and Zina, and Jeush, and Beriah. These, the sons of Shimei, four.<verse eid="1CH 23:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 23:11"/>And Jahath was the head, and Zizah the second, but Jeush and Beriah did not have many sons, and they were to a house of a father for one group.<verse eid="1CH 23:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 23:12"/>The sons of Kohath: Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and Uzziel, four.<verse eid="1CH 23:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 23:13"/>The sons of Amram: Aaron and Moses. And Aaron was set apart for him to consecrate the most holy things, he and his sons until forever, to make sacrifices before the face of Yahweh to minister for him and to bless in his name until forever.<verse eid="1CH 23:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 23:14"/>And Moses, the man of God, his sons were called according to the tribe of Levi.<verse eid="1CH 23:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CH 23:15"/>The sons of Moses: Gershom and Eliezer.<verse eid="1CH 23:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CH 23:16"/>The sons of Gershom: Shebuel the head.<verse eid="1CH 23:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CH 23:17"/>And the sons of Eliezer were Rehabiah the head, and there were not to Eliezer other sons, but the sons of Rehabiah were many above that.<verse eid="1CH 23:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CH 23:18"/>The sons of Izhar: Shelomith the head.<verse eid="1CH 23:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CH 23:19"/>The sons of Hebron: Jeriah the head, Amariah the second, Jahaziel the third, and Jekameam the fourth.<verse eid="1CH 23:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CH 23:20"/>The sons of Uzziel: Micah the head, and Isshiah the second.<verse eid="1CH 23:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CH 23:21"/>The sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi. The sons of Mahli: Eleazar and Kish.<verse eid="1CH 23:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CH 23:22"/>And Eleazar died and there were not to him sons, but only daughters. And the sons of Kish, their brothers, lifted them.<verse eid="1CH 23:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CH 23:23"/>The sons of Mushi: Mahli, and Eder, and Jerimoth, three.<verse eid="1CH 23:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CH 23:24"/>These were the sons of Levi according to the house of their fathers, heads of the fathers, by their appointments, in the numbering of names by their heads, the doer of the work of the service of the house of Yahweh; from the sons of 20 years and upward.<verse eid="1CH 23:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CH 23:25"/>For David said, “Yahweh, the God of Israel, has given rest to his people. And he dwells in Jerusalem until forever.<verse eid="1CH 23:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CH 23:26"/>And also, for the Levites, no longer to carry the tabernacle and all its items for its service.”<verse eid="1CH 23:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CH 23:27"/>For by the last words of David, they were numbering the sons of Levi, from the sons of 20 years and upward.<verse eid="1CH 23:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CH 23:28"/>For their office was by the hand of the sons of Aaron for the service of the house of Yahweh over the courts, and over the chambers, and over the cleansing of all the sacred things, and the work of the service of the house of God.<verse eid="1CH 23:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CH 23:29"/>And concerning the bread of the arrangement, and concerning the fine flour for the offering, and concerning the wafers of the unleavened bread, and concerning the pan, and concerning that which is mixed, and concerning all measure and size.<verse eid="1CH 23:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CH 23:30"/>And to stand morning by morning to thank and to praise Yahweh, and thus in the evening.<verse eid="1CH 23:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CH 23:31"/>And concerning to offer all the burnt offerings to Yahweh for the Sabbaths, for the new moons, and for the appointed times in the numbering according to the judgment over them regularly before the face of Yahweh.<verse eid="1CH 23:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CH 23:32"/>And they were to keep the charge of the tent of meeting and the charge of the holy place, and the charge of the sons of Aaron their brothers for the service of the house of Yahweh.<verse eid="1CH 23:32"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 23"/>
<chapter number="24" style="c" sid="1CH 24"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 24:1"/>And to the sons of Aaron, their division. The sons of Aaron: Nadab, and Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar.<verse eid="1CH 24:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 24:2"/>And Nadab died, as well as Abihu, before the face of their father, and sons were not to them. And Eleazar and Ithamar became priests.<verse eid="1CH 24:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 24:3"/>And David divided them, along with Zadok from the sons of Eleazar, and Ahimelech from the sons of Ithamar, according to their office in their service.<verse eid="1CH 24:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 24:4"/>And more sons of Eleazar were found for heads of men than the sons of Ithamar, and they divided them for the sons of Eleazar, heads of a house of the fathers, 16, and for the sons of Ithamar for the house of their fathers, eight.<verse eid="1CH 24:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 24:5"/>And they divided them by lots, these with these, for there were sacred chiefs and chiefs of God from the sons of Eleazar and in the sons of Ithamar.<verse eid="1CH 24:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 24:6"/>And Shemaiah the son of Nethanel the scribe from the Levites wrote them before the face of the king, and the chiefs, and Zadok the priest, and Ahimelech the son of Abiathar, and the heads of the fathers for the priests and for the Levites. One house of a father was picked for Eleazar, and one was picked for Ithamar.<verse eid="1CH 24:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 24:7"/>And the first lot went to Jehoiarib, to Jedaiah the second,<verse eid="1CH 24:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 24:8"/>to Harim the third, to Seorim the fourth,<verse eid="1CH 24:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 24:9"/>to Malkijah the fifth, to Mijamin the sixth,<verse eid="1CH 24:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 24:10"/>to Hakkoz the seventh, to Abijah the eighth,<verse eid="1CH 24:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 24:11"/>to Jeshua the ninth, to Shecaniah the tenth,<verse eid="1CH 24:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 24:12"/>to Eliashib the 11th, to Jakim the 12th,<verse eid="1CH 24:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 24:13"/>to Huppah the 13th, to Jeshebeab the 14th,<verse eid="1CH 24:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 24:14"/>to Bilgah the 15th, to Immer the 16th,<verse eid="1CH 24:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CH 24:15"/>to Hezir the 17th, to Happizzez the 18th,<verse eid="1CH 24:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CH 24:16"/>to Pethahiah the 19th, to Jehezkel the 20th,<verse eid="1CH 24:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CH 24:17"/>to Jakin the 21st, to Gamul the 22nd,<verse eid="1CH 24:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CH 24:18"/>to Delaiah the 23rd, to Maaziah the 24th.<verse eid="1CH 24:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CH 24:19"/>These, their office for their service to come into the house of Yahweh, according to the judgments by the hand of Aaron their father, just as Yahweh the God of Israel commanded him.<verse eid="1CH 24:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CH 24:20"/>And to the sons of Levi, the ones who are left, of the sons of Amram, Shubael; of the sons of Shubael, Jehdeiah.<verse eid="1CH 24:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CH 24:21"/>To Rehabiah, of the sons of Rehabiah, the head Ishijah.<verse eid="1CH 24:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CH 24:22"/>To the Izharites, Shelomoth, of the sons of Shelomoth, Jahath.<verse eid="1CH 24:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CH 24:23"/>And the sons of Jeriah, Amariah the second, Jahaziel the third, and Jekameam the fourth.<verse eid="1CH 24:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CH 24:24"/>The sons of Uzziel, Micah, of the sons of Micah, Shamir.<verse eid="1CH 24:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CH 24:25"/>The brother of Micah, Ishijah, of the sons of Ishijah, Zechariah.<verse eid="1CH 24:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CH 24:26"/>The sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi. The sons of Jaaziah: Beno.<verse eid="1CH 24:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CH 24:27"/>The sons of Merari, of Jaaziah: Beno, and Shoham, and Zaccur, and Ibri.<verse eid="1CH 24:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CH 24:28"/>To Mahli, Eleazar, and not were to him sons.<verse eid="1CH 24:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CH 24:29"/>To Kish, the sons of Kish, Jerahmeel.<verse eid="1CH 24:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CH 24:30"/>And the sons of Mushi: Mahli, and Eder, and Jerimoth. These, the sons of the Levites, according to the house of their fathers.<verse eid="1CH 24:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CH 24:31"/>And these also cast lots just like their brothers, the sons of Aaron, before the face of King David, along with Zadok and Ahimelech and the heads of the fathers, for the priests and for the Levites; the fathers of the head just like his younger brother.<verse eid="1CH 24:31"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 24"/>
<chapter number="25" style="c" sid="1CH 25"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 25:1"/>And David and the chiefs of the army divided for the service for the sons of Asaph, and Heman, and Jeduthun, the ones prophesying with harps, with lyres, and with cymbals. And the numbering of the men of work for their service was:<verse eid="1CH 25:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 25:2"/>Of the sons of Asaph: Zaccur, and Joseph, and Nethaniah, and Asharelah, the sons of Asaph, under the hand of Asaph, who was prophesying under the hands of the king.<verse eid="1CH 25:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 25:3"/>Of Jeduthun, the sons of Jeduthun: Gedaliah, and Zeri, and Jeshaiah, Hashabiah, and Mattithiah, six, under the hands of their father Jeduthun, with the harp one prophesying, for giving thanks and to praise Yahweh.<verse eid="1CH 25:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 25:4"/>Of Heman, the sons of Heman: Bukkiah, Mattaniah, Uzziel, Shubael, and Jerimoth, Hananiah, Hanani, Eliathah, Giddalti, and Romamti-Ezer, Joshbekashah, Mallothi, Hothir, Mahazioth.<verse eid="1CH 25:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 25:5"/>All these, the sons of Heman, the seer of the king by the words of God to lift up a horn. And God gave to Heman 14 sons and three daughters.<verse eid="1CH 25:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 25:6"/>All these, under the hands of their father in the song of the house of Yahweh, with cymbals, harps, and lyres for the service of the house of God under the hands of the king: Asaph, and Jeduthun, and Heman.<verse eid="1CH 25:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 25:7"/>And their numbering with their brothers who were taught the song of Yahweh, all the ones who understand, 288.<verse eid="1CH 25:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 25:8"/>And they cast lots for a charge, small and great alike, one who understands with a student.<verse eid="1CH 25:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 25:9"/>And the first lot went to Asaph, to Joseph; Gedaliah the second, he and his brothers and his sons, 12.<verse eid="1CH 25:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 25:10"/>The third Zaccur, his sons and his brothers, 12.<verse eid="1CH 25:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 25:11"/>The fourth to Izri, his sons and his brothers, 12;<verse eid="1CH 25:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 25:12"/>The fifth Nethaniah, his sons and his brothers, 12.<verse eid="1CH 25:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 25:13"/>The sixth Bukkiah, his sons and his brothers, 12.<verse eid="1CH 25:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 25:14"/>The seventh Jesarelah, his sons and his brothers, 12.<verse eid="1CH 25:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CH 25:15"/>The eighth Jeshaiah, his sons and his brothers, 12.<verse eid="1CH 25:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CH 25:16"/>The ninth Mattaniah, his sons and his brothers, 12.<verse eid="1CH 25:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CH 25:17"/>The tenth Shimei, his sons and his brothers, 12.<verse eid="1CH 25:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CH 25:18"/>The 11th Azarel, his sons and his brothers, 12.<verse eid="1CH 25:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CH 25:19"/>The 12th to Hashabiah, his sons and his brothers, 12.<verse eid="1CH 25:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CH 25:20"/>For the 13th Shubael, his sons and his brothers, 12.<verse eid="1CH 25:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CH 25:21"/>For the 14th Mattithiah, his sons and his brothers, 12.<verse eid="1CH 25:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CH 25:22"/>For the 15th to Jerimoth, his sons and his brothers, 12.<verse eid="1CH 25:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CH 25:23"/>For the 16th to Hananiah, his sons and his brothers, 12.<verse eid="1CH 25:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CH 25:24"/>For the 17th to Joshbekashah, his sons and his brothers, 12.<verse eid="1CH 25:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CH 25:25"/>For the 18th to Hanani, his sons and his brothers, 12.<verse eid="1CH 25:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CH 25:26"/>For the 19th to Mallothi, his sons and his brothers, 12.<verse eid="1CH 25:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CH 25:27"/>For the 20th to Eliathah, his sons and his brothers, 12.<verse eid="1CH 25:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CH 25:28"/>For the 21st to Hothir, his sons and his brothers, 12.<verse eid="1CH 25:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CH 25:29"/>For the 22nd to Giddalti, his sons and his brothers, 12.<verse eid="1CH 25:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CH 25:30"/>For the 23rd to Mahazioth, his sons and his brothers, 12.<verse eid="1CH 25:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CH 25:31"/>For the 24th to Romamti-Ezer, his sons and his brothers, 12.<verse eid="1CH 25:31"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 25"/>
<chapter number="26" style="c" sid="1CH 26"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 26:1"/>For the divisions of the gatekeepers: Of the Korahites, Meshelemiah the son of Kore, from the sons of Asaph.<verse eid="1CH 26:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 26:2"/>And to Meshelemiah sons: Zechariah the firstborn, Jediael the second, Zebadiah the third, Jathniel the fourth,<verse eid="1CH 26:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 26:3"/>Elam the fifth, Jehohanan the sixth, Eliehoenai the seventh.<verse eid="1CH 26:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 26:4"/>And to Obed Edom sons: Shemaiah the firstborn, Jehozabad the second, Joah the third, and Sakar the fourth, and Nethanel the fifth,<verse eid="1CH 26:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 26:5"/>Ammiel the sixth, Issachar the seventh, Peullethai the eighth, for God blessed him.<verse eid="1CH 26:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 26:6"/>And to Shemaiah his son were born sons, rulers in the house of their fathers; for mighty ones of strength they were.<verse eid="1CH 26:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 26:7"/>The sons of Shemaiah: Othni, and Rephael, and Obed, Elzabad his brothers, sons of strength, Elihu and Semakiah.<verse eid="1CH 26:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 26:8"/>All these from the sons of Obed Edom. They and their sons and their brothers, men of strength with power for service, 62 of Obed Edom.<verse eid="1CH 26:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 26:9"/>And to Meshelemiah sons and brothers, sons of strength, 18.<verse eid="1CH 26:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 26:10"/>And to Hosah, from the sons of Merari, sons: Shimri the head, although he was not firstborn, and his father set him as head,<verse eid="1CH 26:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 26:11"/>Hilkiah the second, Tabaliah the third, Zechariah the fourth. All the sons and brothers to Hosah, 13.<verse eid="1CH 26:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 26:12"/>To these divisions of the gatekeepers, to the head males a charge just like their brothers to minister in the house of Yahweh.<verse eid="1CH 26:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 26:13"/>And they cast lots, like small like great, according to the house of their fathers for gate and gate.<verse eid="1CH 26:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 26:14"/>And the lot fell to the east, to Shelemiah and Zechariah his son, an advisor with insight. And they cast lots and his lot went to the north.<verse eid="1CH 26:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CH 26:15"/>To Obed Edom to the south, and to his sons, the house of stores.<verse eid="1CH 26:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CH 26:16"/>To Shuppim and to Hosah, to the west with the gate of Shalleketh on the road that goes up; a guard alongside a guard.<verse eid="1CH 26:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CH 26:17"/>To the east six Levites, to the north per day four, to the south per day four, and to the stores two by two.<verse eid="1CH 26:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CH 26:18"/>At the colonnade to the west, four at the highway, two at the colonnade.<verse eid="1CH 26:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CH 26:19"/>These, the divisions of the gatekeepers for the sons of the Korahites and for the sons of Merari.<verse eid="1CH 26:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CH 26:20"/>And the Levites, Ahijah over the treasuries of the house of God and of the treasuries of the sacred things.<verse eid="1CH 26:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CH 26:21"/>The sons of Ladan, the sons of the Gershonites belonging to Ladan, the heads of the fathers, belonging to Ladan the Gershonite, Jehieli.<verse eid="1CH 26:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CH 26:22"/>The sons of Jehieli: Zetham and Joel his brother, over the treasuries of the house of Yahweh.<verse eid="1CH 26:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CH 26:23"/>Of the Amramites, of the Izharites, of the Hebronites, of the Uzzielites:<verse eid="1CH 26:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CH 26:24"/>And Shubael the son of Gershom, the son of Moses, a leader over the treasuries,<verse eid="1CH 26:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CH 26:25"/>and his brothers; to Eliezer, Rehabiah his son, and Jeshaiah his son, and Joram his son, and Zichri his son, and Shelomith his son.<verse eid="1CH 26:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CH 26:26"/>This Shelomith and his brothers were over all the treasuries of the sacred things which David the king consecrated, and the heads of the fathers, of the chiefs of thousands and hundreds, and the chiefs of the army.<verse eid="1CH 26:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CH 26:27"/>From battles and from plunder they consecrated to strengthen the house of Yahweh.<verse eid="1CH 26:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CH 26:28"/>And all Samuel the seer consecrated, and Saul the son of Kish, and Abner the son of Ner, and Joab the son of Zeruiah. All the sacred things were under the hand of Shelomith and his brothers.<verse eid="1CH 26:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CH 26:29"/>Of the Izharites, Kenaniah and his sons to the work of the outside for Israel as officers and judges.<verse eid="1CH 26:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CH 26:30"/>Of the Hebronites, Hashabiah and his brothers, sons of strength, 1,700, over appointment of Israel from beyond the Jordan to the west for all the work of Yahweh and for the service of the king.<verse eid="1CH 26:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CH 26:31"/>Of the Hebronites, Jeriah the head of the Hebronites according to his generations of fathers. In the 40th year of the reign of David they were sought out and there were found among them mighty ones of strength in Jazer of Gilead,<verse eid="1CH 26:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CH 26:32"/>and his brothers, sons of strength, 2,700 heads of the fathers. And David the king appointed them over the Reubenites and the Gadites and the half tribe of Manasseh, for every matter of God, and matter of the king.<verse eid="1CH 26:32"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 26"/>
<chapter number="27" style="c" sid="1CH 27"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 27:1"/>And the sons of Israel, for the numbering of the heads of the fathers and the chiefs of thousands and hundreds, and their officers of those who minister to the king for any matter of the divisions who come and go month by month for all months of the year, one division, 24, 000.<verse eid="1CH 27:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 27:2"/>Over the first division for the first month, Jashobeam the son of Zabdiel, and over his division, 24, 000.<verse eid="1CH 27:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 27:3"/>From the sons of Perez the head of all the chiefs of the armies for the first month.<verse eid="1CH 27:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 27:4"/>And over the division for the second month, Dodai the Ahohite and his division, and Mikloth the leader, and over his division, 24,000.<verse eid="1CH 27:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 27:5"/>The third chief of the army for the third month, Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, the head priest, and over his division, 24,000.<verse eid="1CH 27:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 27:6"/>This Benaiah the mighty one of the 30, and over the 30 and his division, Ammizabad his son.<verse eid="1CH 27:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 27:7"/>The fourth for the fourth month, Asahel brother of Joab and Zebadiah his son after him, and over his division, 24,000.<verse eid="1CH 27:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 27:8"/>The fifth for the fifth month, the chief Shamhuth the Izrahite, and over his division, 24,000.<verse eid="1CH 27:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 27:9"/>The sixth for the sixth month, Ira the son of Ikkesh the Tekoite, and over his division, 24,000.<verse eid="1CH 27:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 27:10"/>The seventh for the seventh month, Helez the Pelonite, from the sons of Ephraim, and over his division, 24,000.<verse eid="1CH 27:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 27:11"/>The eighth for the eighth month, Sibbekai the Hushathite, of the Zerahites, and over his division, 24,000.<verse eid="1CH 27:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 27:12"/>The ninth for the ninth month, Abiezer the Anathothite, of the Benjaminites, and over his division, 24,000.<verse eid="1CH 27:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 27:13"/>The tenth for the tenth month, Maharai the Netophahite, of the Zerahites, and over his division, 24,000.<verse eid="1CH 27:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 27:14"/>The 11th for the 11th month, Benaiah the Pirathonite, from the sons of Ephraim, and over his division, 24,000.<verse eid="1CH 27:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CH 27:15"/>The 12th for the 12th month, Heldai the Netophahite, of Othniel, and over his division, 24,000.<verse eid="1CH 27:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CH 27:16"/>And over the tribes of Israel: for the Reubenites, a leader, Eliezer the son of Zichri; for the Simeonites, Shephatiah the son of Maacah;<verse eid="1CH 27:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CH 27:17"/>for the Levites, Hashabiah the son of Kemuel; for Aaron, Zadok;<verse eid="1CH 27:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CH 27:18"/>for Judah, Elihu, from the brothers of David; for Issachar, Omri the son of Michael;<verse eid="1CH 27:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CH 27:19"/>for Zebulun, Ishmaiah the son of Obadiah; for Naphtali, Jerimoth the son of Azriel;<verse eid="1CH 27:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CH 27:20"/>for the sons of Ephraim, Hoshea the son of Azaziah; for the half tribe of Manasseh, Joel the son of Pedaiah;<verse eid="1CH 27:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CH 27:21"/>for the half of Manasseh in Gilead, Iddo the son of Zechariah; for Benjamin, Jaasiel the son of Abner;<verse eid="1CH 27:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CH 27:22"/>for Dan, Azarel the son of Jeroham. These, the chiefs of the tribes of Israel.<verse eid="1CH 27:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CH 27:23"/>And David did not lift the numbering for sons of 20 years and downwards, because Yahweh said he would multiply Israel like the stars of the heavens.<verse eid="1CH 27:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CH 27:24"/>Joab the son of Zeruiah began to count, but he did not finish. And there was among this wrath on Israel. And the number did not go up into the number of the matters of the days of King David.<verse eid="1CH 27:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CH 27:25"/>And over the treasuries of the king, Azmaveth the son of Adiel. And over the treasuries in the field, in the cities, and in the villages, and in the towers, Jonathan the son of Uzziah.<verse eid="1CH 27:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CH 27:26"/>And over the ones who do the work of the field, for the service of the ground, Ezri the son of Kelub.<verse eid="1CH 27:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CH 27:27"/>And over the vineyards, Shimei the Ramathite. And over what is in the vineyards for the treasuries of the wine, Zabdi the Shiphmite.<verse eid="1CH 27:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CH 27:28"/>And over the olive trees and the sycamore trees which were in the lowlands, Baal-Hanan the Gederite. And over the treasuries of the oil, Joash.<verse eid="1CH 27:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CH 27:29"/>And over the herd pasturing in Sharon, Shitrai the Sharonite. And over the herd in the valleys, Shaphat the son of Adlai.<verse eid="1CH 27:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CH 27:30"/>And over the camels, Obil the Ishmaelite. And over the female donkeys, Jehdeiah the Meronothite.<verse eid="1CH 27:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="1CH 27:31"/>And over the flock, Jaziz the Hagrite. All these, the chiefs of the property which belonged to King David.<verse eid="1CH 27:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="1CH 27:32"/>And Jonathan, the uncle of David, an advisor, a man of understanding and a scribe, was he. And Jehiel the son of Hakmoni was with the sons of the king.<verse eid="1CH 27:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="1CH 27:33"/>And Ahithophel, an advisor to the king, and Hushai the Arkite, friend to the king.<verse eid="1CH 27:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="1CH 27:34"/>And after Ahithophel, Jehoiada the son of Benaiah and Abiathar. And the chief of the army of the king, Joab.<verse eid="1CH 27:34"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 27"/>
<chapter number="28" style="c" sid="1CH 28"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 28:1"/>And David called to assembly all the chiefs of Israel: the chiefs of the tribes, and the chiefs of the divisions who served the king, and the chiefs of the thousands, and the chiefs of the hundreds, and the chiefs of all the property and cattle belonging to the king and to his sons, with the high officials, and the mighty ones, and to all the mighty ones of strength, to Jerusalem.<verse eid="1CH 28:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 28:2"/>And David the king rose to his feet, and he said, “Hear me, my brothers and my people, I had in my heart to build a house of rest for the Box of the covenant of Yahweh and for the footstool of the feet of our God. And I have prepared to build.<verse eid="1CH 28:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 28:3"/>But God said to me, ‘You will not build a house for my name, because a man of war you are and blood you have shed.’<verse eid="1CH 28:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 28:4"/>Yet Yahweh, the God of Israel, chose me from all of the house of my father to be king over Israel forever, for among Judah he chose for a leader, and in the house of Judah, the house of my father, and among the sons of my father, with me he was pleased to make king over all Israel.<verse eid="1CH 28:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 28:5"/>And from all my sons, for many sons Yahweh has given to me, and he chose Solomon my son to sit on the throne of the kingdom of Yahweh over Israel.<verse eid="1CH 28:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 28:6"/>And he said to me, ‘Solomon your son, he himself will build my house and my courts, for I have chosen him for myself for a son, and I myself will be to him for a father.<verse eid="1CH 28:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 28:7"/>And I will establish his kingdom until forever, if he is strong to do my commands and my judgments, like this day.’<verse eid="1CH 28:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 28:8"/>And now, in the eyes of all Israel, the assembly of Yahweh, and in the ears of our God, keep and seek all the commands of Yahweh your God in order that you all will possess the good land and you all will cause your sons after you to inherit until forever.<verse eid="1CH 28:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 28:9"/>And you, Solomon my son, know the God of your father, and serve him with a whole heart and with a willing life, for all hearts Yahweh seeks and all purpose of thoughts understands. If you seek him, he will be found by you, but if you abandon him, he will reject you forever.<verse eid="1CH 28:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 28:10"/>See, now, that Yahweh has chosen you to build a house for the sanctuary. Be strong and act.”<verse eid="1CH 28:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 28:11"/>And David gave to Solomon his son the plan of the porch, and its houses, and its treasuries, and its upper rooms, and its inner rooms, and the house of the atonement lid,<verse eid="1CH 28:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 28:12"/>and the plan of all that was by the Spirit with him for the courts of the house of Yahweh, and for all the chambers all around, for the treasuries of the house of God and for the treasuries of the sacred things,<verse eid="1CH 28:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 28:13"/>and for the divisions of the priests and the Levites, and for all the work of the service of the house of Yahweh, and for all the items of the service of the house of Yahweh,<verse eid="1CH 28:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 28:14"/>for gold by weight, for gold for all the items of service and service, for all the items of silver by weight, for all the items of service and service,<verse eid="1CH 28:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CH 28:15"/>and the weight for the gold lampstands and their gold lamps by weight of lampstand and lampstand and its lamps, and for the lampstands of silver by weight for the lampstand and its lamps, according to the service of lampstand and lampstand,<verse eid="1CH 28:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CH 28:16"/>and the gold weight for the tables of the arrangement, for the table and table, and silver for the tables of silver,<verse eid="1CH 28:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CH 28:17"/>and the forks and the bowls and the jugs of pure gold and for the basins of gold by weight for basin and basin, and for the basins of silver by weight, for basin and basin,<verse eid="1CH 28:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CH 28:18"/>and for the altar of incense, refined gold by weight, and for the plan of the chariot of the cherubim, gold, that spread out and cover over the Box of the covenant of Yahweh.<verse eid="1CH 28:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CH 28:19"/>The entirety in writing from the hand of Yahweh upon me, he instructed all of the works of the plan.”<verse eid="1CH 28:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CH 28:20"/>And David said to Solomon his son, “Be strong and be courageous and act. Do not fear and do not be dismayed for Yahweh God, my God, is with you. He will not leave you and he will not abandon you until all the work of the service of the house of Yahweh is finished.<verse eid="1CH 28:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CH 28:21"/>And behold, the divisions of the priests and the Levites for all the service of the house of God, and with you in all the work will be every willing one with wisdom, for all the service, and the chiefs and all the people for all your ways.”<verse eid="1CH 28:21"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 28"/>
<chapter number="29" style="c" sid="1CH 29"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="1CH 29:1"/>And King David said to all the assembly, “Solomon my son, alone God has chosen him, is young and tender, and the work is great; for not for man is the palace but for Yahweh God.<verse eid="1CH 29:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="1CH 29:2"/>And according to all my power I have provided for the house of my God, the gold for the gold, and the silver for the silver, and the bronze for the bronze, the iron for the iron, and the wood for the wood, stones of onyx and settings, stones of antimony and colorful things, and all the rare stones and alabaster stones, in abundance.<verse eid="1CH 29:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="1CH 29:3"/>And again, in my delighting in the house of my God, possessions belonging to me, gold and silver, I give to the house of my God, above all I have prepared for the sacred house:<verse eid="1CH 29:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="1CH 29:4"/>3,000 talents of gold from the gold of Ophir, and 7,000 talents of refined silver, to overlay the walls of the houses,<verse eid="1CH 29:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="1CH 29:5"/>gold for gold, and silver for silver, and for all the work by the hand of the craftsmen. And who offers freely to fill his hand today to Yahweh?”<verse eid="1CH 29:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="1CH 29:6"/>And the chiefs of the fathers offered freely as well as the chiefs of the tribes of Israel and the chiefs of thousands and hundreds, and the chiefs of the work of the king.<verse eid="1CH 29:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="1CH 29:7"/>And they gave for the service of the house of God gold, 5,000 talents and 10,000 darics, and silver, 10,000 talents, and bronze, 18,000 talents, and iron, 100,000 talents.<verse eid="1CH 29:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="1CH 29:8"/>And he who was found with it, stones, they gave to the treasury of the house of Yahweh, under the hand of Jehiel the Gershonite.<verse eid="1CH 29:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="1CH 29:9"/>And the people rejoiced because they offered freely, for with a whole heart they offered freely to Yahweh. And also King David rejoiced with great joy.<verse eid="1CH 29:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="1CH 29:10"/>And David blessed Yahweh in the eyes of all the assembly. And David said, “Blessed are you, Yahweh, God of Israel, our father, from forever and until forever.<verse eid="1CH 29:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="1CH 29:11"/>To you, Yahweh, the greatness, and the might, and the beauty, and the splendor, and the majesty; indeed, everything in the heavens and in the earth. To you, Yahweh, the kingdom and lifting yourself above all as head.<verse eid="1CH 29:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="1CH 29:12"/>And the riches and the glory from before your face, and you are ruling over all, and in your hand power and might, and in your hand to make great and to strengthen all.<verse eid="1CH 29:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="1CH 29:13"/>And now, our God, we are giving thanks to you and praising the name of your beauty.<verse eid="1CH 29:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="1CH 29:14"/>But who am I, and who are my people, that we should retain power to offer freely like this? For from you is everything, and from your hand we have given to you.<verse eid="1CH 29:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="1CH 29:15"/>For we are foreigners before your face and sojourners, like all our fathers, like the shadow are our days on the earth, and there is no hope.<verse eid="1CH 29:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="1CH 29:16"/>Yahweh our God, all this abundance that we have prepared in order to build for you a house for the name of your holiness, from your hand it is and for you is all.<verse eid="1CH 29:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="1CH 29:17"/>And I know, my God, that you examine the heart and in uprightness are pleased. I, in the uprightness of my heart, I have offered freely all these, and now your people are found here, I see with joy, to offer freely to you.<verse eid="1CH 29:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="1CH 29:18"/>Yahweh, the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Israel—our fathers—keep this forever concerning the purpose of the thoughts of the heart of your people, and direct their hearts to you.<verse eid="1CH 29:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="1CH 29:19"/>And to Solomon my son, give a whole heart to keep your commandments, your testimonies, and your statutes, and to do all and to build the palace for which I have prepared.”<verse eid="1CH 29:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="1CH 29:20"/>And David said to all the assembly, “Bless Yahweh your God.” And all the assembly blessed Yahweh, the God of their fathers. And they bowed down and paid homage to Yahweh and to the king.<verse eid="1CH 29:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="1CH 29:21"/>And they sacrificed to Yahweh sacrifices, and they offered burnt offerings to Yahweh on the day following that day, 1,000 bulls, 1,000 rams, 1,000 lambs, and their drink offerings and sacrifices in abundance for all Israel.<verse eid="1CH 29:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="1CH 29:22"/>And they ate and drank before the face of Yahweh that day with great joy. And they made king a second time Solomon, the son of David, and they anointed for Yahweh for a leader and Zadok for priest.<verse eid="1CH 29:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="1CH 29:23"/>And Solomon sat on the throne of Yahweh as king instead of David his father, and he succeeded. And all Israel listened to him.<verse eid="1CH 29:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="1CH 29:24"/>And all the chiefs, and the mighty ones, and also all the sons of King David gave a hand under King Solomon.<verse eid="1CH 29:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="1CH 29:25"/>And Yahweh made Solomon exceedingly great in the eyes of all Israel. And he bestowed on him majesty of a kingdom which has not been on any king before his face over Israel.<verse eid="1CH 29:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="1CH 29:26"/>And David the son of Jesse reigned over all Israel.<verse eid="1CH 29:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="1CH 29:27"/>And the days which he reigned over Israel, 40 years. In Hebron he reigned seven years, and in Jerusalem he reigned 33.<verse eid="1CH 29:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="1CH 29:28"/>And he died at a good old age, full of days, riches, and glory. And Solomon his son reigned in his place.<verse eid="1CH 29:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="1CH 29:29"/>And the matters of King David, the first things and the last things, behold, they are written in the words of Samuel the Seer, and in the words of Nathan the prophet, and in the words of Gad the prophet,<verse eid="1CH 29:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="1CH 29:30"/>with all his reign and his might and the times which passed over on him, and on Israel, and on all the kingdoms of the lands.<verse eid="1CH 29:30"/></para>
<chapter eid="1CH 29"/>
</usx>