<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<usx version="3.1">
<book code="MRK" style="id">- unfoldingWord Literal -</book>
<para style="h">Mark</para>
<para style="toc1">Mark</para>
<para style="toc2">Mark</para>
<para style="mt1">Mark</para>
<chapter number="1" style="c" sid="MRK 1"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 1:1"/>The beginning of the gospel of Jesus Christ, the Son of God.<verse eid="MRK 1:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 1:2"/>Just as it has been written in Isaiah the prophet, “Behold, I am sending my messenger before your face, who will prepare your way;<verse eid="MRK 1:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 1:3"/>a voice of one calling out in the wilderness, ‘Make ready the way of the Lord; make his paths straight.’”<verse eid="MRK 1:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 1:4"/>John came, the one baptizing in the wilderness and preaching a baptism of repentance for forgiveness of sins.<verse eid="MRK 1:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 1:5"/>And all the Judea region and all the Jerusalemites were going out to him and were being baptized by him in the Jordan River, confessing their sins.<verse eid="MRK 1:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 1:6"/>And John was clothed with camel hair and a leather belt around his waist, and {he was} eating locusts and wild honey.<verse eid="MRK 1:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 1:7"/>And he was proclaiming, saying, “One more powerful than I is coming after me, of whom I am not worthy, stooping down, to untie the strap of his sandals.<verse eid="MRK 1:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 1:8"/>I baptized you with water, but he will baptize you with the Holy Spirit.”<verse eid="MRK 1:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 1:9"/>And it happened that in those days Jesus came from Nazareth in Galilee, and he was baptized by John in the Jordan.<verse eid="MRK 1:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 1:10"/>And immediately, coming up out of the water, he saw the heavens being split open and the Spirit coming down on him like a dove.<verse eid="MRK 1:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 1:11"/>And a voice came out of the heavens, “You are my beloved Son. With you, I am well pleased.”<verse eid="MRK 1:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 1:12"/>And immediately, the Spirit casts him out into the wilderness.<verse eid="MRK 1:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 1:13"/>And he was in the wilderness 40 days, being tempted by Satan. And he was with the wild animals, and the angels were serving him.<verse eid="MRK 1:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 1:14"/>But after John was handed over, Jesus came to Galilee, proclaiming the gospel of God<verse eid="MRK 1:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 1:15"/>and saying, “The time has been fulfilled, and the kingdom of God has come near. Repent and believe in the gospel.”<verse eid="MRK 1:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 1:16"/>And passing beside the Sea of Galilee, he saw Simon and Andrew, the brother of Simon, net-casting into the sea, for they were fishermen.<verse eid="MRK 1:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 1:17"/>And Jesus said to them, “Come after me, and I will make you to become fishers of men.”<verse eid="MRK 1:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 1:18"/>And immediately, having left the nets, they followed him.<verse eid="MRK 1:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 1:19"/>And having gone on a little farther, he saw James, the {son} of Zebedee, and John, his brother, and they {were} mending the nets in the boat.<verse eid="MRK 1:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 1:20"/>And immediately he called them and, having left their father Zebedee in the boat with the hired servants, they went away after him.<verse eid="MRK 1:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 1:21"/>And they enter into Capernaum, and immediately on the Sabbaths, having entered into the synagogue, he was teaching.<verse eid="MRK 1:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 1:22"/>And they were astonished at his teaching, for he was teaching them as having authority and not as the scribes.<verse eid="MRK 1:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 1:23"/>And immediately there was in their synagogue a man with an unclean spirit, and he cried out,<verse eid="MRK 1:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 1:24"/>saying, “What to us and to you, Jesus of Nazareth? Have you come to destroy us? I know who you are—the Holy One of God!”<verse eid="MRK 1:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 1:25"/>And Jesus rebuked him, saying, “Be silenced and come out from him!”<verse eid="MRK 1:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 1:26"/>And having convulsed him and having cried out with a loud voice, the unclean spirit went out from him.<verse eid="MRK 1:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 1:27"/>And they all were amazed, so that they discussed among themselves, saying, “What is this? A new teaching according to authority! And he commands the unclean spirits, and they obey him!”<verse eid="MRK 1:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 1:28"/>And the hearing of him immediately went out everywhere into the whole surrounding region of Galilee.<verse eid="MRK 1:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 1:29"/>And immediately, having come out from the synagogue, they came into the house of Simon and Andrew, along with James and John.<verse eid="MRK 1:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 1:30"/>Now the mother-in-law of Simon was lying down, being sick with a fever, and immediately they speak to him concerning her.<verse eid="MRK 1:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 1:31"/>And having approached, he raised her up, having taken hold of her hand, and the fever left her, and she was serving them.<verse eid="MRK 1:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 1:32"/>Now evening having come, after the sun {had} set, they were bringing to him all the ones having sickness and the ones possessed by demons.<verse eid="MRK 1:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 1:33"/>And the whole city was gathered together at the door.<verse eid="MRK 1:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 1:34"/>And he healed many having sickness with various diseases and cast out many demons, but he was not permitting the demons to speak, because they knew him.<verse eid="MRK 1:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 1:35"/>And in the morning, {while it was} still very dark, having gotten up, he went out and went away to a desolate place, and there he was praying.<verse eid="MRK 1:35"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 1:36"/>And Simon and the ones with him pursued him<verse eid="MRK 1:36"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 1:37"/>and found him and say to him, “All are seeking you.”<verse eid="MRK 1:37"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 1:38"/>And he says to them, “Let us go elsewhere, into the surrounding towns, so that I may preach there also, because for this I went out.”<verse eid="MRK 1:38"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 1:39"/>And he went in all Galilee, preaching in their synagogues and casting out the demons.<verse eid="MRK 1:39"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 1:40"/>And a leper comes to him, begging him and kneeling down, saying to him, “If you are willing, you are able to make me clean.”<verse eid="MRK 1:40"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 1:41"/>And having had compassion, having reached out his hand, he touched {him} and says to him, “I am willing. Be clean.”<verse eid="MRK 1:41"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 1:42"/>And immediately the leprosy departed from him, and he was made clean.<verse eid="MRK 1:42"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 1:43"/>But having strictly warned him, he immediately sent him away.<verse eid="MRK 1:43"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 1:44"/>And he says to him, “See that you say nothing to anyone, but go, show yourself to the priest, and offer for your cleansing what Moses commanded, for a testimony to them.”<verse eid="MRK 1:44"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 1:45"/>But he, having gone out, began to proclaim much and to report the word, so that he was able no longer to enter into a town openly, but he was out in desolate places, and they were coming to him from all sides.<verse eid="MRK 1:45"/></para>
<chapter eid="MRK 1"/>
<chapter number="2" style="c" sid="MRK 2"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 2:1"/>And having entered again into Capernaum after {some} days, it was heard that he is in a house.<verse eid="MRK 2:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 2:2"/>And many were gathered, so that it could no longer receive, not even the {areas} at the door, and he was speaking the word to them.<verse eid="MRK 2:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 2:3"/>And they come bringing to him a paralytic, being carried by four men.<verse eid="MRK 2:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 2:4"/>And not being able to bring {him} to him because of the crowd, they removed the roof where he was, and having dug {it} out, they lower the mat where the paralytic was lying.<verse eid="MRK 2:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 2:5"/>And Jesus, having seen their faith, says to the paralytic, “Child, your sins are forgiven.”<verse eid="MRK 2:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 2:6"/>But some of the scribes were sitting there and debating in their hearts,<verse eid="MRK 2:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 2:7"/>“Why does this one speak in this way? He blasphemes! Who is able to forgive sins except one, God?”<verse eid="MRK 2:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 2:8"/>And immediately Jesus, having known in his spirit that they are debating in this way within themselves, says to them, “Why are you debating these things in your hearts?<verse eid="MRK 2:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 2:9"/>Which is easier to say to the paralytic, ‘Your sins are forgiven’ or to say, ‘Get up and take up your mat and walk’?<verse eid="MRK 2:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 2:10"/>But in order that you may know that the Son of Man has authority on the earth to forgive sins,”—he says to the paralytic—<verse eid="MRK 2:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 2:11"/>“I say to you, get up, pick up your mat, and go to your house.”<verse eid="MRK 2:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 2:12"/>And having gotten up and immediately having taken up the mat, he went out before all, so that all were amazed and glorified God, saying, “We never saw thus.”<verse eid="MRK 2:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 2:13"/>And he went out again beside the sea, and all the crowd was coming to him, and he was teaching them.<verse eid="MRK 2:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 2:14"/>And passing by, he saw Levi the {son} of Alphaeus sitting at the tax collector’s office, and he says to him, “Follow me.” And having gotten up, he followed him.<verse eid="MRK 2:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 2:15"/>And it happens {that} he reclined to eat in his house, and many tax collectors and sinners were dining with Jesus and his disciples, for they were many, and they were following him.<verse eid="MRK 2:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 2:16"/>And the scribes of the Pharisees, having seen that he eats with the sinners and tax collectors, were saying to his disciples, “Does he eat with the tax collectors and sinners?”<verse eid="MRK 2:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 2:17"/>And having heard, Jesus says to them, “The ones being healthy do not have need of a physician, but the ones having sickness. I did not come to call the righteous, but sinners.”<verse eid="MRK 2:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 2:18"/>And the disciples of John and the Pharisees were fasting, and they come and say to him, “For what reason do the disciples of John and the disciples of the Pharisees fast, but your disciples do not fast?”<verse eid="MRK 2:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 2:19"/>And Jesus said to them, “The sons of the bridal chamber are not able to fast while the bridegroom is still with them, are they? As much time as they have the bridegroom with them, they are not able to fast.<verse eid="MRK 2:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 2:20"/>But days will come when the bridegroom will be taken away from them, and in those days, then they will fast.<verse eid="MRK 2:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 2:21"/>No one sews a patch of unshrunk cloth on an old garment, but if not, the patch tears away from it, the new from the old, and a worse tear happens.<verse eid="MRK 2:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 2:22"/>And no one puts new wine into old wineskins, but if not, the wine will burst the wineskins and the wine and the wineskins are destroyed, but new wine into new wineskins.”<verse eid="MRK 2:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 2:23"/>And it happened {that}, on the Sabbaths, he was passing through the grainfields, and his disciples began to make a way, picking the heads of grain.<verse eid="MRK 2:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 2:24"/>And the Pharisees were saying to him, “Behold, why are they doing what is not lawful on the Sabbaths?”<verse eid="MRK 2:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 2:25"/>And he says to them, “Have you never read what David did when he had need and was hungry, he and the ones with him—<verse eid="MRK 2:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 2:26"/>how he went into the house of God in the time of Abiathar the high priest and ate the loaves of the presence, which is not lawful to eat except for the priests, and he also gave to the ones being with him?”<verse eid="MRK 2:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 2:27"/>And he was saying to them, “The Sabbath was made for man, and not man for the Sabbath.<verse eid="MRK 2:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 2:28"/>Therefore, the Son of Man is Lord, even of the Sabbath.”<verse eid="MRK 2:28"/></para>
<chapter eid="MRK 2"/>
<chapter number="3" style="c" sid="MRK 3"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 3:1"/>And he entered into a synagogue again, and there was a man there having a withered hand.<verse eid="MRK 3:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 3:2"/>And they were watching him closely, if he will heal him on the Sabbaths, so that they might accuse him.<verse eid="MRK 3:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 3:3"/>And he says to the man having the withered hand, “Get up in the midst.”<verse eid="MRK 3:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 3:4"/>And he says to them, “Is it lawful on the Sabbaths to do good or to do harm; to save a life or to kill?” But they were keeping silent.<verse eid="MRK 3:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 3:5"/>And having looked around at them with anger, being grieved by the hardness of their heart, he says to the man, “Stretch out your hand.” And he stretched it out, and his hand was restored.<verse eid="MRK 3:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 3:6"/>And having gone out, the Pharisees immediately were making counsel with the Herodians against him so that they might destroy him.<verse eid="MRK 3:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 3:7"/>And Jesus, with his disciples, withdrew to the sea, and a great multitude followed from Galilee. And from Judea<verse eid="MRK 3:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 3:8"/>and from Jerusalem and from Idumea and beyond the Jordan and around Tyre and Sidon a great multitude, hearing how much he was doing, came to him.<verse eid="MRK 3:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 3:9"/>And he spoke to his disciples so that a small boat might be ready for him because of the crowd, so that they might not press against him.<verse eid="MRK 3:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 3:10"/>For he healed many, so that as many as had afflictions pressed against him so that they might touch him.<verse eid="MRK 3:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 3:11"/>And whenever the unclean spirits saw him, they were falling down before him and crying out, saying, “You are the Son of God.”<verse eid="MRK 3:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 3:12"/>And he was rebuking them much so that they might not make him known.<verse eid="MRK 3:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 3:13"/>And he goes up on the mountain and summons those whom he was wanting, and they went away to him.<verse eid="MRK 3:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 3:14"/>And he appointed 12, whom he also named apostles, so that they might be with him and so that he might send them to preach<verse eid="MRK 3:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 3:15"/>and to have authority to cast out the demons.<verse eid="MRK 3:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 3:16"/>And he appointed the Twelve, and he gave to Simon the name Peter;<verse eid="MRK 3:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 3:17"/>and James the {son} of Zebedee, and John the brother of James, and he gave names to them, Boanerges, that is, Sons of Thunder;<verse eid="MRK 3:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 3:18"/>and Andrew and Philip and Bartholomew and Matthew and Thomas and James the {son} of Alphaeus and Thaddaeus and Simon the Cananaios<verse eid="MRK 3:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 3:19"/>and Judas Iscariot, who also handed him over.<verse eid="MRK 3:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 3:20"/>And he comes into a house, and the crowd comes together again, so that they were not able even to eat bread.<verse eid="MRK 3:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 3:21"/>And the ones from him, having heard, went out to seize him, for they were saying, “He is out of his mind.”<verse eid="MRK 3:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 3:22"/>And the scribes having come down from Jerusalem were saying, “He has Beelzebul” and “By the ruler of the demons he casts out the demons.”<verse eid="MRK 3:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 3:23"/>And having summoned them, in parables he was saying to them, “How is Satan able to cast out Satan?<verse eid="MRK 3:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 3:24"/>And if a kingdom has been divided against itself, that kingdom is not able to stand.<verse eid="MRK 3:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 3:25"/>And if a house has been divided against itself, that house will not be able to stand.<verse eid="MRK 3:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 3:26"/>And if Satan rose up against himself and was divided, he is not able to stand, but he has an end.<verse eid="MRK 3:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 3:27"/>But no one is able, having entered into the house of the strong man, to steal his possessions if he has not first bound the strong man, and then he will plunder his house.<verse eid="MRK 3:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 3:28"/>Truly I say to you that all the sins and the blasphemies, as much as they may blaspheme, will be forgiven the sons of men,<verse eid="MRK 3:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 3:29"/>but whoever blasphemes against the Holy Spirit does not have forgiveness to eternity but is guilty of an eternal sin”—<verse eid="MRK 3:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 3:30"/>because they were saying, “He has an unclean spirit.”<verse eid="MRK 3:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 3:31"/>And his mother and his brothers come, and standing outside, they sent to him, calling him.<verse eid="MRK 3:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 3:32"/>And a crowd was sitting around him, and they say to him, “Behold, your mother and your brothers seek you outside.”<verse eid="MRK 3:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 3:33"/>And answering them, he says, “Who are my mother and my brothers?”<verse eid="MRK 3:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 3:34"/>And having looked around at the ones sitting in a circle around him, he says, “Behold, my mother and my brothers!<verse eid="MRK 3:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 3:35"/>For whoever does the will of God, this is my brother and sister and mother.”<verse eid="MRK 3:35"/></para>
<chapter eid="MRK 3"/>
<chapter number="4" style="c" sid="MRK 4"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 4:1"/>And again, he began to teach beside the sea, and the largest crowd is gathered to him. As a result, having gotten into a boat, he sat down on the sea, and the whole crowd was on the land beside the sea.<verse eid="MRK 4:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 4:2"/>And he was teaching them many things in parables, and he was saying to them in his teaching,<verse eid="MRK 4:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 4:3"/>“Listen! Behold, the sower went out to sow.<verse eid="MRK 4:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 4:4"/>And it happened that as he sowed, some fell beside the road, and the birds came and devoured it.<verse eid="MRK 4:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 4:5"/>And other fell on the rocky ground, where it did not have much soil, and immediately it sprang up, because it did not have deep soil.<verse eid="MRK 4:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 4:6"/>And when the sun rose, it was scorched, and because it had no root, it withered.<verse eid="MRK 4:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 4:7"/>And other fell into the thorns, and the thorns grew up and choked it, and it did not give fruit.<verse eid="MRK 4:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 4:8"/>And others fell on the good soil, and it was giving fruit, growing up and being increased, and one was bearing 30, and one, 60, and one, 100.”<verse eid="MRK 4:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 4:9"/>And he was saying, “Whoever has ears to hear, let him hear!”<verse eid="MRK 4:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 4:10"/>And when he was alone, the ones around him with the Twelve were asking him about the parables.<verse eid="MRK 4:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 4:11"/>And he was saying to them, “To you has been given the mystery of the kingdom of God, but to those, the ones outside, everything is in parables,<verse eid="MRK 4:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 4:12"/>so that, ‘Looking, they may look but may not see, and hearing, they may hear but may not understand, lest they might turn back, and it might be forgiven to them.’”<verse eid="MRK 4:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 4:13"/>And he says to them, “Do you not understand this parable? And how will you understand all the parables?<verse eid="MRK 4:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 4:14"/>The sower sows the word.<verse eid="MRK 4:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 4:15"/>Now these are the ones beside the road, where the word is being sown, but whenever they have heard it, Satan immediately comes and takes away the word that was sown in them.<verse eid="MRK 4:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 4:16"/>And similarly, these are the ones being sown on the rocky ground, who, whenever they have heard the word, immediately receive it with joy,<verse eid="MRK 4:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 4:17"/>and they have no root in themselves, but are temporary. Then, tribulation or persecution having happened because of the word, immediately they are caused to stumble.<verse eid="MRK 4:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 4:18"/>And others are the ones being sown into the thorns. These are the ones having heard the word,<verse eid="MRK 4:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 4:19"/>and the worries of the age and the deceitfulness of riches and the desires concerning other things, entering in, choke the word, and it becomes unfruitful.<verse eid="MRK 4:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 4:20"/>And those are the ones sown on the good soil, who hear the word and receive it and bear fruit—one, 30, and one, 60, and one, 100.”<verse eid="MRK 4:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 4:21"/>And he was saying to them, “The lamp does not come so that it might be put under the basket or under the bed, does it? Is it not so that it might be put on the lampstand?<verse eid="MRK 4:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 4:22"/>For it is not hidden except so that it might be revealed, nor has it become secret except so that it might come into visibility.<verse eid="MRK 4:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 4:23"/>If anyone has ears to hear, let him hear!”<verse eid="MRK 4:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 4:24"/>And he was saying to them, “Watch what you hear. With the measure by which you measure, it will be measured to you, and it will be added to you.<verse eid="MRK 4:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 4:25"/>For he who has, it will be given to him, and he who does not have, even what he has will be taken away from him.”<verse eid="MRK 4:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 4:26"/>And he was saying, “Thus is the kingdom of God: As a man throws the seed on the ground,<verse eid="MRK 4:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 4:27"/>and he sleeps and gets up, night and day, and the seed sprouts and grows—how, he himself does not know.<verse eid="MRK 4:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 4:28"/>The soil produces a crop of its own accord: first a blade, then a head, then a mature grain in the head.<verse eid="MRK 4:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 4:29"/>And whenever the fruit hands over, he immediately sends the sickle, because the harvest has come.”<verse eid="MRK 4:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 4:30"/>And he was saying, “How will we compare the kingdom of God, or in what parable will we put it?<verse eid="MRK 4:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 4:31"/>{It is} like a mustard seed, which, when it has been sown in the soil, being the smallest of all the seeds on the earth,<verse eid="MRK 4:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 4:32"/>and when it has been sown, it grows and becomes greater than all the vegetable plants, and it makes large branches, so that the birds of the sky are able to nest in its shadow.”<verse eid="MRK 4:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 4:33"/>And with many such parables he was speaking the word to them, just as they were able to hear;<verse eid="MRK 4:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 4:34"/>but he was not speaking to them without a parable, but by himself he was explaining everything to his own disciples.<verse eid="MRK 4:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 4:35"/>And he says to them on that day, evening having come, “Let us cross over to the other side.”<verse eid="MRK 4:35"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 4:36"/>And having left the crowd, they take him with {them}, as he was, in the boat, and other boats were with him.<verse eid="MRK 4:36"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 4:37"/>And a great storm of wind happens, and the waves were breaking into the boat, so that the boat was already filled.<verse eid="MRK 4:37"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 4:38"/>And he himself was in the stern, sleeping on the cushion. And they wake him up and say to him, “Teacher, is it not a concern to you that we are perishing?”<verse eid="MRK 4:38"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 4:39"/>And awaking, he rebuked the wind, and said to the sea, “Be silent! Be still!” And the wind ceased, and there was a great calm.<verse eid="MRK 4:39"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 4:40"/>And he said to them, “Why are you cowardly? Do you not yet have faith?”<verse eid="MRK 4:40"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 4:41"/>And they feared a great fear and were saying to one another, “Who then is this, that even the wind and the sea obey him?”<verse eid="MRK 4:41"/></para>
<chapter eid="MRK 4"/>
<chapter number="5" style="c" sid="MRK 5"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 5:1"/>And they came to the other side of the sea, to the region of the Gerasenes.<verse eid="MRK 5:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 5:2"/>And he having gone out from the boat, immediately a man with an unclean spirit met him from the tombs,<verse eid="MRK 5:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 5:3"/>who had his dwelling in the tombs, and no one was able to bind him anymore, not even with a chain,<verse eid="MRK 5:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 5:4"/>because he had often been bound with shackles and chains, and the chains had been torn apart by him and the shackles had been shattered, and no one was strong enough to subdue him.<verse eid="MRK 5:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 5:5"/>And throughout every night and day, in the tombs and in the mountains, he was crying out and cutting himself with stones.<verse eid="MRK 5:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 5:6"/>And having seen Jesus from a distance, he ran to him and bowed down to him.<verse eid="MRK 5:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 5:7"/>And crying out with a loud voice, he says, “What to me and to you, Jesus, Son of the Most High God? I make you swear by God, do not torment me.”<verse eid="MRK 5:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 5:8"/>For he was saying to him, “Come out from the man, unclean spirit.”<verse eid="MRK 5:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 5:9"/>And he was asking him, “What {is} your name?” And he says to him, “My name {is} Legion, for we are many.”<verse eid="MRK 5:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 5:10"/>And he was begging him much that he would not send them out of the region.<verse eid="MRK 5:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 5:11"/>But there was a great herd of pigs being fed on the hill,<verse eid="MRK 5:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 5:12"/>and they begged him, saying, “Send us into the pigs, so that we might enter into them.”<verse eid="MRK 5:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 5:13"/>And he permitted them, and having come out, the unclean spirits entered into the pigs, and the herd—about 2, 000—rushed down the steep slope into the sea and were drowned in the sea.<verse eid="MRK 5:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 5:14"/>And the ones feeding them ran away and reported it in the city and in the countryside, and they went out to see what it is that had happened.<verse eid="MRK 5:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 5:15"/>And they come to Jesus and see the one being demon-possessed, sitting, clothed and being sound-minded—the one that had had the legion—and they were afraid.<verse eid="MRK 5:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 5:16"/>And the ones having seen explained to them how it happened to the one being demon-possessed, and about the pigs.<verse eid="MRK 5:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 5:17"/>And they began to beg him to depart from their region.<verse eid="MRK 5:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 5:18"/>And he getting into the boat, the one having been demon-possessed was begging him so that he might be with him.<verse eid="MRK 5:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 5:19"/>And he did not permit him, but he says to him, “Go to your house, to your {people}, and report to them as much as the Lord has done for you and had mercy on you.”<verse eid="MRK 5:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 5:20"/>And he went away and began to proclaim in the Decapolis as much as Jesus did for him, and all were marveling.<verse eid="MRK 5:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 5:21"/>And Jesus having crossed over again to the other side in the boat, a great crowd was gathered around him, and he was beside the sea.<verse eid="MRK 5:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 5:22"/>And behold, one of the synagogue rulers, Jairus by name, comes, and having seen him, he falls at his feet.<verse eid="MRK 5:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 5:23"/>And he begs him much, saying, “My little daughter is having {her} end; so that, coming, you might lay your hands on her in order that she might be saved, and she might live.”<verse eid="MRK 5:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 5:24"/>And he went away with him. And a great crowd was following him and was pressing around him.<verse eid="MRK 5:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 5:25"/>And a woman, being with a flow of blood for 12 years,<verse eid="MRK 5:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 5:26"/>and having suffered much from many physicians, and having spent everything {that was} from herself, and benefitting nothing, but instead having come to the worse,<verse eid="MRK 5:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 5:27"/>having heard the things about Jesus, having come up behind him in the crowd, touched his cloak.<verse eid="MRK 5:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 5:28"/>For she was saying, “If I touch just his clothes, I will be saved.”<verse eid="MRK 5:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 5:29"/>And immediately the flow of her blood was dried up, and she knew in her body that she had been healed from the affliction.<verse eid="MRK 5:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 5:30"/>And immediately Jesus, having realized in himself the power having gone out from him, having turned around in the crowd, was saying, “Who touched my clothes?”<verse eid="MRK 5:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 5:31"/>And his disciples were saying to him, “You see the crowd pressing around you, and you say, ‘Who touched me?’”<verse eid="MRK 5:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 5:32"/>And he was looking around to see the one having done this.<verse eid="MRK 5:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 5:33"/>And the woman, having become afraid and trembling, having known what had happened to her, came and fell down before him and told him the whole truth.<verse eid="MRK 5:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 5:34"/>But he said to her, “Daughter, your faith has saved you. Depart in peace and be healed from your affliction.”<verse eid="MRK 5:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 5:35"/>He still speaking, they come from the synagogue ruler, saying, “Your daughter died. Why trouble the teacher further?”<verse eid="MRK 5:35"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 5:36"/>But Jesus, having overheard the word being spoken, says to the synagogue ruler, “Do not fear. Only believe.”<verse eid="MRK 5:36"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 5:37"/>And he did not allow anyone to accompany him except Peter and James and John the brother of James.<verse eid="MRK 5:37"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 5:38"/>And he comes to the house of the leader of the synagogue, and he sees a commotion and weeping and much wailing.<verse eid="MRK 5:38"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 5:39"/>And entering, he says to them, “Why are you being disturbed and weeping? The child did not die but is sleeping.”<verse eid="MRK 5:39"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 5:40"/>And they were laughing at him. But he, having cast {them} all out, takes along the father of the child and the mother and the ones with him, and he enters where the child was.<verse eid="MRK 5:40"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 5:41"/>And having taken the hand of the child, he says to her, “Talitha, koum!” which is translated: “Little girl, I say to you, arise.”<verse eid="MRK 5:41"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 5:42"/>And immediately the little girl rose up and was walking (for she was 12 years), and they were immediately astonished with great amazement.<verse eid="MRK 5:42"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 5:43"/>And he commanded them much that no one might know this, and he said that something should be given to her to eat.<verse eid="MRK 5:43"/></para>
<chapter eid="MRK 5"/>
<chapter number="6" style="c" sid="MRK 6"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 6:1"/>And he went out from there and comes to his hometown, and his disciples are following him.<verse eid="MRK 6:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 6:2"/>And a Sabbath having come, he began to teach in the synagogue. And the many ones hearing him were astonished, saying, “From where to this one {are} these things, and what {is} the wisdom that has been given to this one, and such miracles happening by his hands?<verse eid="MRK 6:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 6:3"/>Is this not the carpenter, the son of Mary and a brother of James and Joses and Judas and Simon? And are his sisters not here with us?” And they were being caused to stumble on him.<verse eid="MRK 6:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 6:4"/>And Jesus was saying to them, “A prophet is not without honor, except in his hometown and among his relatives and in his house.”<verse eid="MRK 6:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 6:5"/>And he was not able to do any miracle there, except, having laid his hands on a few sick people, he healed {them}.<verse eid="MRK 6:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 6:6"/>And he was amazed because of their unbelief. And he was going around the villages in a circle teaching.<verse eid="MRK 6:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 6:7"/>And he calls the Twelve and began to send them out two by two, and he was giving them authority over the unclean spirits,<verse eid="MRK 6:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 6:8"/>and he commanded them that they should take nothing for the road except only a staff—no bread, no bag, no money in the belt—<verse eid="MRK 6:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 6:9"/>but having put on sandals, and, “You may not wear two tunics.”<verse eid="MRK 6:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 6:10"/>And he was saying to them, “Whenever you enter into a house, remain there until you go out from there.<verse eid="MRK 6:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 6:11"/>And whatever place does not receive you nor listen to you, going out from there, shake off the dust that {is} under your feet for a testimony against them.”<verse eid="MRK 6:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 6:12"/>And having gone out, they proclaimed that they should repent.<verse eid="MRK 6:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 6:13"/>And they were casting out many demons and anointing many sick {people} with oil and healing them.<verse eid="MRK 6:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 6:14"/>And King Herod heard, for his name became known, and they were saying,  “John the Baptist has been raised from the dead, and because of this the powers work in him.”<verse eid="MRK 6:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 6:15"/>But others were saying, “He is Elijah.” But others were saying, “A prophet, like one of the prophets.”<verse eid="MRK 6:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 6:16"/>But Herod, having heard this, was saying, “{The one} whom I beheaded, John, this one has been raised.”<verse eid="MRK 6:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 6:17"/>For Herod himself, having sent, seized John and bound him in prison because of Herodias, the wife of his brother Philip, because he married her.<verse eid="MRK 6:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 6:18"/>For John was saying to Herod, “It is not lawful for you to have the wife of your brother.”<verse eid="MRK 6:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 6:19"/>But Herodias was angry with him and was wanting to kill him, and she was not able,<verse eid="MRK 6:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 6:20"/>for Herod was fearing John, knowing him {to be} a righteous and holy man, and he was keeping him safe, and having heard him, he was much perplexed, and he was listening to him gladly.<verse eid="MRK 6:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 6:21"/>And an opportune day having come, when Herod made a dinner for his birthday for his great ones and for the chiliarchs and for the first of Galilee,<verse eid="MRK 6:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 6:22"/>and his daughter, of Herodias, having entered and having danced and having pleased Herod and the ones reclining to eat with {him}, the king said to the girl, “Ask me whatever you desire, and I will give {it} to you.”<verse eid="MRK 6:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 6:23"/>And he swore to her, “If you ask me, I will give {it} to you, up to half of my kingdom.”<verse eid="MRK 6:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 6:24"/>And having gone out, she said to her mother, “What should I ask?” And she said, “The head of John the Baptist.”<verse eid="MRK 6:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 6:25"/>And immediately, having entered in with haste to the king, she requested, saying, “I desire that you would give me at once the head of John the Baptist on a platter.”<verse eid="MRK 6:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 6:26"/>And the king, having become deeply grieved because of his oaths and the ones reclining to eat with him, did not want to refuse her,<verse eid="MRK 6:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 6:27"/>and the king, immediately having sent an executioner, commanded {him} to bring his head, and having departed, he beheaded him in the prison.<verse eid="MRK 6:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 6:28"/>And he brought his head on a platter and gave it to the girl, and the girl gave it to her mother.<verse eid="MRK 6:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 6:29"/>And his disciples, having heard, came and took away his corpse and placed it in a tomb.<verse eid="MRK 6:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 6:30"/>And the apostles are gathered together with Jesus and reported to him everything, as much as they did and as much as they taught.<verse eid="MRK 6:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 6:31"/>And he says to them, “You yourselves, come by yourselves to a desolate place and rest a little while.” For the ones coming and the ones going were many, and they were not even having opportunity to eat.<verse eid="MRK 6:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 6:32"/>And they went away in the boat to a desolate place by themselves.<verse eid="MRK 6:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 6:33"/>And they saw them leaving, and many knew, and they ran there together on foot from all the cities, and they arrived before them.<verse eid="MRK 6:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 6:34"/>And having come out, he saw a large crowd, and he had compassion on them because they were like sheep not having a shepherd, and he began to teach them many things.<verse eid="MRK 6:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 6:35"/>And the hour already having become much, his disciples, having come to him, were saying, “This place is desolate, and the hour {is} already much.<verse eid="MRK 6:35"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 6:36"/>Send them away so that, having gone away into the surrounding countryside and villages, they might buy something for themselves {that} they might eat.”<verse eid="MRK 6:36"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 6:37"/>But he, answering, said to them, “You give them to eat.” And they say to him, “Having gone away, might we buy loaves of 200 denarii and give {them} to them to eat?”<verse eid="MRK 6:37"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 6:38"/>But he says to them, “How many loaves do you have? Go. See.” And having known, they say, “Five, and two fish.”<verse eid="MRK 6:38"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 6:39"/>And he commanded them all to recline group by group on the green grass.<verse eid="MRK 6:39"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 6:40"/>And they reclined group by group according to hundreds and according to fifties.<verse eid="MRK 6:40"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 6:41"/>And having taken the five loaves and the two fish, having looked up to heaven, he blessed and broke the loaves into pieces and was giving them to his disciples so that they might set them before them, and he divided the two fish among all.<verse eid="MRK 6:41"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 6:42"/>And they all ate and were satisfied.<verse eid="MRK 6:42"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 6:43"/>And they took up the broken pieces, the fillings of 12 baskets, and from the fish.<verse eid="MRK 6:43"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 6:44"/>And the ones having eaten the loaves were 5,000 men.<verse eid="MRK 6:44"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 6:45"/>And immediately he compelled his disciples to get into the boat and to go ahead to the other side, to Bethsaida, while he sends the crowd away.<verse eid="MRK 6:45"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="46" style="v" sid="MRK 6:46"/>And having said farewell to them, he went to the mountain to pray.<verse eid="MRK 6:46"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="47" style="v" sid="MRK 6:47"/>And evening having come, the boat was in the middle of the sea, and he {was} alone on the land.<verse eid="MRK 6:47"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="48" style="v" sid="MRK 6:48"/>And having seen them being tormented as they rowed—for the wind was against them—and about the fourth watch of the night, he comes to them, walking on the sea, and he was wishing to pass by them.<verse eid="MRK 6:48"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="49" style="v" sid="MRK 6:49"/>But they, having seen him walking on the sea, thought that he is a ghost, and they cried out,<verse eid="MRK 6:49"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="50" style="v" sid="MRK 6:50"/>for they all saw him and were troubled. But immediately he spoke with them and says to them, “Take courage! It is I! Do not be afraid!”<verse eid="MRK 6:50"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="51" style="v" sid="MRK 6:51"/>And he got into the boat with them, and the wind ceased, and they were very amazed within themselves.<verse eid="MRK 6:51"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="52" style="v" sid="MRK 6:52"/>For they did not understand about the loaves, but their heart was having been hardened.<verse eid="MRK 6:52"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="53" style="v" sid="MRK 6:53"/>And having crossed over, they came to the land at Gennesaret and anchored there.<verse eid="MRK 6:53"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="54" style="v" sid="MRK 6:54"/>And they having come out from the boat, immediately having recognized him,<verse eid="MRK 6:54"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="55" style="v" sid="MRK 6:55"/>they ran throughout that whole region, and they began to carry on their mats the ones having sickness where they were hearing that he is.<verse eid="MRK 6:55"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="56" style="v" sid="MRK 6:56"/>And wherever he was entering into villages or into cities or into fields, they were placing the ones being sick in the marketplaces, and they were begging him so that they might even touch the edge of his garment, and as many as touched it were being healed.<verse eid="MRK 6:56"/></para>
<chapter eid="MRK 6"/>
<chapter number="7" style="c" sid="MRK 7"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 7:1"/>And the Pharisees and some of the scribes, having come from Jerusalem, are being gathered to him.<verse eid="MRK 7:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 7:2"/>And having seen some of his disciples, that they eat loaves with defiled hands, that is, unwashed—<verse eid="MRK 7:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 7:3"/>for the Pharisees and all the Jews do not eat unless they would wash their hands with a fist, holding to the tradition of the elders;<verse eid="MRK 7:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 7:4"/>and from a marketplace, they do not eat unless they baptize, and there are many other things which they received to hold to: baptisms of cups and pitchers and copper vessels—<verse eid="MRK 7:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 7:5"/>also the Pharisees and the scribes ask him, “Why do your disciples not walk according to the tradition of the elders, but they eat bread with defiled hands?”<verse eid="MRK 7:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 7:6"/>But he, answering, said to them, “Isaiah prophesied well about you hypocrites. As it is written, ‘This people honors me with their lips, but their heart is far away from me.<verse eid="MRK 7:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 7:7"/>But they worship me in vain, teaching as doctrines commandments of men.’<verse eid="MRK 7:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 7:8"/>Having left the commandment of God, you hold to the tradition of men.”<verse eid="MRK 7:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 7:9"/>And he was saying to them, “Well do you reject the commandment of God so that you may keep your tradition!<verse eid="MRK 7:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 7:10"/>For Moses said, ‘Honor your father and your mother,’ and, ‘The one speaking evil of his father or mother, let him end in death.’<verse eid="MRK 7:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 7:11"/>But you say, ‘If a man says to his father or his mother, “Whatever you might have benefited from me {is} Corban”’ (that is, a gift),<verse eid="MRK 7:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 7:12"/>you no longer permit him to do anything for his father or his mother,<verse eid="MRK 7:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 7:13"/>setting aside the word of God by your tradition which you handed down, and you do many such similar things.”<verse eid="MRK 7:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 7:14"/>And having summoned the crowd again, he was saying to them, “Listen to me, all {of you}, and understand:<verse eid="MRK 7:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 7:15"/>there is nothing from outside the man, entering into him, that is able to defile him; but the things that come out from the man are the things defiling the man.<verse eid="MRK 7:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 7:16"/>[If anyone has ears to hear, let him hear.]”<verse eid="MRK 7:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 7:17"/>And when he entered into a house from the crowd, his disciples were asking him about the parable.<verse eid="MRK 7:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 7:18"/>And he says to them, “Are you also thus without understanding? Do you not understand that everything that enters into the man from outside is not able to defile him,<verse eid="MRK 7:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 7:19"/>because it does not go into his heart, but into the stomach, and passes out into the latrine (cleansing all foods)?”<verse eid="MRK 7:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 7:20"/>But he was saying, “What is coming out from the man, that defiles the man.<verse eid="MRK 7:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 7:21"/>For from within, from the heart of men, come out evil thoughts, sexual immorality, thefts, murders,<verse eid="MRK 7:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 7:22"/>adultery, coveting, wickedness, deceit, sensuality, an evil eye, blasphemy, pride, {and} folly.<verse eid="MRK 7:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 7:23"/>All these evils come out from within, and they defile the man.”<verse eid="MRK 7:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 7:24"/>Now having gotten up from there, he went away to the region of Tyre and Sidon, and having entered into a house, he was wanting no one to know {it}, but he was not able to hide.<verse eid="MRK 7:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 7:25"/>But immediately having heard about him, a woman, of whom her little daughter had an unclean spirit, having come, fell down at his feet.<verse eid="MRK 7:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 7:26"/>Now the woman was a Greek, a Syrophoenician by descent, and she was asking him that he would cast out the demon from her daughter.<verse eid="MRK 7:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 7:27"/>And he was saying to her, “Permit the children first to be fed, for it is not good to take the bread of the children and to throw {it} to the little dogs.”<verse eid="MRK 7:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 7:28"/>But she answered and says to him, “Yes, Lord, and the little dogs under the table eat from the crumbs of the children.”<verse eid="MRK 7:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 7:29"/>And he said to her, “Because of this word, go! The demon has gone out from your daughter.”<verse eid="MRK 7:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 7:30"/>And having gone away to her house, she found the child having been put on the bed and the demon having gone out.<verse eid="MRK 7:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 7:31"/>And again having gone out from the region of Tyre, he went through Sidon to the Sea of Galilee, in the midst of the region of the Decapolis.<verse eid="MRK 7:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 7:32"/>And they bring to him {one} deaf and barely able to speak, and they beg him that he would lay his hand on him.<verse eid="MRK 7:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 7:33"/>And having taken him aside from the crowd by himself, he put his fingers into his ears, and having spit, he touched his tongue.<verse eid="MRK 7:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 7:34"/>And having looked up to heaven, he sighed and says to him, “Ephphatha!” (that is, “Be opened!”).<verse eid="MRK 7:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 7:35"/>And his ears were opened, and the bond of his tongue was loosed, and he began speaking rightly.<verse eid="MRK 7:35"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 7:36"/>And he commanded them so that they would tell {it} to no one. But as much as he commanded them, the more abundantly they were proclaiming {it}.<verse eid="MRK 7:36"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 7:37"/>And they were extremely astonished, saying, “He has done all things well, and he makes the deaf to hear and the mute to speak.”<verse eid="MRK 7:37"/></para>
<chapter eid="MRK 7"/>
<chapter number="8" style="c" sid="MRK 8"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 8:1"/>In those days, there again being a great crowd, and not having anything {that} they might eat, having summoned his disciples, he says to them,<verse eid="MRK 8:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 8:2"/>“I have compassion on the crowd because they are remaining with me already three days and do not have anything {that} they might eat.<verse eid="MRK 8:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 8:3"/>And if I would send them away to their home hungry, they will faint on the way, and some of them have come from far way.”<verse eid="MRK 8:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 8:4"/>And his disciples answered him, “From where will anyone be able to satisfy these {people} with loaves here in a desolate place?”<verse eid="MRK 8:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 8:5"/>And he asked them, “How many loaves do you have?” And they said, “Seven.”<verse eid="MRK 8:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 8:6"/>And he commands the crowd to recline on the ground, and having taken the seven loaves, having given thanks, he broke {them} and was giving {them} to his disciples so that they might set {them} before {them}, and they set {them} before the crowd.<verse eid="MRK 8:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 8:7"/>And they had a few small fish, and having blessed them, he said to set these also before {them}.<verse eid="MRK 8:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 8:8"/>And they ate and were satisfied, and they took up the remaining of the broken pieces—seven baskets.<verse eid="MRK 8:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 8:9"/>Now there were about 4,000, and he sent them away.<verse eid="MRK 8:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 8:10"/>And immediately, having gotten into the boat with his disciples, he went into the regions of Dalmanutha.<verse eid="MRK 8:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 8:11"/>And the Pharisees came out and began to argue with him, seeking from him a sign from heaven, testing him.<verse eid="MRK 8:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 8:12"/>And having sighed greatly in his spirit, he says, “Why does this generation seek a sign? Truly I say to you, if a sign will be given to this generation …”<verse eid="MRK 8:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 8:13"/>And having left them, having gotten into {a boat} again, he went away to the other side.<verse eid="MRK 8:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 8:14"/>And they forgot to bring loaves, and except for one loaf, they did not have {any} with them in the boat.<verse eid="MRK 8:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 8:15"/>And he was commanding them, saying, “See, watch out for the yeast of the Pharisees and the yeast of Herod.”<verse eid="MRK 8:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 8:16"/>And they were reasoning with each other that they have no loaves.<verse eid="MRK 8:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 8:17"/>And having known this, Jesus says to them, “Why are you reasoning that you do not have loaves? Do you not yet perceive, nor understand? Has your heart become hardened?<verse eid="MRK 8:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 8:18"/>Having eyes, do you not see? And having ears, do you not hear? And do you not remember?<verse eid="MRK 8:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 8:19"/>When I broke the five loaves for the 5, 000, how many baskets full of broken pieces did you take up?” They say to him, “12.”<verse eid="MRK 8:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 8:20"/>“And when the seven for the 4, 000, the fillings of how many baskets of broken pieces did you take up?” And they say to him, “Seven.”<verse eid="MRK 8:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 8:21"/>And he was saying to them, “How do you not yet understand?”<verse eid="MRK 8:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 8:22"/>And they come to Bethsaida, and they bring to him a blind {man} and beg him that he would touch him.<verse eid="MRK 8:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 8:23"/>And having taken hold of the hand of the blind man, he led him out from the village. And having spit into his eyes, having laid his hands on him, he was asking him, “Do you see anything?”<verse eid="MRK 8:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 8:24"/>And having looked up, he was saying, “I see men, for I see {them} like trees walking.”<verse eid="MRK 8:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 8:25"/>Then he again laid his hands upon his eyes, and he looked intently and was restored, and he was seeing everything clearly.<verse eid="MRK 8:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 8:26"/>And he sent him away to his home, saying, “You may not even enter into the town.”<verse eid="MRK 8:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 8:27"/>And Jesus and his disciples went out into the villages of Caesarea Philippi, and on the way he was questioning his disciples, saying to them, “Who do men say that I am?”<verse eid="MRK 8:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 8:28"/>But they said to him, saying, “John the Baptist, and others, Elijah, but others, one of the prophets.”<verse eid="MRK 8:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 8:29"/>And he was questioning them, “But who do you say that I am?” And answering, Peter says to him, “You are the Christ.”<verse eid="MRK 8:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 8:30"/>And he strongly warned them that they might tell no one about him.<verse eid="MRK 8:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 8:31"/>And he began to teach them that it is necessary for the Son of Man to suffer many things and to be rejected by the elders and the chief priests and the scribes and to be killed and to rise up after three days.<verse eid="MRK 8:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 8:32"/>And he was speaking the word with openness. And having taken him aside, Peter began to rebuke him.<verse eid="MRK 8:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 8:33"/>But Jesus, having turned and having looked at his disciples, rebuked Peter and says, “Get behind me, Satan! For you are not considering the things of God, but the things of men.”<verse eid="MRK 8:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 8:34"/>And having summoned the crowd along with his disciples, he said to them, “If anyone wants to follow after me, let him deny himself and take up his cross and follow me.<verse eid="MRK 8:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 8:35"/>For whoever wants to save his life will lose it, but whoever loses his life for the sake of me and of the gospel will save it.<verse eid="MRK 8:35"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 8:36"/>For what does it benefit a man to gain the whole world and to forfeit his life?<verse eid="MRK 8:36"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 8:37"/>For what might a man give in exchange for his life?<verse eid="MRK 8:37"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 8:38"/>For whoever is ashamed of me and of my words in this adulterous and sinful generation, the Son of Man will also be ashamed of him when he comes in the glory of his Father with the holy angels.”<verse eid="MRK 8:38"/></para>
<chapter eid="MRK 8"/>
<chapter number="9" style="c" sid="MRK 9"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 9:1"/>And he was saying to them, “Truly, I say to you that there are some of the ones standing here who will certainly not taste death until they see the kingdom of God having come with power.”<verse eid="MRK 9:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 9:2"/>And after six days, Jesus takes along Peter and James and John and brings them up onto a high mountain by themselves, alone, and he was transfigured before them.<verse eid="MRK 9:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 9:3"/>And his garments became radiantly, extremely white, such as no launderer on the earth is able thus to make them white.<verse eid="MRK 9:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 9:4"/>And Elijah with Moses were seen by them, and they were talking with Jesus.<verse eid="MRK 9:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 9:5"/>And answering, Peter says to Jesus, “Rabbi, it is good for us to be here, and let us make three tents, one for you, and one for Moses, and one for Elijah.”<verse eid="MRK 9:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 9:6"/>(For he did not know what he should answer, for they were terrified.)<verse eid="MRK 9:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 9:7"/>And a cloud appeared, overshadowing them, and there was a voice from the cloud, “This is my beloved Son. Listen to him.”<verse eid="MRK 9:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 9:8"/>And suddenly, having looked around, they no longer saw anyone with them, but only Jesus.<verse eid="MRK 9:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 9:9"/>And they coming down from the mountain, he ordered them so that they would relate to no one what they had seen, until the Son of Man had risen from the dead.<verse eid="MRK 9:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 9:10"/>And they kept the word to themselves, discussing together what it is “to rise from the dead.”<verse eid="MRK 9:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 9:11"/>And they were questioning him, saying, “Why do the scribes say that it is necessary for Elijah to come first?”<verse eid="MRK 9:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 9:12"/>But he was saying to them, “Elijah, having come first, restores all things. And how has it been written about the Son of Man that he would suffer many things and be despised?<verse eid="MRK 9:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 9:13"/>But I say to you that also Elijah has come, and they did to him whatever they were wanting, just as it is written about him.”<verse eid="MRK 9:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 9:14"/>And having come to the disciples, they saw a great crowd around them and scribes arguing with them.<verse eid="MRK 9:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 9:15"/>And immediately, the whole crowd, having seen him, were amazed, and running up to {him}, they were greeting him.<verse eid="MRK 9:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 9:16"/>And he asked them, “What are you arguing with them about?”<verse eid="MRK 9:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 9:17"/>And one from the crowd answered him, “Teacher, I brought my son to you, having a mute spirit.<verse eid="MRK 9:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 9:18"/>And wherever it might seize him, it throws him down, and he foams at the mouth and grinds his teeth, and he becomes stiff, and I spoke to your disciples so that they would cast it out, and they were not able.”<verse eid="MRK 9:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 9:19"/>But answering them, he says, “O unbelieving generation, until when will I be with you? Until when will I bear with you? Bring him to me.”<verse eid="MRK 9:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 9:20"/>And they brought him to him, and having seen him, the spirit immediately shook him with convulsions, and having fallen on the ground, he was rolling around, foaming at the mouth.<verse eid="MRK 9:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 9:21"/>And he asked his father, “How much time is it while this has been happening to him?” And he said, “From childhood.<verse eid="MRK 9:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 9:22"/>And it has often thrown him both into fire and into waters in order that it might destroy him, but if you are able to do anything, help us, having compassion on us.”<verse eid="MRK 9:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 9:23"/>But Jesus said to him, “‘If you are able’? All things are possible for the one believing.”<verse eid="MRK 9:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 9:24"/>And immediately the father of the child, having cried out, was saying, “I believe! Help my unbelief!”<verse eid="MRK 9:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 9:25"/>And Jesus, having seen that a crowd is running to {them}, rebuked the unclean spirit, saying to it, “Mute and deaf spirit, I command you, come out from him, and never enter into him again.”<verse eid="MRK 9:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 9:26"/>And having cried out and having convulsed him much, it came out, and he became like a dead {person}, so that many said, “He has died.”<verse eid="MRK 9:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 9:27"/>But Jesus, having taken his hand, raised him up, and he got up.<verse eid="MRK 9:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 9:28"/>And he having gone into a house, his disciples were asking him privately, “Why were we not able to cast it out?”<verse eid="MRK 9:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 9:29"/>And he said to them, “This kind is able to come out by nothing except by prayer and fasting.”<verse eid="MRK 9:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 9:30"/>And having gone out from there, they were passing through Galilee, and he was not wanting that anyone would know,<verse eid="MRK 9:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 9:31"/>for he was teaching his disciples and saying to them, “The Son of Man is being handed over into the hands of men, and they will kill him. And having been killed, he will rise up after three days.”<verse eid="MRK 9:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 9:32"/>But they were not understanding the word, and they were afraid to ask him.<verse eid="MRK 9:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 9:33"/>And they came to Capernaum, and being in the house, he was asking them, “What were you discussing on the way?”<verse eid="MRK 9:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 9:34"/>But they were silent, for they had been arguing with one another on the way about who {was} greatest.<verse eid="MRK 9:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 9:35"/>And having sat down, he called the Twelve together and says to them, “If anyone wants to be first, he will be last of all and a servant of all.”<verse eid="MRK 9:35"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 9:36"/>And having taken a little child, he set him in the midst of them, and having taken him in his arms, he said to them,<verse eid="MRK 9:36"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 9:37"/>“Whoever receives one of these little children in my name receives me; and whoever receives me does not receive me but the one having sent me.”<verse eid="MRK 9:37"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 9:38"/>John was saying to him, “Teacher, we saw someone casting out demons in your name, and we were preventing him because he was not following with us.”<verse eid="MRK 9:38"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 9:39"/>But Jesus said, “Do not prevent him, for there is no one who will do a mighty work in my name and will be able soon afterwards to speak evil about me.<verse eid="MRK 9:39"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 9:40"/>For whoever is not against us is for us.<verse eid="MRK 9:40"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 9:41"/>For whoever gives you a cup of water in the name that you are Christ’s, truly I say to you that he will certainly not lose his reward.<verse eid="MRK 9:41"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 9:42"/>And whoever causes one of these little ones who believe in me to stumble, it is better for him instead if a millstone of a donkey is put around his neck and he has been thrown into the sea.<verse eid="MRK 9:42"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 9:43"/>And if your hand causes you to stumble, cut it off. It is better for you to enter into life crippled than, having two hands, to go away into Gehenna, into the unquenchable fire<verse eid="MRK 9:43"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 9:44"/>[where their worm does not end, and the fire is not quenched].<verse eid="MRK 9:44"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 9:45"/>And if your foot causes you to stumble, cut it off. It is better for you to enter into life lame than, having two feet, to be thrown into Gehenna<verse eid="MRK 9:45"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="46" style="v" sid="MRK 9:46"/>[where their worm does not end, and the fire is not quenched].<verse eid="MRK 9:46"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="47" style="v" sid="MRK 9:47"/>And if your eye causes you to stumble, throw it out. It is better for you to enter into the kingdom of God with one eye than, having two eyes, to be thrown into Gehenna,<verse eid="MRK 9:47"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="48" style="v" sid="MRK 9:48"/>where their worm does not end, and the fire is not quenched.<verse eid="MRK 9:48"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="49" style="v" sid="MRK 9:49"/>For everyone will be salted with fire.<verse eid="MRK 9:49"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="50" style="v" sid="MRK 9:50"/>Salt is good, but if the salt becomes unsalty, with what will you season it? Have salt in yourselves, and be at peace with one another.”<verse eid="MRK 9:50"/></para>
<chapter eid="MRK 9"/>
<chapter number="10" style="c" sid="MRK 10"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 10:1"/>And having gotten up, he goes from that place to the regions of Judea and beyond the Jordan, and the crowds come together to him again. And he was teaching them again, as he had been accustomed {to do}.<verse eid="MRK 10:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 10:2"/>And having approached, the Pharisees were questioning him whether it is lawful for a husband to divorce a wife, testing him.<verse eid="MRK 10:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 10:3"/>But he, answering, said to them, “What did Moses command you?”<verse eid="MRK 10:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 10:4"/>And they said, “Moses permitted him to write a certificate of divorce and to divorce her.”<verse eid="MRK 10:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 10:5"/>But Jesus said to them, “Because of your hardness of heart, he wrote this commandment to you.<verse eid="MRK 10:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 10:6"/>But from the beginning of creation, ‘He made them male and female.’<verse eid="MRK 10:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 10:7"/>‘Because of this, a man will leave his father and mother,<verse eid="MRK 10:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 10:8"/>and the two will be one flesh.’ So then, they are no longer two, but one flesh.<verse eid="MRK 10:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 10:9"/>Therefore, what God joined together, let man not separate.”<verse eid="MRK 10:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 10:10"/>And in the house again, the disciples were asking him about this.<verse eid="MRK 10:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 10:11"/>And he says to them, “Whoever divorces his wife and marries another commits adultery against her.<verse eid="MRK 10:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 10:12"/>And if she, having divorced her husband, marries another, she commits adultery.”<verse eid="MRK 10:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 10:13"/>And they were bringing little children to him so that he might touch them, but the disciples rebuked them.<verse eid="MRK 10:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 10:14"/>But having seen this, Jesus was indignant and said to them, “Permit the little children to come to me, and do not forbid them, for of the ones such as these is the kingdom of God.<verse eid="MRK 10:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 10:15"/>Truly I say to you, whoever does not receive the kingdom of God as a little child will certainly not enter into it.”<verse eid="MRK 10:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 10:16"/>And having taken them into his arms, he blessed {them}, placing his hands on them.<verse eid="MRK 10:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 10:17"/>And he going out on the way, one, having run up to {him} and having knelt before him, was asking him, “Good Teacher, what should I do in order that I might inherit eternal life?”<verse eid="MRK 10:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 10:18"/>But Jesus said to him, “Why are you calling me good? No one {is} good except one—God.<verse eid="MRK 10:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 10:19"/>You know the commandments—do not kill, do not commit adultery, do not steal, do not testify falsely, do not defraud, honor your father and mother.”<verse eid="MRK 10:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 10:20"/>But he said to him, “Teacher, all these things I have kept from my youth.”<verse eid="MRK 10:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 10:21"/>But Jesus, having looked at him, loved him, and said to him, “One thing you lack; go, sell as much as you have, and give to the poor, and you will have treasure in heaven; and come, follow me.”<verse eid="MRK 10:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 10:22"/>But he, having become downcast at this word, went away being grieved, for he was having many possessions.<verse eid="MRK 10:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 10:23"/>And having looked around, Jesus says to his disciples, “How difficultly do the ones having riches enter into the kingdom of God!”<verse eid="MRK 10:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 10:24"/>And the disciples were astonished at his words, but again answering, Jesus says to them, “Children, how hard it is to enter into the kingdom of God!<verse eid="MRK 10:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 10:25"/>It is easier for a camel to pass through an eye of a needle than for a rich {person} to enter into the kingdom of God.”<verse eid="MRK 10:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 10:26"/>And they were greatly astonished, saying to him,  “And who is able to be saved?”<verse eid="MRK 10:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 10:27"/>Having looked at them, Jesus says, “With men {it is} impossible, but not with God. For all things {are} possible with God.”<verse eid="MRK 10:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 10:28"/>Peter began to speak to him, “Behold, we left everything and have followed you.”<verse eid="MRK 10:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 10:29"/>Jesus was saying, “Truly I say to you, there is no one who has left a house or brothers or sisters or a mother or a father or children or lands, for the sake of me and of the gospel,<verse eid="MRK 10:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 10:30"/>who will not receive 100 times {as much} now in this time: houses and brothers and sisters and mothers and children and lands with persecutions, and in the age that is coming, eternal life.<verse eid="MRK 10:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 10:31"/>But many first will be last, and last, first.”<verse eid="MRK 10:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 10:32"/>Now they were on the way, going up to Jerusalem, and Jesus was going ahead of them. And they were amazed, but the ones following behind were afraid. And having taken the Twelve aside again, he began to tell them the things being about to happen to him:<verse eid="MRK 10:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 10:33"/>“Behold, we are going up to Jerusalem, and the Son of Man will be handed over to the chief priests and the scribes, and they will condemn him to death and hand him over to the Gentiles.<verse eid="MRK 10:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 10:34"/>And they will mock him and spit on him and whip him and kill {him}, and after three days, he will rise.”<verse eid="MRK 10:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 10:35"/>And James and John, the sons of Zebedee, approach him, saying to him, “Teacher, we desire that whatever we ask you, you do for us.”<verse eid="MRK 10:35"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 10:36"/>And he said to them, “What do you desire {that} I do for you?”<verse eid="MRK 10:36"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 10:37"/>And they said to him, “Grant to us that we might sit in your glory, one at your right hand and one at your left hand.”<verse eid="MRK 10:37"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 10:38"/>But Jesus said to them, “You do not know what you are asking. Are you able to drink the cup which I drink or to be baptized with the baptism with which I am being baptized?”<verse eid="MRK 10:38"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 10:39"/>And they said to him, “We are able.” But Jesus said to them, “The cup that I drink, you will drink, and with the baptism with which I am being baptized, you will be baptized.<verse eid="MRK 10:39"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 10:40"/>But to sit at my right hand or at my left hand is not mine to give, but for whom it has been prepared.”<verse eid="MRK 10:40"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 10:41"/>And having heard this, the ten began to be very angry with James and John.<verse eid="MRK 10:41"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 10:42"/>And having summoned them, Jesus says to them, “You know that the ones considered rulers of the Gentiles lord it over them, and their great ones exercise authority over them.<verse eid="MRK 10:42"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 10:43"/>But it is not this way among you. Instead, whoever desires to become great among you will be your servant,<verse eid="MRK 10:43"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 10:44"/>and whoever desires to be first among you will be a slave of all.<verse eid="MRK 10:44"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 10:45"/>For even the Son of Man did not come to be served, but to serve and to give his life as a ransom in exchange for many.”<verse eid="MRK 10:45"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="46" style="v" sid="MRK 10:46"/>And they come into Jericho, and he and his disciples and a great crowd going out from Jericho, Bartimaeus, a blind beggar, son of Timaeus, was sitting beside the road.<verse eid="MRK 10:46"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="47" style="v" sid="MRK 10:47"/>And having heard that it is Jesus the Nazarene, he began to cry out and to say, “Son of David, Jesus, have mercy on me!”<verse eid="MRK 10:47"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="48" style="v" sid="MRK 10:48"/>And many were rebuking him, so that he would be silent, but he was crying out much more, “Son of David, have mercy on me!”<verse eid="MRK 10:48"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="49" style="v" sid="MRK 10:49"/>And having stood still, Jesus said, “Call him.” And they call the blind {man}, saying to him, “Take courage! Get up! He is calling you.”<verse eid="MRK 10:49"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="50" style="v" sid="MRK 10:50"/>And having thrown aside his coat, having sprung up, he came to Jesus.<verse eid="MRK 10:50"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="51" style="v" sid="MRK 10:51"/>And answering him, Jesus said, “What do you desire {that} I might do for you?” And the blind man said to him, “Rabbi, that I might see again.”<verse eid="MRK 10:51"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="52" style="v" sid="MRK 10:52"/>And Jesus said to him, “Go. Your faith has saved you.” And immediately he saw again, and he was following him on the road.<verse eid="MRK 10:52"/></para>
<chapter eid="MRK 10"/>
<chapter number="11" style="c" sid="MRK 11"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 11:1"/>And when they come near to Jerusalem, to Bethphage and Bethany, to the Mount of Olives, he sends out two of his disciples<verse eid="MRK 11:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 11:2"/>and says to them, “Go into the village opposite you, and immediately, entering into it, you will find a colt tied up, on which no one of men has yet sat. Untie it and bring it {here}.<verse eid="MRK 11:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 11:3"/>And if anyone says to you, ‘Why are you doing this?’ say, ‘The Lord has need of it and immediately he sends it back here.’”<verse eid="MRK 11:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 11:4"/>And they went away and found a colt having been tied up at a door outside on the street, and they untie it.<verse eid="MRK 11:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 11:5"/>And some of the ones standing there were saying to them, “What are you doing, untying the colt?”<verse eid="MRK 11:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 11:6"/>And they spoke to them just as Jesus told them, and they let them go.<verse eid="MRK 11:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 11:7"/>And they brought the colt to Jesus and throw their cloaks upon it, and he sat on it.<verse eid="MRK 11:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 11:8"/>And many spread their cloaks on the road, and others, branches, having cut {them} from the fields.<verse eid="MRK 11:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 11:9"/>Both the ones going before and the ones following were crying out, “Hosanna! Blessed is the one coming in the name of the Lord.<verse eid="MRK 11:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 11:10"/>Blessed is the coming kingdom of our father David! Hosanna in the highest!”<verse eid="MRK 11:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 11:11"/>And he entered into Jerusalem, into the temple; and having looked around at everything, the hour already being late, he went out to Bethany with the Twelve.<verse eid="MRK 11:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 11:12"/>And the next day, they having come out from Bethany, he was hungry.<verse eid="MRK 11:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 11:13"/>And having seen from far away a fig tree having leaves, he went, if perhaps he will find anything on it. And having come to it, he found nothing except leaves, for it was not the season of figs.<verse eid="MRK 11:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 11:14"/>And answering, he said to it, “May no one any longer eat fruit from you to eternity.” And his disciples heard {it}.<verse eid="MRK 11:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 11:15"/>And they come into Jerusalem. And having entered into the temple, he began to cast out the ones selling and the ones buying in the temple, and he overturned the tables of the money changers and the seats of the ones selling the doves,<verse eid="MRK 11:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 11:16"/>and he was not permitting that anyone would carry a container through the temple.<verse eid="MRK 11:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 11:17"/>And he was teaching them and saying, “Has it not been written, ‘My house will be called a house of prayer for all the nations’? But you have made it a ‘den of robbers.’”<verse eid="MRK 11:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 11:18"/>And the chief priests and the scribes heard this, and they were seeking how they might destroy him, for they were fearing him, for all the crowd was being amazed at his teaching.<verse eid="MRK 11:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 11:19"/>And when evening came, they were going out outside the city.<verse eid="MRK 11:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 11:20"/>And passing by in the morning, they saw the fig tree having withered from the roots.<verse eid="MRK 11:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 11:21"/>And having been reminded, Peter says to him, “Rabbi, behold! The fig tree that you cursed has withered.”<verse eid="MRK 11:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 11:22"/>And answering, Jesus says to them, “Have faith in God.<verse eid="MRK 11:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 11:23"/>Truly I say to you that whoever says to this mountain, ‘Be taken up and be thrown into the sea,’ and does not doubt in his heart, but believes that what he says is happening, it will be for him.<verse eid="MRK 11:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 11:24"/>Because of this, I say to you, everything, as much as you pray and request, believe that you have received {it}, and it will be to you.<verse eid="MRK 11:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 11:25"/>And when you stand praying, if you have something against anyone, forgive so that your Father in the heavens may also forgive you your trespasses.<verse eid="MRK 11:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 11:26"/>[But if you do not forgive, neither will your Father in the heavens forgive your trespasses.]”<verse eid="MRK 11:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 11:27"/>And they come to Jerusalem again, and he walking in the temple, the chief priests and the scribes and the elders come to him.<verse eid="MRK 11:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 11:28"/>And they were saying to him, “By what authority do you do these things, or who gave you this authority, so that you might do these things?”<verse eid="MRK 11:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 11:29"/>But Jesus said to them, “I also will ask you one word, and you answer me, and I will tell you by what authority I do these things.<verse eid="MRK 11:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 11:30"/>Was the baptism of John from heaven, or from men? Answer me.”<verse eid="MRK 11:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 11:31"/>And they were reasoning with each other, saying, “If we say, ‘From heaven,’ he will say, ‘For what {reason} then did you not believe him?’<verse eid="MRK 11:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 11:32"/>But should we say, ‘From men’?” (They were afraid of the crowd, for they all held that John really was a prophet.)<verse eid="MRK 11:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 11:33"/>And answering Jesus, they say, “We do not know.” And Jesus says to them, “Nor do I tell you by what authority I do these things.”<verse eid="MRK 11:33"/></para>
<chapter eid="MRK 11"/>
<chapter number="12" style="c" sid="MRK 12"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 12:1"/>And he began to speak to them in parables: “A man planted a vineyard and put a hedge around it and dug a pit for a winepress and built a watchtower and rented it out to farmers and went abroad.<verse eid="MRK 12:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 12:2"/>And at the time he sent a servant to the farmers so that he might receive from the farmers from the fruits of the vineyard.<verse eid="MRK 12:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 12:3"/>And having seized him, they beat {him}, and sent {him} away empty.<verse eid="MRK 12:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 12:4"/>And again he sent to them another servant, and that one they wounded in the head and treated shamefully.<verse eid="MRK 12:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 12:5"/>And he sent another, and that one they killed, and many others—beating some and killing others.<verse eid="MRK 12:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 12:6"/>Having one more, a beloved son, he sent him to them last, saying, ‘They will respect my son.’<verse eid="MRK 12:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 12:7"/>But those farmers said to each other, ‘This is the heir. Come, let us kill him, and the inheritance will be ours.’<verse eid="MRK 12:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 12:8"/>And having seized {him}, they killed him, and threw him out of the vineyard.<verse eid="MRK 12:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 12:9"/>What then will the lord of the vineyard do? He will come and destroy the farmers and will give the vineyard to others.<verse eid="MRK 12:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 12:10"/>And have you not read this scripture? ‘A stone that the builders rejected, this has become the head of the corner.<verse eid="MRK 12:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 12:11"/>This came about from the Lord, and it is marvelous in our eyes.’”<verse eid="MRK 12:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 12:12"/>And they were seeking to seize him, and they feared the crowd, for they knew that he spoke the parable against them. And having left him, they went away.<verse eid="MRK 12:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 12:13"/>And they send some of the Pharisees and the Herodians to him in order to trap him with a word.<verse eid="MRK 12:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 12:14"/>And having come, they say to him, “Teacher, we know that you are truthful, and it is not a concern to you about anyone, for you do not look at the face of men, but you teach the way of God on the basis of truth. Is it lawful to give a poll tax to Caesar, or not? Should we give, or should we not give?”<verse eid="MRK 12:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 12:15"/>But he, knowing their hypocrisy, said to them, “Why do you test me? Bring to me a denarius so that I might look at {it}.”<verse eid="MRK 12:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 12:16"/>And they brought {it}, and he says to them, “Whose image and inscription {is} this?” And they said to him, “Caesar’s.”<verse eid="MRK 12:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 12:17"/>And Jesus said to them, “The things of Caesar, give back to Caesar, and the things of God, to God.” And they were marveling at him.<verse eid="MRK 12:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 12:18"/>And Sadducees, who say there is no resurrection, come to him and were questioning him, saying,<verse eid="MRK 12:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 12:19"/>“Teacher, Moses wrote to us that if someone’s brother dies and leaves behind a wife but does not leave a child, his brother should take the wife and raise up seed for his brother.<verse eid="MRK 12:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 12:20"/>There were seven brothers, and the first took a wife and dying, did not leave seed,<verse eid="MRK 12:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 12:21"/>and the second took her and died, not having left seed, and the third likewise.<verse eid="MRK 12:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 12:22"/>And the seven did not leave seed. Last of all, the woman also died.<verse eid="MRK 12:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 12:23"/>In the resurrection, when they rise again, of which of them will she be a wife? For the seven had her {as} wife.”<verse eid="MRK 12:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 12:24"/>Jesus said to them, “Are you not being led astray because of this, not knowing the Scriptures nor the power of God?<verse eid="MRK 12:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 12:25"/>For when they rise from the dead, they neither marry nor are given in marriage, but they are like angels in the heavens.<verse eid="MRK 12:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 12:26"/>But concerning the dead, that they are raised, did you not read in the book of Moses, at the bush, how God spoke to him, saying, ‘I am the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob’?<verse eid="MRK 12:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 12:27"/>He is not a God of the dead, but of the living. You are being much deceived.”<verse eid="MRK 12:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 12:28"/>And one of the scribes, having come up, having heard them discussing this together, having seen that he answered them well, questioned him, “Which is the first commandment of all?”<verse eid="MRK 12:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 12:29"/>Jesus answered, “The first is, ‘Hear, Israel, the Lord our God is one Lord.<verse eid="MRK 12:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 12:30"/>And you will love the Lord your God from your whole heart, and from your whole soul, and from your whole mind, and from your whole strength.’<verse eid="MRK 12:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 12:31"/>The second {is} this, ‘You will love your neighbor as yourself.’ There is no other commandment greater than these.”<verse eid="MRK 12:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 12:32"/>And the scribe said to him, “Well, Teacher! On the basis of truth you have said that he is one, and there is no other besides him.<verse eid="MRK 12:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 12:33"/>And to love him from the whole heart and from the whole understanding and from the whole strength, and to love the neighbor as oneself is even more than all the whole burnt offerings and sacrifices.”<verse eid="MRK 12:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 12:34"/>And Jesus, having seen him, that he had answered wisely, said to him, “You are not far from the kingdom of God.” And no one any longer was daring to question him.<verse eid="MRK 12:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 12:35"/>And answering, Jesus, teaching in the temple, said, “How do the scribes say that the Christ is the son of David?<verse eid="MRK 12:35"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 12:36"/>David himself, in the Holy Spirit, said, ‘The Lord said to my Lord, “Sit at my right hand, until I put your enemies under your feet.”’<verse eid="MRK 12:36"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 12:37"/>David himself calls him ‘Lord,’ and how is he his son?” And a large crowd was listening to him gladly.<verse eid="MRK 12:37"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 12:38"/>And in his teaching, he was saying, “Watch out for the scribes, desiring to walk in long robes and greetings in the marketplaces<verse eid="MRK 12:38"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 12:39"/>and first seats in the synagogues and first places at the banquets,<verse eid="MRK 12:39"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 12:40"/>the ones devouring the houses of the widows, and as a pretext, offering long prayers. These will receive greater condemnation.”<verse eid="MRK 12:40"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 12:41"/>And having sat down opposite the treasury, he was watching how the crowd puts money into the treasury. And many rich were putting in much.<verse eid="MRK 12:41"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 12:42"/>And having come, one poor widow put in two lepta, which is a quadrans.<verse eid="MRK 12:42"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 12:43"/>And having summoned his disciples, he said to them, “Truly I say to you that this poor widow put in more than all the ones putting into the treasury.<verse eid="MRK 12:43"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 12:44"/>For all put in from the things abounding to them, but she, from her poverty, put in everything, as much as she had, her whole life.”<verse eid="MRK 12:44"/></para>
<chapter eid="MRK 12"/>
<chapter number="13" style="c" sid="MRK 13"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 13:1"/>And he going out from the temple, one of his disciples says to him, “Teacher, look! What manner of stones and what manner of buildings!”<verse eid="MRK 13:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 13:2"/>And Jesus said to him, “Do you see these great buildings? A stone upon a stone will certainly not be left here, which will certainly not be torn down.”<verse eid="MRK 13:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 13:3"/>And he sitting on the Mount of Olives opposite the temple, Peter and James and John and Andrew were asking him by themselves,<verse eid="MRK 13:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 13:4"/>“Tell us, when will these things be? And what {is} the sign when all these things are about to be completed?”<verse eid="MRK 13:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 13:5"/>Now Jesus began to say to them, “Be careful that no one leads you astray.<verse eid="MRK 13:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 13:6"/>Many will come in my name, saying, ‘I am he!’ and they will lead many astray.<verse eid="MRK 13:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 13:7"/>But when you hear of wars and rumors of wars, do not be troubled; it is necessary {for this} to happen, but the end {is} not yet.<verse eid="MRK 13:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 13:8"/>For nation will rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom. There will be earthquakes in various places; there will be famines. These things {are} the beginning of birth pains.<verse eid="MRK 13:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 13:9"/>But you, watch yourselves! They will hand you over to councils, and in synagogues you will be beaten, and you will be made to stand before governors and kings for my sake, for a testimony to them.<verse eid="MRK 13:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 13:10"/>And first, it is necessary for the gospel to be proclaimed to all the nations.<verse eid="MRK 13:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 13:11"/>And when they lead you away, handing {you} over, do not worry about what you will say. But whatever is given to you in that hour, speak that; for you are not the ones speaking, but the Holy Spirit.<verse eid="MRK 13:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 13:12"/>And brother will hand over brother to death, and a father, his child, and children will rise up against parents and put them to death.<verse eid="MRK 13:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 13:13"/>And you will be hated by all because of my name. But the one having endured to the end, this one will be saved.<verse eid="MRK 13:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 13:14"/>But when you see the abomination of desolation standing where he should not be” (let the one reading understand), “then let the ones in Judea flee to the mountains,<verse eid="MRK 13:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 13:15"/>but let the one on the housetop not go down nor go in to take anything from his house,<verse eid="MRK 13:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 13:16"/>and let the one in the field not turn back to the things behind to get his cloak.<verse eid="MRK 13:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 13:17"/>But woe to the ones having in the womb and to the ones nursing in those days!<verse eid="MRK 13:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 13:18"/>But pray that it might not happen in winter.<verse eid="MRK 13:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 13:19"/>For there will be in those days tribulation—such as this kind has not happened from the beginning of creation which God created until now and will certainly not happen.<verse eid="MRK 13:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 13:20"/>And if the Lord did not shorten the days, no flesh would be saved. But because of the elect whom he chose, he shortened the days.<verse eid="MRK 13:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 13:21"/>And then if anyone says to you, ‘Behold, here {is} the Christ! Behold, there!’ do not believe {it}.<verse eid="MRK 13:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 13:22"/>For false Christs and false prophets will be raised up and will give signs and wonders, to lead astray, if possible, the elect.<verse eid="MRK 13:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 13:23"/>But you, watch out! Behold, I have told you everything beforehand.<verse eid="MRK 13:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 13:24"/>But in those days, after that tribulation, the sun will be darkened, and the moon will not give its light;<verse eid="MRK 13:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 13:25"/>and the stars will be falling from heaven, and the powers in the heavens will be shaken.<verse eid="MRK 13:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 13:26"/>And then they will see the Son of Man coming in clouds with much power and glory.<verse eid="MRK 13:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 13:27"/>And then he will send the angels and he will gather together his elect from the four winds, from the end of the earth to the end of heaven.<verse eid="MRK 13:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 13:28"/>Now learn the parable from the fig tree: When its branch already becomes tender and it puts out leaves, you know that the summer is near.<verse eid="MRK 13:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 13:29"/>Thus also you, when you see these things happening, know that it is near, at the doors.<verse eid="MRK 13:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 13:30"/>Truly I say to you that this generation will certainly not pass away until all these things happen.<verse eid="MRK 13:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 13:31"/>The heaven and the earth will pass away, but my words will certainly not pass away.<verse eid="MRK 13:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 13:32"/>But concerning that day or the hour, no one knows, neither the angels in heaven, nor the Son, except the Father.<verse eid="MRK 13:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 13:33"/>Watch! Stay awake and pray, for you do not know when the time is.<verse eid="MRK 13:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 13:34"/>As a man on a journey, having left his house, and having given authority to his servants, to each his work, also he commanded the doorkeeper that he should stay alert;<verse eid="MRK 13:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 13:35"/>therefore, stay alert, because you do not know when the lord of the house is coming—whether evening or midnight or at rooster crowing or at morning—<verse eid="MRK 13:35"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 13:36"/>lest, having come suddenly, he might find you sleeping.<verse eid="MRK 13:36"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 13:37"/>But what I say to you I say to all: Stay alert!”<verse eid="MRK 13:37"/></para>
<chapter eid="MRK 13"/>
<chapter number="14" style="c" sid="MRK 14"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 14:1"/>Now the Passover and the Festival of Unleavened Bread was in two days, and the chief priests and the scribes were seeking how, having seized him by deceit, they might kill him.<verse eid="MRK 14:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 14:2"/>For they were saying, “Not during the festival, so that there will not be a riot of the people.”<verse eid="MRK 14:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 14:3"/>And he being in Bethany in the house of Simon the leper, he reclining to eat, a woman came, having an alabaster jar of very precious perfumed oil of pure nard. Having broken the jar, she poured it on his head.<verse eid="MRK 14:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 14:4"/>But there were some being very angry within themselves, “For what has this waste of the perfumed oil happened?<verse eid="MRK 14:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 14:5"/>For this perfumed oil was able to be sold for more than 300 denarii and given to the poor.” And they were scolding her.<verse eid="MRK 14:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 14:6"/>But Jesus said, “Leave her alone. Why are you causing trouble for her? She did a good work in me.<verse eid="MRK 14:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 14:7"/>For you always have the poor with you, and whenever you desire, you are able to do good to them, but you do not always have me.<verse eid="MRK 14:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 14:8"/>What she had, she did. She anticipated to anoint my body for burial.<verse eid="MRK 14:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 14:9"/>And truly I say to you, wherever the gospel is preached in the whole world, also what she did will be spoken in remembrance of her.”<verse eid="MRK 14:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 14:10"/>And Judas Iscariot, one of the Twelve, went away to the chief priests so that he might hand him over to them.<verse eid="MRK 14:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 14:11"/>And they, having heard {it}, rejoiced and promised to give him silver. And he was seeking how he might opportunely hand him over.<verse eid="MRK 14:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 14:12"/>And on the first day of the Festival of Unleavened Bread, when they were sacrificing the Passover, his disciples say to him, “Where do you want {that} we, having gone away, might prepare so that you may eat the Passover?”<verse eid="MRK 14:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 14:13"/>And he sends two of his disciples and says to them, “Go into the city, and a man carrying a pitcher of water will meet you. Follow him.<verse eid="MRK 14:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 14:14"/>And wherever he enters, say to the master of that house, ‘The Teacher says, “Where is my guest room where I may eat the Passover with my disciples?”’<verse eid="MRK 14:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 14:15"/>And he will show you a large upper room, furnished {and} ready, and prepare {it} for us there.”<verse eid="MRK 14:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 14:16"/>And the disciples left and went to the city, and they found {it} just as he said to them, and they prepared the Passover.<verse eid="MRK 14:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 14:17"/>And evening having come, he comes with the Twelve.<verse eid="MRK 14:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 14:18"/>And they reclining to eat, and eating, Jesus said, “Truly I say to you that one of you, one eating with me, will hand me over.”<verse eid="MRK 14:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 14:19"/>They began to be grieved and to say to him one by one, “Surely not I?”<verse eid="MRK 14:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 14:20"/>And he said to them, “{It is} one of the Twelve, the one dipping with me into the bowl.<verse eid="MRK 14:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 14:21"/>For the Son of Man departs just as it has been written about him, but woe to that man through whom the Son of Man is handed over! It would have been good for him if that man had not been born.”<verse eid="MRK 14:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 14:22"/>And they eating, having taken bread, having blessed, he broke {it} and gave {it} to them and said, “Take. This is my body.”<verse eid="MRK 14:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 14:23"/>And having taken a cup, having given thanks, he gave {it} to them, and they all drank from it.<verse eid="MRK 14:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 14:24"/>And he said to them, “This is my blood of the covenant, which is being poured out for many.<verse eid="MRK 14:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 14:25"/>Truly I say to you that I will certainly not any longer drink from the fruit of the vine until that day when I drink it new in the kingdom of God.”<verse eid="MRK 14:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 14:26"/>And having sung a hymn, they went out to the Mount of Olives.<verse eid="MRK 14:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 14:27"/>And Jesus says to them, “You all will be caused to stumble, for it is written, ‘I will strike the shepherd, and the sheep will be scattered.’<verse eid="MRK 14:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 14:28"/>But after I am raised up, I will go before you into Galilee.”<verse eid="MRK 14:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 14:29"/>But Peter was saying to him, “Even if all will be caused to stumble, yet not I.”<verse eid="MRK 14:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 14:30"/>And Jesus says to him, “Truly I say to you that today—this night—before a rooster crows twice, you will deny me three times.”<verse eid="MRK 14:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 14:31"/>But he was saying emphatically, “Even if it were necessary for me to die with you, I will certainly not deny you.” And they all also were speaking in the same manner.<verse eid="MRK 14:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 14:32"/>And they come to a place, the name of which {is} Gethsemane, and he says to his disciples, “Sit here while I pray.”<verse eid="MRK 14:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 14:33"/>And he takes along Peter and James and John with him and began to be distressed and greatly troubled.<verse eid="MRK 14:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 14:34"/>And he says to them, “My soul is very grieved, to death. Remain here and be alert.”<verse eid="MRK 14:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 14:35"/>And having gone a little farther, he fell to the ground and was praying that, if it is possible, the hour might pass from him.<verse eid="MRK 14:35"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 14:36"/>And he was saying, “Abba, Father, all things {are} possible for you. Remove this cup from me. But not what I will, but what you.”<verse eid="MRK 14:36"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 14:37"/>And he comes and finds them sleeping, and he says to Peter, “Simon, are you sleeping? Were you not able to be alert for one hour?<verse eid="MRK 14:37"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 14:38"/>Be alert and pray so that you do not enter into temptation. The spirit indeed {is} willing, but the flesh {is} weak.”<verse eid="MRK 14:38"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 14:39"/>And again, having gone away, he prayed, having said the same word.<verse eid="MRK 14:39"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 14:40"/>And having come again, he found them sleeping, for their eyes were weighed down, and they did not know what they might answer him.<verse eid="MRK 14:40"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 14:41"/>And he comes the third time and says to them, “Are you still sleeping and resting? It is enough! The hour has come. Behold, the Son of Man is handed over into the hands of the sinners.<verse eid="MRK 14:41"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 14:42"/>Get up, let us go. Behold, the one handing me over has come near.”<verse eid="MRK 14:42"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 14:43"/>And immediately, he still speaking, Judas, one of the Twelve, arrives, and a crowd with him with swords and clubs from the chief priests and the scribes and the elders.<verse eid="MRK 14:43"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 14:44"/>Now the one handing him over had given them a signal, saying, “Whomever I kiss is he. Seize him and lead {him} away securely.”<verse eid="MRK 14:44"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 14:45"/>And having come, immediately having approached him, he says, “Rabbi,” and he kissed him.<verse eid="MRK 14:45"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="46" style="v" sid="MRK 14:46"/>And they laid their hands on {him} and seized him.<verse eid="MRK 14:46"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="47" style="v" sid="MRK 14:47"/>But a certain one of the ones standing by, having drawn his sword, struck the servant of the high priest and cut off his ear.<verse eid="MRK 14:47"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="48" style="v" sid="MRK 14:48"/>And answering, Jesus said to them, “As against a robber have you come out with swords and clubs to seize me?<verse eid="MRK 14:48"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="49" style="v" sid="MRK 14:49"/>Every day I was with you in the temple teaching, and you did not seize me. But so that the Scriptures might be fulfilled.”<verse eid="MRK 14:49"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="50" style="v" sid="MRK 14:50"/>And having left him, they all fled.<verse eid="MRK 14:50"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="51" style="v" sid="MRK 14:51"/>And a certain young man was following him, wearing a linen garment over his naked body. And they seize him,<verse eid="MRK 14:51"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="52" style="v" sid="MRK 14:52"/>but he, having left behind the linen garment, fled naked.<verse eid="MRK 14:52"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="53" style="v" sid="MRK 14:53"/>And they led Jesus away to the high priest, and all the chief priests and the elders and the scribes gather together.<verse eid="MRK 14:53"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="54" style="v" sid="MRK 14:54"/>And Peter followed him from a distance, as far as inside into the courtyard of the high priest, and he was sitting with the officers and warming himself at the fire.<verse eid="MRK 14:54"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="55" style="v" sid="MRK 14:55"/>Now the chief priests and the entire Sanhedrin were seeking testimony against Jesus to put him to death, and they were not finding {any}.<verse eid="MRK 14:55"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="56" style="v" sid="MRK 14:56"/>For many were testifying falsely against him, and their testimonies were not the same.<verse eid="MRK 14:56"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="57" style="v" sid="MRK 14:57"/>And certain ones, having stood up, were testifying falsely against him, saying,<verse eid="MRK 14:57"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="58" style="v" sid="MRK 14:58"/>“We heard him saying, ‘I will destroy this temple made with hands, and in three days I will build another made without hands.’”<verse eid="MRK 14:58"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="59" style="v" sid="MRK 14:59"/>And not even in this manner was their testimony the same.<verse eid="MRK 14:59"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="60" style="v" sid="MRK 14:60"/>And having stood up in the midst, the high priest questioned Jesus, saying, “Do you not answer anything? What are these testifying against you?”<verse eid="MRK 14:60"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="61" style="v" sid="MRK 14:61"/>But he was silent and did not answer anything. Again the high priest was questioning him and says to him, “Are you the Christ, the Son of the Blessed One?”<verse eid="MRK 14:61"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="62" style="v" sid="MRK 14:62"/>And Jesus said, “I am; and you will see the Son of Man sitting at the right hand of power and coming with the clouds of heaven.”<verse eid="MRK 14:62"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="63" style="v" sid="MRK 14:63"/>But the high priest, having torn his tunics, says, “Why do we still have need of witnesses?<verse eid="MRK 14:63"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="64" style="v" sid="MRK 14:64"/>You have heard the blasphemy. What is evident to you?” And they all condemned him to be deserving of death.<verse eid="MRK 14:64"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="65" style="v" sid="MRK 14:65"/>And certain ones began to spit on him and to blindfold his face and to beat him and to say to him, “Prophesy!” And the officers received him with slaps.<verse eid="MRK 14:65"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="66" style="v" sid="MRK 14:66"/>And Peter being below in the courtyard, one of the servant girls of the high priest comes.<verse eid="MRK 14:66"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="67" style="v" sid="MRK 14:67"/>And having seen Peter warming himself, having looked closely at him, she says, “You  also were with the Nazarene, Jesus.”<verse eid="MRK 14:67"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="68" style="v" sid="MRK 14:68"/>But he denied {it}, saying, “Neither have I known, nor do I understand what you are saying.” And he went out, outside into the forecourt.<verse eid="MRK 14:68"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="69" style="v" sid="MRK 14:69"/>And the servant girl, having seen him {there}, began to say again to the ones standing around, “This one is from them!”<verse eid="MRK 14:69"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="70" style="v" sid="MRK 14:70"/>But he was denying {it} again. And after a little {while} the ones standing around again were saying to Peter, “Truly you are from them, for also you are a Galilean.”<verse eid="MRK 14:70"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="71" style="v" sid="MRK 14:71"/>And he began to curse and to swear, “I do not know this man whom you are talking about.”<verse eid="MRK 14:71"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="72" style="v" sid="MRK 14:72"/>And immediately a rooster crowed a second time, and Peter remembered the word that Jesus said to him: “Before a rooster crows twice, you will deny me three times,” and having broken down, he was weeping.<verse eid="MRK 14:72"/></para>
<chapter eid="MRK 14"/>
<chapter number="15" style="c" sid="MRK 15"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 15:1"/>And immediately in the morning, having made counsel, the chief priests with the elders and scribes and the entire Sanhedrin, having bound Jesus, led {him} away and handed {him} over to Pilate.<verse eid="MRK 15:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 15:2"/>And Pilate questioned him, “Are you the King of the Jews?” But he, answering him, says, “You say {it}.”<verse eid="MRK 15:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 15:3"/>And the chief priests were accusing him of many things.<verse eid="MRK 15:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 15:4"/>Now Pilate again was questioning him, saying, “Do you not answer anything? See how many things they are accusing you!”<verse eid="MRK 15:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 15:5"/>But Jesus no longer answered anything, so as to amaze Pilate.<verse eid="MRK 15:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 15:6"/>Now at the festival, he was releasing to them one prisoner whom they were requesting.<verse eid="MRK 15:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 15:7"/>Now there was the one called Barabbas, having been bound with the rebels, who had committed murder in the insurrection.<verse eid="MRK 15:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 15:8"/>And having come up, the crowd began to request just as he was doing for them.<verse eid="MRK 15:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 15:9"/>And Pilate answered them, saying, “Do you want {that} I would release to you the King of the Jews?”<verse eid="MRK 15:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 15:10"/>For he knew that the chief priests had handed him over because of envy.<verse eid="MRK 15:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 15:11"/>But the chief priests stirred up the crowd so that he would release Barabbas to them instead.<verse eid="MRK 15:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 15:12"/>And Pilate, answering again, was saying to them, “What therefore should I do {with the one} you call the King of the Jews?”<verse eid="MRK 15:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 15:13"/>But they cried out again, “Crucify him!”<verse eid="MRK 15:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 15:14"/>But Pilate was saying to them, “For what evil did he do?” But they cried out even more, “Crucify him.”<verse eid="MRK 15:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 15:15"/>Now Pilate, wanting to do {what} was pleasing to the crowd, released Barabbas to them and handed Jesus over, having flogged {him}, so that he might be crucified.<verse eid="MRK 15:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 15:16"/>Now the soldiers led him inside the courtyard (that is, the Praetorium) and call together the whole cohort<verse eid="MRK 15:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 15:17"/>and put on him a purple robe and place on him, having woven {it} together, a crown of thorns,<verse eid="MRK 15:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 15:18"/>and they began to greet him: “Rejoice, King of the Jews!”<verse eid="MRK 15:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 15:19"/>And they were striking his head with a reed and spitting on him, and bending the knee, they were bowing down to him.<verse eid="MRK 15:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 15:20"/>And when they had mocked him, they took the purple robe off him and put his robes on him and lead him out so that they might crucify him.<verse eid="MRK 15:20"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="21" style="v" sid="MRK 15:21"/>And they press into service a certain passerby, Simon, a Cyrenean (the father of Alexander and Rufus), coming from the country, so that he might carry his cross.<verse eid="MRK 15:21"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="22" style="v" sid="MRK 15:22"/>And they bring him to the place Golgotha, which is translated, “Place of a Skull.”<verse eid="MRK 15:22"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="23" style="v" sid="MRK 15:23"/>And they were giving to him wine having been mixed with myrrh, but he did not receive {it}.<verse eid="MRK 15:23"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="24" style="v" sid="MRK 15:24"/>And having crucified him, also they divide his garments, casting a lot for them, who would take what.<verse eid="MRK 15:24"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="25" style="v" sid="MRK 15:25"/>Now it was the third hour, and they crucified him.<verse eid="MRK 15:25"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="26" style="v" sid="MRK 15:26"/>And this was the inscription of his charge, having been written: “The King of the Jews.”<verse eid="MRK 15:26"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="27" style="v" sid="MRK 15:27"/>And they crucify two robbers with him, one at his right and one at his left.<verse eid="MRK 15:27"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="28" style="v" sid="MRK 15:28"/>[And the scripture was fulfilled that says, “And he was counted with lawless ones.”]<verse eid="MRK 15:28"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="29" style="v" sid="MRK 15:29"/>And the ones passing by were blaspheming him, wagging their heads and saying, “Aha! The one destroying the temple and rebuilding {it} in three days,<verse eid="MRK 15:29"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="30" style="v" sid="MRK 15:30"/>save yourself, having come down from the cross!”<verse eid="MRK 15:30"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="31" style="v" sid="MRK 15:31"/>Likewise also the chief priests, mocking {him} to each other with the scribes, were saying, “He saved others; he is not able to save himself.<verse eid="MRK 15:31"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="32" style="v" sid="MRK 15:32"/>Let the Christ, the King of Israel, come down now from the cross so that we might see and might believe,” and the ones having been crucified with him were reviling him.<verse eid="MRK 15:32"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="33" style="v" sid="MRK 15:33"/>And the sixth hour having come, darkness happened over the whole land until the ninth hour.<verse eid="MRK 15:33"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="34" style="v" sid="MRK 15:34"/>And at the ninth hour, Jesus cried out with a loud voice, “Eloi, Eloi, lema sabachthani?” which is translated, “My God, my God, why did you forsake me?”<verse eid="MRK 15:34"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="35" style="v" sid="MRK 15:35"/>And some of the ones having stood by, having heard {it}, were saying, “Behold, he calls Elijah.”<verse eid="MRK 15:35"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="36" style="v" sid="MRK 15:36"/>And someone, having run and having filled a sponge with vinegar, having put {it} around a reed, was giving {it} to him to drink, saying, “Leave {him}! Let us see if Elijah comes to take him down!”<verse eid="MRK 15:36"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="37" style="v" sid="MRK 15:37"/>And Jesus, having let out a loud voice, expired.<verse eid="MRK 15:37"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="38" style="v" sid="MRK 15:38"/>And the curtain of the temple was split in two from top to bottom.<verse eid="MRK 15:38"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="39" style="v" sid="MRK 15:39"/>Now the centurion, having stood by opposite him, having seen that he expired in this way, said, “Truly this man was a Son of God.”<verse eid="MRK 15:39"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="40" style="v" sid="MRK 15:40"/>Now there were also women watching from a distance, among whom {were} also Mary Magdalene and Mary the mother of James the little and of Joses and Salome,<verse eid="MRK 15:40"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="41" style="v" sid="MRK 15:41"/>who, when he was in Galilee, were following him and serving him, and many other {women} who had come up with him to Jerusalem.<verse eid="MRK 15:41"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="42" style="v" sid="MRK 15:42"/>And evening already having come, because it was the Day of Preparation, that is, the day before the Sabbath,<verse eid="MRK 15:42"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="43" style="v" sid="MRK 15:43"/>Joseph, the one from Arimathea, a respected member of the council who also himself was waiting for the kingdom of God, having come, having dared, entered in to Pilate and asked for the body of Jesus.<verse eid="MRK 15:43"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="44" style="v" sid="MRK 15:44"/>But Pilate marveled if he had already died, and having called the centurion, he questioned him, whether he had already died.<verse eid="MRK 15:44"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="45" style="v" sid="MRK 15:45"/>And having learned from the centurion, he gave the corpse to Joseph.<verse eid="MRK 15:45"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="46" style="v" sid="MRK 15:46"/>And having bought a linen cloth, having taken him down, he wrapped {him} in the linen cloth and put him in a tomb, which was having been cut from rock. And he rolled a stone against the door of the tomb.<verse eid="MRK 15:46"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="47" style="v" sid="MRK 15:47"/>Now Mary Magdalene and Mary the {mother} of Joses were watching where he had been put.<verse eid="MRK 15:47"/></para>
<chapter eid="MRK 15"/>
<chapter number="16" style="c" sid="MRK 16"/>
<para style="p"><verse number="1" style="v" sid="MRK 16:1"/>And the Sabbath having passed, Mary Magdalene and Mary the {mother} of James and Salome bought spices so that, having come, they might anoint him.<verse eid="MRK 16:1"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="2" style="v" sid="MRK 16:2"/>And very early on the first of the week, they arrive at the tomb, the sun having come up.<verse eid="MRK 16:2"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="3" style="v" sid="MRK 16:3"/>And they were saying to one another, “Who will roll away the stone for us from the door of the tomb?”<verse eid="MRK 16:3"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="4" style="v" sid="MRK 16:4"/>And having looked up, they see that the stone has been rolled away, for it was extremely large.<verse eid="MRK 16:4"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="5" style="v" sid="MRK 16:5"/>And having entered into the tomb, they saw a young man sitting on the right side, dressed in a white robe, and they were alarmed.<verse eid="MRK 16:5"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="6" style="v" sid="MRK 16:6"/>But he says to them, “Do not be alarmed. You seek Jesus, the Nazarene, the one having been crucified. He was raised up! He is not here. Behold, {this is} the place where they put him.<verse eid="MRK 16:6"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="7" style="v" sid="MRK 16:7"/>But go, say to his disciples and to Peter, ‘He is going before you to Galilee. There you will see him, just as he said to you.’”<verse eid="MRK 16:7"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="8" style="v" sid="MRK 16:8"/>And having gone out, they fled from the tomb, for trembling and amazement was gripping them. And they said nothing to anyone, for they were afraid.<verse eid="MRK 16:8"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="9" style="v" sid="MRK 16:9"/>[Now having arisen early in the morning on the first of the week, he appeared first to Mary Magdalene, from whom he had cast out seven demons.<verse eid="MRK 16:9"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="10" style="v" sid="MRK 16:10"/>That {one}, going, reported {it} to the ones having been with him, mourning and weeping.<verse eid="MRK 16:10"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="11" style="v" sid="MRK 16:11"/>And those {ones}, having heard that he lives and was seen by her, did not believe.<verse eid="MRK 16:11"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="12" style="v" sid="MRK 16:12"/>Now after these things, he appeared in a different form to two of them walking, going into the country.<verse eid="MRK 16:12"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="13" style="v" sid="MRK 16:13"/>And those {ones}, having gone away, reported {it} to the rest, but they did not believe those {ones}.<verse eid="MRK 16:13"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="14" style="v" sid="MRK 16:14"/>Now later, he appeared to the Eleven, they reclining to eat, and he rebuked their unbelief and hardness of heart, because they did not believe the ones having seen him, having been raised from the dead.<verse eid="MRK 16:14"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="15" style="v" sid="MRK 16:15"/>And he said to them, “Having gone into all the world, preach the gospel to all the creation.<verse eid="MRK 16:15"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="16" style="v" sid="MRK 16:16"/>The one having believed and having been baptized will be saved, but the one not having believed will be condemned.<verse eid="MRK 16:16"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="17" style="v" sid="MRK 16:17"/>Now these signs will accompany the ones having believed: In my name they will cast out demons; they will speak in new tongues;<verse eid="MRK 16:17"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="18" style="v" sid="MRK 16:18"/>they will pick up snakes, and if they drink anything deadly, it will certainly not hurt them; they will lay hands on the sick, and they will get well.”<verse eid="MRK 16:18"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="19" style="v" sid="MRK 16:19"/>After he spoke to them, the Lord Jesus was taken up into heaven and sat down at the right hand of God.<verse eid="MRK 16:19"/></para>
<para style="p"><verse number="20" style="v" sid="MRK 16:20"/>Now those {ones}, having gone out, preached everywhere, the Lord working with {them} and confirming the word through the accompanying signs. Amen.]<verse eid="MRK 16:20"/></para>
<chapter eid="MRK 16"/>
</usx>